[
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Enthalpy of an ideal gas is a function only of ___________.",
        "options": [
            "entropy",
            "internal energy",
            "temperature",
            "pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "temperature"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following is the most efficient thermodynamic cycle?",
        "options": [
            "Brayton",
            "Otto",
            "Carnot",
            "Diesel"
        ],
        "answer": "Carnot"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "What is the first law of thermodynamics?",
        "options": [
            "internal energy is due to molecular motions",
            "entropy of the universe is increased by irreversible processes",
            "energy can neither be crated nor destroyed",
            "heat energy cannot be completely transformed into work"
        ],
        "answer": "energy can neither be crated nor destroyed"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "An ideal gas is compressed isothermally, what is the enthalpy change?",
        "options": [
            "always negative",
            "always positive",
            "zero",
            "undefined"
        ],
        "answer": "zero"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Name the process that has no heat transfer.",
        "options": [
            "isothermal",
            "isobaric",
            "Polytropic",
            "adiabatic"
        ],
        "answer": "adiabatic"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "An ideal gas is compressed in a cylinder so well insulated that there is essentially no heat transfer. The temperature of the gas",
        "options": [
            "decreases",
            "increases",
            "remain constant",
            "is zero"
        ],
        "answer": "increases"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "What is the SI unit of pressure?",
        "options": [
            "kg/cm2",
            "dynes/cm2",
            "Pascal",
            "Psi"
        ],
        "answer": "Pascal"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The equation Cp = Cv + R applies to which of the following?",
        "options": [
            "enthalpy",
            "ideal gas",
            "two phase state",
            "all pure substances"
        ],
        "answer": "ideal gas"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "In the flow process, neglecting kinetic and potential energies, the integral of Vdp represents what?",
        "options": [
            "heat transfer",
            "flow energy",
            "enthalpy change",
            "shaft work"
        ],
        "answer": "shaft work"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Mechanical energy of pressure transformed into energy of heat.",
        "options": [
            "kinetic energy",
            "enthalpy",
            "heat exchanger",
            "heat of compression"
        ],
        "answer": "enthalpy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The theory of changing heat into mechanical work.",
        "options": [
            "thermodynamics",
            "kinematics",
            "inertia",
            "kinetics"
        ],
        "answer": "thermodynamics"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Average pressure on a surface when a changing pressure condition exist.",
        "options": [
            "back pressure",
            "partial pressure",
            "pressure drop",
            "mean effective pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "mean effective pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following cycles consists two isothermal and two constant volume processes?",
        "options": [
            "diesel cycle",
            "Ericson cycle",
            "Stirling cycle",
            "Otto cycle"
        ],
        "answer": "Stirling cycle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A control volume refers to what?",
        "options": [
            "a fixed region in space",
            "a reversible process",
            "an isolated system",
            "a specified mass"
        ],
        "answer": "a fixed region in space"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "In the polytropic process, PVn = constant, if the value of n is infinitely large, the process is",
        "options": [
            "isobaric",
            "isometric",
            "isothermal",
            "polytropic"
        ],
        "answer": "isometric"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "If the temperature is held constant and the pressure is increased beyond the saturation pressure, then the working medium must be:",
        "options": [
            "compressed liquid",
            "sub cooled liquid",
            "saturated vapour",
            "saturated liquid"
        ],
        "answer": "compressed liquid"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Is one whose temperature is below the saturation temperature corresponding to its pressure.",
        "options": [
            "super heated vapor",
            "wet vapor",
            "sub cooled liquid",
            "saturated liquid"
        ],
        "answer": "sub cooled liquid"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Number of molecules in a mole of any substance is a constant called __________.",
        "options": [
            "Rankine constant",
            "Avogadro’s number",
            "Otto cycle",
            "Thompson constant"
        ],
        "answer": "Avogadro’s number"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "If the pressure of a gas is constant the volume is directly proportional to the absolute temperature.",
        "options": [
            "Boyle’s law",
            "Joule’s law",
            "Charle’s law",
            "Kelvin’s law"
        ],
        "answer": "Charle’s law"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The number of protons in the nucleus of an atom or the number of electrons in the orbit of an atom.",
        "options": [
            "atomic volume",
            "atomic number",
            "atomic weight",
            "atomic mass"
        ],
        "answer": "atomic number"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "In a P-T diagram of a pure substance, the curve separating the solid phase from the liquid phase is:",
        "options": [
            "vaporization curve",
            "fusion curve",
            "boiling point",
            "sublimation point"
        ],
        "answer": "fusion curve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A water temperature of 18 °F in the water cooled condenser is equivalent in °C to ________.",
        "options": [
            "7.78",
            "10",
            "263.56",
            "-9.44"
        ],
        "answer": "10"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Form of energy associated with the kinetic energy of the random motion of large number of molecules.",
        "options": [
            "internal energy",
            "kinetic energy",
            "heat of fusion",
            "heat"
        ],
        "answer": "heat"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "If the temperature is held constant and the pressure is increased beyond the saturation pressure, then the working medium must be:",
        "options": [
            "saturated vapor",
            "compressed liquid",
            "saturated liquid",
            "sub cooled liquid"
        ],
        "answer": "compressed liquid"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Is the condition of pressure and temperature at which a liquid and its vapor are indistinguishable.",
        "options": [
            "critical point",
            "dew point",
            "absolute humidity",
            "relative humidity"
        ],
        "answer": "critical point"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "When a substance in gaseous state is below the critical temperature, it is called ___________.",
        "options": [
            "vapor",
            "cloud",
            "moisture",
            "steam"
        ],
        "answer": "vapor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Super heated vapour behaves",
        "options": [
            "just as gas",
            "just as steam",
            "just as ordinary vapor",
            "approximately as gas"
        ],
        "answer": "approximately as gas"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following provides the basis for measuring thermodynamic property of temperature?",
        "options": [
            "zeroth law of thermodynamics",
            "first law of thermodynamics",
            "second law of thermodynamics",
            "third law of thermodynamics"
        ],
        "answer": "zeroth law of thermodynamics"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following is commonly used as liquid absorbent?",
        "options": [
            "silica gel",
            "activated alumina",
            "ethylene glycol",
            "none of these"
        ],
        "answer": "ethylene glycol"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Mechanism designed to lower the temperature of air passing through it.",
        "options": [
            "air cooler",
            "air defense",
            "air spill ove",
            "air cycle"
        ],
        "answer": "air cooler"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A device for measuring the velocity of wind.",
        "options": [
            "aneroid barometer",
            "anemometer",
            "anemoscope",
            "anemograph"
        ],
        "answer": "anemometer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Heat normally flowing from a high temperature body to a low temperature body where in it is impossible to convert heat with out other effects.",
        "options": [
            "first law of thermodynamics",
            "second law of thermodynamics",
            "third law of thermodynamics",
            "zeroth law of thermodynamics"
        ],
        "answer": "second law of thermodynamics"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The temperature at which its vapour pressure is equal to the pressure exerted on the liquid.",
        "options": [
            "absolute humidity",
            "calorimeter",
            "boiling point",
            "thermal point"
        ],
        "answer": "boiling point"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A nozzle is used to",
        "options": [
            "increase velocity and decrease pressure",
            "decrease velocity as well as pressure",
            "increase velocity as well as pressure",
            "decrease velocity and increase pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "increase velocity and decrease pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The sum of energies of all the molecules in a system where energies appear in several complex form.",
        "options": [
            "kinetic energy",
            "potential energy",
            "internal energy",
            "frictional energy"
        ],
        "answer": "internal energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The total energy in a compressible or incompressible fluid flowing across any section in a pipeline is a function of",
        "options": [
            "pressure and velocity",
            "pressure, density and velocity",
            "pressure, density, velocity and viscosity",
            "flow energy, kinetic energy, height above datum and internal energy"
        ],
        "answer": "flow energy, kinetic energy, height above datum and internal energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The ratio of the density of a substance to the density of some standard substance.",
        "options": [
            "relative density",
            "specific gravity",
            "specific density",
            "relative gravity"
        ],
        "answer": "specific gravity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Is one whose pressure is higher than the saturation pressure corresponding to its temperature.",
        "options": [
            "compressed liquid",
            "saturated liquid",
            "saturated vapor",
            "super heated vapor"
        ],
        "answer": "compressed liquid"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The changing of solid directly to vapour without passing through the liquid state is called.",
        "options": [
            "evaporation",
            "vaporation",
            "sublimation",
            "condensation"
        ],
        "answer": "sublimation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Weight per unit volume is termed as __________.",
        "options": [
            "specific gravity",
            "density",
            "weight density",
            "specific volume"
        ],
        "answer": "weight density"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "What is the SI unit of force?",
        "options": [
            "pound",
            "Newton",
            "Kilogram",
            "Dyne"
        ],
        "answer": "Newton"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The volume of fluid passing a cross-section of steam in unit time.",
        "options": [
            "steady flow",
            "uniform flow",
            "discharge",
            "Dyne"
        ],
        "answer": "uniform flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "What equation applies in the first law of thermodynamics for an ideal gas in a reversible open steady-state system?",
        "options": [
            "Q – W = U2 - U1",
            "Q + VdP = H2 - H1",
            "Q – VdP = U2 - U1",
            "Q – PdV = H2 - H1"
        ],
        "answer": "Q + VdP = H2 - H1"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A pressure of 1 millibar is equivalent to",
        "options": [
            "1000 dynes/cm2",
            "1000 cm of Hg",
            "1000 psi",
            "1000 kg/cm2"
        ],
        "answer": "1000 dynes/cm2"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "When a system deviates infinitesimally from equilibrium at every instant of its state, it is undergoing:",
        "options": [
            "isobaric process",
            "quasi-static process",
            "isometric process",
            "cyclic process"
        ],
        "answer": "quasi-static process"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "What is the force which tends to draw a body toward the center about which it is rotating?",
        "options": [
            "centrifugal force",
            "centrifugal in motion",
            "centrifugal in advance",
            "centripetal force"
        ],
        "answer": "centripetal force"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "What is the process that has no heat transfer?",
        "options": [
            "reversible isometric",
            "isothermal",
            "polytropic",
            "adiabatic"
        ],
        "answer": "adiabatic"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the engine is used for fighter bombers?",
        "options": [
            "turbojet",
            "pulse jet",
            "rockets",
            "ramjet"
        ],
        "answer": "turbojet"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Exhaust gases from an engine posses:",
        "options": [
            "solar energy",
            "kinetic energy",
            "chemical energy",
            "stored energy"
        ],
        "answer": "kinetic energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "At critical point the latent enthalpy of vaporization is",
        "options": [
            "temperature dependent",
            "zero",
            "minimum",
            "maximum"
        ],
        "answer": "zero"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "What is the force which tends to draw a body toward the center about which it is rotating?",
        "options": [
            "centrifugal force",
            "centrifugal in motion",
            "centrifugal advance",
            "centripetal force"
        ],
        "answer": "centripetal force"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "When a system deviates infinitesimally from equilibrium at every instant of its state, it is undergoing",
        "options": [
            "isobaric process",
            "quasi – static process",
            "isometric process",
            "cyclic process"
        ],
        "answer": "quasi – static process"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A pressure of 1 millibar is equivalent to",
        "options": [
            "1000 dynes/cm2",
            "1000 cm of Hg",
            "1000 psi",
            "1000 kg/cm2"
        ],
        "answer": "1000 dynes/cm2"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Work done per unit charge when charged is moved from one point to another.",
        "options": [
            "equipotential surface",
            "potential at a point",
            "electro static point",
            "potential difference"
        ],
        "answer": "potential at a point"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "How many independent properties are required to completely fix the equilibrium state of a pure gaseous compound?",
        "options": [
            "1",
            "2",
            "3",
            "4"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following relations defines enthalpy?",
        "options": [
            "h = u + p/T",
            "h = u +pV",
            "h = u + p/V",
            "h = pV + T"
        ],
        "answer": "h = u +pV"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following is true for water at a reference temperature where enthalpy is zero?",
        "options": [
            "internal energy is negative",
            "entropy is non - zero",
            "specific volume is zero",
            "vapour pressure is zero"
        ],
        "answer": "internal energy is negative"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "On what plane is the Mollier diagram plotted",
        "options": [
            "p - V",
            "p - T",
            "h - s",
            "h - u"
        ],
        "answer": "h - s"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The compressibility factor z, is used for predicting the behaviour of non – ideal gasses. How is the compressibility factor defined relative to an ideal gas? (subscript c refers to critical value)",
        "options": [
            "z = P/Pc",
            "z = PV/RT",
            "z = T/TC",
            "z = (T/Tc)(Pc/P)"
        ],
        "answer": "z = PV/RT"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "How is the quality x of a liquid – vapour mixture defined?",
        "options": [
            "the fraction of the total volume that is saturated vapor",
            "the fraction of the total volume that is saturated liquid",
            "the fraction of the total mass that is saturated vapor",
            "the fraction of the total mass that is saturated liquid"
        ],
        "answer": "the fraction of the total mass that is saturated vapor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "What is the expression for heat of vaporization?",
        "options": [
            "hg",
            "hf",
            "hg - hf",
            "hf - hg"
        ],
        "answer": "C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "What is the value of the work done for a closed, reversible, isometric system?",
        "options": [
            "zero",
            "positive",
            "negative",
            "indeterminate"
        ],
        "answer": "zero"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "What is the equation for the done by a constant temperature system?",
        "options": [
            "W = mRT ln(V2 - V2)",
            "W = mRT (T2−T1) ln(V2/ V1)",
            "W = MRT ln(V2/V1)",
            "W = RT ln(V2/V1)"
        ],
        "answer": "W = MRT ln (V2/V1)"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "What is the true about the polytropic exponent  n for a perfect gas undergoing an isobaric process?",
        "options": [
            "n > 0",
            "n < 0",
            "n = ∞",
            "n = 0"
        ],
        "answer": "n = 0"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "How does an adiabatic process compare to an isentropic process?",
        "options": [
            "adiabatic: heat transfer = 0, isentropic: heat transfer = 0",
            "adiabatic: heat transfer = 0, isentropic: heat transfer = 0",
            "adiabatic: reversible, isentropic: not reversible",
            "both: heat transfer = 0; isentropic: reversible"
        ],
        "answer": "both: heat transfer = 0; isentropic: reversible"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "During an adiabatic, internally reversible process, what is true about the change in entropy?",
        "options": [
            "it is always zero",
            "it is always less than zero",
            "it is always greater than zero",
            "it is temperature - dependent"
        ],
        "answer": "it is always zero"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "For an irreversible process, what is true about the change in entropy of the system and surroundings?",
        "options": [
            "ds = dq dt",
            "ds = 0",
            "ds > 0",
            "ds < 0"
        ],
        "answer": "ds > 0"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "For which type of process does the equation dQ = Tds hold?",
        "options": [
            "irreversible",
            "reversible",
            "isobaric",
            "isothermal"
        ],
        "answer": "reversible"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following is true for any process?",
        "options": [
            "∆S (surrounding) + ∆ (system) > 0",
            "∆S (surrounding) + ∆ (system) < 0",
            "∆S (surrounding) + ∆ (system) ≤ 0",
            "∆S (surrounding) + ∆ (system) ≥ 0"
        ],
        "answer": "∆S (surrounding) + ∆ (system) ≥ 0"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following thermodynamic cycle is the most efficient?",
        "options": [
            "Brayton",
            "Rankine",
            "Carnot",
            "Otto"
        ],
        "answer": "Carnot"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The ideal reversible Carnot cycle involves four basic processes. What type of processes are they?",
        "options": [
            "all isothermal",
            "all adiabatic",
            "all isentropic",
            "two isothermal and two isentropic"
        ],
        "answer": "two isothermal and two isentropic"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "What is the temperature difference of the cycle if the entropy difference is ∆S, and the work done is W?",
        "options": [
            "W - ∆S",
            "W / ∆S",
            "∆S / W",
            "∆S - W"
        ],
        "answer": "W / ∆S"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following is not an advantage of a superheated, closed Rankine cycle over an open Rankine cycle?",
        "options": [
            "lower equipment cost",
            "increased efficiency",
            "increased turbine life",
            "increased boiler life"
        ],
        "answer": "increased boiler life"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following statements regarding Rankine cycle is not true?",
        "options": [
            "use of a condensable vapour in the cycle increases the efficiency of the cycle",
            "the temperatures at which energy is transferred to and from the working liquid are less separated than in a Carnot cycle,",
            "super heating increases the efficiency of a Rankine cycle",
            "in practical terms, the susceptibility of the engine materials to corrosion is not a key limitation on the operating efficiency."
        ],
        "answer": "in practical terms, the susceptibility of the engine materials to corrosion is not a key"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which one of the following is standard temperature and pressure (STP)",
        "options": [
            "0 K and 1atm pressure",
            "0 F and zero pressure",
            "32 F and zero pressure",
            "0 °C and 1atm pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "0 °C and 1atm pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A substance is oxidized when which of the following occurs?",
        "options": [
            "it turns red",
            "it loses electrons",
            "it gives off heat",
            "it absorbs energy"
        ],
        "answer": "it loses electrons"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following is not a unit of pressure?",
        "options": [
            "Pa",
            "kg/m−s",
            "bars",
            "kg/m2"
        ],
        "answer": "kg"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following is the definition of Joule?",
        "options": [
            "Newton meter",
            "kg-m/s^2",
            "unit of power",
            "rate of change of energy"
        ],
        "answer": "Newton meter"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following is the basis for Bernoulli’s law for fluid flow?",
        "options": [
            "the principle of conservation of mass",
            "the principle of conservation of energy",
            "the continuity equation",
            "Fourier’s law"
        ],
        "answer": "the principle of conservation of energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Equation of state for a single component can be any of the following except:",
        "options": [
            "the ideal gas law",
            "any relationship interrelating 3 or more state functions",
            "relationship mathematically interrelating thermodynamic properties of the material",
            "a mathematical expression defining a path between states"
        ],
        "answer": "a mathematical expression defining a path between states"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The state of a thermodynamic system is always defined by its:",
        "options": [
            "absolute temperature",
            "process",
            "properties",
            "temperature and pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "properties"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "In any non quasi – static thermodynamic process, the overall entropy of an isolated system will",
        "options": [
            "increase and then decrease",
            "decrease and then increase",
            "increase only",
            "decrease only"
        ],
        "answer": "increase only"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Entropy is the measure of :",
        "options": [
            "the internal energy of a gas",
            "the heat capacity of a substance",
            "randomness or disorder",
            "the change of enthalpy"
        ],
        "answer": "randomness or disorder"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following statements about entropy is false?",
        "options": [
            "entropy of mixture is greater than that of its components under the same condition",
            "an irreversible process increases entropy of the universe",
            "net entropy change in any closed cycle is zero",
            "entropy of a crystal at 0 °F is zero"
        ],
        "answer": "entropy of a crystal at 0 °F is zero"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Work or energy can be a function of all of the following except :",
        "options": [
            "force and distance",
            "power and time",
            "force and time",
            "temperature and entropy"
        ],
        "answer": "force and time"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Energy changes are represented by all except which one of the following:",
        "options": [
            "mCpdt",
            "- ∫VdP",
            "Tds - PdV",
            "dQ/T"
        ],
        "answer": "dQ"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "U + pV is a quantity called :",
        "options": [
            "shaft work",
            "entropy",
            "enthalpy",
            "internal energy"
        ],
        "answer": "enthalpy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "In flow process, neglecting KE and PE changes, ∫vdP represents which item below?",
        "options": [
            "heat transfer",
            "shaft work",
            "enthalpy change",
            "closed system work"
        ],
        "answer": "shaft work"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Power, may be expressed in units of",
        "options": [
            "ft - lb",
            "Kw - hr",
            "Btu",
            "Btu/hr"
        ],
        "answer": "Btu"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Equilibrium condition exist in all except which of the following?",
        "options": [
            "in reversible process",
            "in processes where driving forces are infinitesimals",
            "in a steady state flow process",
            "where nothing can occur without an effect on the system’s surrounding"
        ],
        "answer": "in a steady state flow process"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "In a closed system (with a moving boundary) which of the following represents work done during an isothermal process?",
        "options": [
            "W = 0",
            "W = P(V2−V1)",
            "W = P1V1ln(V2/V1)",
            "W = (P2V2−P1V1)/1−n"
        ],
        "answer": "W = P1V1lnV2"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A substance that exist, or is regarded as existing, as a continuoum characterized by a lo w resistance to flow and the tendency to assume the shape of its container.",
        "options": [
            "fluid",
            "atom",
            "molecule",
            "vapor"
        ],
        "answer": "fluid"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A substance that is homogenous in composition and homogenous and invariable in chemical aggregation.",
        "options": [
            "pure substance",
            "simple substance",
            "vapor",
            "water"
        ],
        "answer": "pure substance"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A substance whose state is defined  by variable intensive thermodynamic properties.",
        "options": [
            "pure substance",
            "simple substance",
            "vapor",
            "water"
        ],
        "answer": "simple substance"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A system in which there is no exchange of matter with the surrounding or mass does not cross its boundaries.",
        "options": [
            "open system",
            "closed system",
            "isolated system",
            "non flow system"
        ],
        "answer": "closed system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A system that is completely impervious to its surrounding or neither mass nor energy cross its boundaries.",
        "options": [
            "open system",
            "closed system",
            "isolated system",
            "non flow system"
        ],
        "answer": "isolated system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A system in which there is a flow of mass across its boundaries.",
        "options": [
            "open system",
            "closed system",
            "isolated system",
            "non flow system"
        ],
        "answer": "open system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The properties that are dependent upon the mass of the system and are total values such as total volume and total internal energy.",
        "options": [
            "intensive properties",
            "extensive properties",
            "specific properties",
            "state properties"
        ],
        "answer": "extensive properties"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The properties that are independent of the mass of the system such as temperature, pressure,   density and voltage.",
        "options": [
            "intensive properties",
            "extensive properties",
            "specific properties",
            "state properties"
        ],
        "answer": "intensive properties"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The properties for a unit mass and are intensive by definition such as specific volume.",
        "options": [
            "intensive properties",
            "extensive properties",
            "specific properties",
            "thermodynamic properties"
        ],
        "answer": "specific properties"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The condition as identified through the properties of the substance, generally defined by particular values of any two independent properties.",
        "options": [
            "state",
            "point",
            "process",
            "flow"
        ],
        "answer": "state"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The only base unit with a prefix kilo is",
        "options": [
            "kilogram",
            "kilo meter",
            "kilo Joule",
            "kilo Pascal"
        ],
        "answer": "kilogram"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The force gravity on a body.",
        "options": [
            "weight",
            "specific gravity",
            "attraction",
            "mass"
        ],
        "answer": "weight"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The mass per unit volume of any substance.",
        "options": [
            "density",
            "specific volume",
            "specific weight",
            "specific gravity"
        ],
        "answer": "density"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The force of gravity on unit volume is",
        "options": [
            "density",
            "specific volume",
            "specific weight",
            "specific gravity"
        ],
        "answer": "density"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The reciprocal of density is",
        "options": [
            "specific volume",
            "specific weight",
            "specific gravity",
            "specific heat"
        ],
        "answer": "specific volume"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Avogadro’s number a fundamental constant of nature, is the number of molecules in a gram – mole. This constant is",
        "options": [
            "6.05222x1023",
            "6.02252x1023",
            "6.20522x1023",
            "6.50222x1023"
        ],
        "answer": "6.02252x1023"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The ratio of the gas constant to Avogadro’s number is :",
        "options": [
            "Maxwell’s constant",
            "Boltzmann’z constant",
            "Napier’s constant",
            "Joule’s constant"
        ],
        "answer": "Boltzmann’z constant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The absolute zero on the Fahrenheit scale is at",
        "options": [
            "-459.7 °F",
            "459.7 °F",
            "-273.15 °C",
            "273.15 °C"
        ],
        "answer": "-459.7 °F"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Absolute temperature on the Fahrenheit scale are called:",
        "options": [
            "degrees Rankine",
            "degrees Kelvin",
            "absolute Fahrenheit",
            "absolute Celsius"
        ],
        "answer": "absolute Fahrenheit"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The absolute zero on the Celsius scale is at",
        "options": [
            "-459.7 °F",
            "459.7 °F",
            "-273.15 °C",
            "273.15 °C"
        ],
        "answer": "-273.15 °C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "What is the absolute temperature in Celsius scale?",
        "options": [
            "degrees Rankine",
            "degrees Kelvin",
            "absolute Fahrenheit",
            "absolute Celsius"
        ],
        "answer": "degrees Kelvin"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The Fahrenheit scale was introduced by Gabriel Fahrenheit of Amsterdam, Holland in what year?",
        "options": [
            "1592",
            "1742",
            "1730",
            "1720"
        ],
        "answer": "1720"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The centigrade scale was introduced by Celsius in what year?",
        "options": [
            "1542",
            "1740",
            "1730",
            "1720"
        ],
        "answer": "1740"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The national Bureau of standards uses, among others, the liquid – vapour equilibrium of hydrogen at",
        "options": [
            "-196 °C",
            "196 °C",
            "253 °C",
            "-253 °C"
        ],
        "answer": "-253 °C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The national Bureau of standards uses, among others, the liquid – vapour equilibrium of nitrogen at",
        "options": [
            "-196 °C",
            "196 °C",
            "253 °C",
            "-253 °C"
        ],
        "answer": "-196 °C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The liquid – vapour equilibrium of oxygen is at what temperature?",
        "options": [
            "197.82 °C",
            "-197.82 °C",
            "182.97 °C",
            "-182.97 °C"
        ],
        "answer": "-182.97 °C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The solid – liquid equilibrium of Mercury is at what temperature?",
        "options": [
            "38.87 °C",
            "-38.87 °C",
            "37.88 °C",
            "-37.88 °C"
        ],
        "answer": "-38.87 °C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The solid – liquid equilibrium of Tin is at what temperature?",
        "options": [
            "-38.87 °C",
            "38.87 °C",
            "231.9 °C",
            "-231.9 °C"
        ],
        "answer": "231.9 °C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The solid – liquid equilibrium of Zinc is what temperature?",
        "options": [
            "231.9 °C",
            "419.505 °C",
            "444.60 °C",
            "630.5 °C"
        ],
        "answer": "419.505 °C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The liquid – vapour equilibrium of sulphur is what temperature?",
        "options": [
            "231.9 °C",
            "419.505 °C",
            "444.60 °C",
            "630.5 °C"
        ],
        "answer": "444.60 °C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The solid liquid equilibrium of Antimony is what temperature?",
        "options": [
            "630.5 °C",
            "419.505 °C",
            "444.60 °C",
            "231.9 °C"
        ],
        "answer": "630.5 °C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The solid – liquid equilibrium of silver is at what temperature?",
        "options": [
            "630.5 °C",
            "960.8 °C",
            "1063 °C",
            "1774 °C"
        ],
        "answer": "960.8 °C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The solid – equilibrium of Gold is at what temperature?",
        "options": [
            "630.5 °C",
            "960.8 °C",
            "1063 °C",
            "1774 °C"
        ],
        "answer": "1063 °C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The solid – liquid equilibrium of Platinum is what temperature?",
        "options": [
            "630.5 °C",
            "960.8 °C",
            "1063 °C",
            "1774 °C"
        ],
        "answer": "1774 °C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The device that measures temperature by the electromotive force?",
        "options": [
            "thermometer",
            "thermo couple",
            "electro - thermometer",
            "thermo seebeck"
        ],
        "answer": "thermo couple"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The emf is a function of the temperature difference between the junction, a phenomenon called :",
        "options": [
            "seebeck effect",
            "stagnation effect",
            "Primming",
            "electromotive force"
        ],
        "answer": "seebeck effect"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The device that measure temperature by the electromotive force called thermo couple was discovered by :",
        "options": [
            "Galileo",
            "Fahrenheit",
            "Celsius",
            "Seebeck"
        ],
        "answer": "Seebeck"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "When two bodies, isolated from other environment, are in thermal equilibrium with a third body, the two are in thermal equilibrium with each other.",
        "options": [
            "Zeroth law of thermodynamics",
            "First law of thermodynamics",
            "Second law of thermodynamics",
            "Third law of thermodynamics"
        ],
        "answer": "Zeroth law of thermodynamics"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The total entropy of pure substances approaches zero as the absolute thermodynamic temperature approaches zero.",
        "options": [
            "Zeroth law of thermodynamics",
            "First law of thermodynamics",
            "Second law of thermodynamics",
            "Third law of thermodynamics"
        ],
        "answer": "Third law of thermodynamics"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "If any one more properties of a system change, the system is said to have undergone a _______.",
        "options": [
            "cycle",
            "process",
            "flow",
            "control"
        ],
        "answer": "process"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "When a certain mass of liquid in a particular state passes through a series of processes and returns to its initial state, it undergoes a :",
        "options": [
            "revolution",
            "rotation",
            "process",
            "cycle"
        ],
        "answer": "cycle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The term given to the collection of matter under consideration enclosed within a boundary.",
        "options": [
            "system",
            "matter",
            "environment",
            "atoms"
        ],
        "answer": "system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The region outside the boundary or the space and matter external to a system :",
        "options": [
            "ex – system",
            "surrounding",
            "matter",
            "extension"
        ],
        "answer": "surrounding"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The true pressure measured above a perfect vacuum.",
        "options": [
            "absolute pressure",
            "gage pressure",
            "atmospheric pressure",
            "vacuum pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "absolute pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The pressure measured from the level of atmospheric pressure by most pressure recording instrument like pressure gage and open – ended manometer.",
        "options": [
            "gage pressure",
            "atmospheric pressure",
            "atmospheric pressure",
            "absolute pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "gage pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The pressure obtained from barometric reading.",
        "options": [
            "absolute pressure",
            "gage pressure",
            "atmospheric pressure",
            "vacuum pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "atmospheric pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "It is a form of energy associated with the kinetic random motion of large number of molecules.",
        "options": [
            "internal energy",
            "kinetic energy",
            "heat",
            "enthalpy"
        ],
        "answer": "heat"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The heat needed to change the temperature of the body without changing its phase.",
        "options": [
            "latent heat",
            "sensible heat",
            "specific heat",
            "heat transfer"
        ],
        "answer": "sensible heat"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The heat needed by the body to change its phase without changing its temperature.",
        "options": [
            "latent heat",
            "sensible heat",
            "specific heat",
            "heat transfer"
        ],
        "answer": "latent heat"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The measure of randomness of the molecules of the substance.",
        "options": [
            "enthalpy",
            "internal energy",
            "entropy",
            "heat"
        ],
        "answer": "entropy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The heat energy transferred to a substance at a constant pressure process is :____________.",
        "options": [
            "enthalpy",
            "heat",
            "internal energy",
            "entropy"
        ],
        "answer": "enthalpy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "It is the energy stored within the body.",
        "options": [
            "enthalpy",
            "heat",
            "internal energy",
            "entropy"
        ],
        "answer": "internal energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A theoretically ideal gas which strictly follows Boyle’s law and Charle’s law of gases.",
        "options": [
            "universal gas",
            "perfect gas",
            "combined gas",
            "imperfect gas"
        ],
        "answer": "perfect gas"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "In a confined gas, if the absolute temperature is held constant, the volume is inversely proportional to the absolute pressure.",
        "options": [
            "Boyle’s law",
            "Charle’s law",
            "Daltoon’s law",
            "Avogadro’s law"
        ],
        "answer": "Boyle’s law"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "In a confined gas if the absolute pressure is held constant the volume is directly proportional to the absolute temperature.",
        "options": [
            "Boyle’s law",
            "Charle’s law",
            "Dalton’s law",
            "Avogadro’s law"
        ],
        "answer": "Charle’s law"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The pressure exerted in a vessel by a mixture of gases is equal to the sum of the pressures that each separate gas would exert if it alone occupied the whole volume of the vessel.",
        "options": [
            "Boyle’s law",
            "Charle’s law",
            "Dalton’s law",
            "Avogadro’s law"
        ],
        "answer": "Dalton’s law"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "At equal volume, at the same temperature and pressure conditions, the gases contain the same number of molecules.",
        "options": [
            "Boyle’s law",
            "Charle’s law",
            "Dalton’s law",
            "Avogadro’s law"
        ],
        "answer": "Avogadro’s law"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A process in which the system departs from equilibrium state only infinitesimally at every instant.",
        "options": [
            "reversible process",
            "irreversible process",
            "cyclic process",
            "Quasi – static process"
        ],
        "answer": "Quasi – static process"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A process which gives the same states/conditions after the system undergoes a series of processes :",
        "options": [
            "reversible process",
            "irreversible process",
            "cyclic process",
            "Quasi – static process"
        ],
        "answer": "cyclic process"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A thermodynamic system that generally serve as a heat source or heat sink for another system.",
        "options": [
            "combustion chamber",
            "heat reservoir",
            "heat engine",
            "Stirling engine"
        ],
        "answer": "heat reservoir"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A thermodynamic system that operates continuously with only energy (heat and work) crossing its boundaries; its boundaries are impervious to the flow of mass.",
        "options": [
            "heat engine",
            "steady flow work",
            "Stirling engine",
            "Ericson engine"
        ],
        "answer": "heat engine"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A surface that is impervious to heat is",
        "options": [
            "isothermal surface",
            "adiabatic surface",
            "isochoric surface",
            "isobaric surface"
        ],
        "answer": "adiabatic surface"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "One of the consequences of Einstein’s theory of relativity is that mass maybe converted into energy and energy into mass, the relation being given by the famous equation, E = mc2. What is the value of the speed of light c?",
        "options": [
            "2.7797x1010 cm/s",
            "2.9979x1010 cm/s",
            "1.7797x1010 cm/s",
            "2.9979x1010 cm/s"
        ],
        "answer": "2.9979x1010 cm/s"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "In the polytropic process we have pvn = constant, if the value of n is infinitely large, the process is called:",
        "options": [
            "constant volume process",
            "constant pressure process",
            "constant temperature process",
            "adiabatic process"
        ],
        "answer": "constant volume process"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The thermodynamic cycle used in a thermal power plant is :",
        "options": [
            "Ericson",
            "Brayton",
            "Joule",
            "Rankine"
        ],
        "answer": "Rankine"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "For the same heat input and same compression ratio :",
        "options": [
            "both Otto cycle and Diesel cycle are equally efficient",
            "Otto cycle is less efficient than diesel cycle",
            "efficiency depends mainly cn working substance",
            "none of the above is correct"
        ],
        "answer": "efficiency depends mainly cn working substance"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A heat exchange process where in the product of pressure and volume remains constant called:",
        "options": [
            "heat exchange process",
            "isentropic process",
            "throttling process",
            "hyperbolic process"
        ],
        "answer": "hyperbolic process"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following provides the basis for measuring thermodynamic property of temperature?",
        "options": [
            "Zeroth law of thermodynamics",
            "First law of thermodynamics",
            "Second law of thermodynamics",
            "Third law of thermodynamics"
        ],
        "answer": "Zeroth law of thermodynamics"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "1 watt .....",
        "options": [
            "1 Nm/s",
            "1 Nm/min",
            "1 Nm/hr",
            "1 kNm/hr"
        ],
        "answer": "1 Nm/s"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Under ideal conditions, isothermal, isobaric, isochoric and adiabatic processes are :",
        "options": [
            "dynamic processes",
            "stable processes",
            "quasi – static processes",
            "static processes"
        ],
        "answer": "quasi – static processes"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Isentropic flow is",
        "options": [
            "perfect gas flow",
            "irreversible adiabatic flow",
            "ideal fluid flow",
            "reversible adiabatic flow"
        ],
        "answer": "reversible adiabatic flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Exhaust gases from an engine posses",
        "options": [
            "solar energy",
            "kinetic energy",
            "chemical energy",
            "stored energy"
        ],
        "answer": "kinetic energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The extension and compression of a helical spring is an example of what process?",
        "options": [
            "isothermal cycle",
            "thermodynamic process",
            "adiabatic process",
            "reversible process"
        ],
        "answer": "reversible process"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "At critical point the latent enthalpy of vaporization is __________.",
        "options": [
            "dependent on temperature",
            "zero",
            "minimum",
            "maximum"
        ],
        "answer": "maximum"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following relations is not applicable in a free expansion process?",
        "options": [
            "heat supplied is zero",
            "heat rejected is zero",
            "work done is zero",
            "change in temperature is zero"
        ],
        "answer": "change in temperature is zero"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The triple point of a substance is the temperature and pressure at wich:",
        "options": [
            "the solid and liquid phases are in equilibrium",
            "the liquid and gaseous phase are in equilibrium",
            "the solid, liquid and gaseous phases are in equilibrium",
            "the solid does not melt, the liquid does not boil and the gas does not condense."
        ],
        "answer": "the solid does not melt, the liquid does not boil and the gas does not condense."
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "According to Clausius statement",
        "options": [
            "heat flows from hot substance to cold substance unaided",
            "heat cannot flow from cold substance to hot substance",
            "heat can flow from cold substance to hot substance with the aid of external work",
            "A and C"
        ],
        "answer": "A and C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A heat engine is supplied heat at rate of 30,000 J/s gives an output of 9kW. The thermal efficiency of the engine is __________.",
        "options": [
            "30%",
            "43%",
            "50%",
            "55%"
        ],
        "answer": "30%"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The RMS velocity of hydrogen gas at N.T.P. is approximately ____________.",
        "options": [
            "3838 m/s",
            "1839 m/s",
            "4839 m/s",
            "839 m/s"
        ],
        "answer": "1839 m/s"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following cycles has two isothermal and two constant volume processes?",
        "options": [
            "joule cycle",
            "diesel cycle",
            "Ericson cycle",
            "Stirling cycle"
        ],
        "answer": "Stirling cycle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "“ it is impossible to construct a heat engine that operates in a cycle and receives a given quantity of heat from a high temperature body and does an equal amount of work” The above statement is known as :",
        "options": [
            "Gay Lussac’s law",
            "Kinetic theory",
            "Kelvin – Planck’s law",
            "Joule – Thomson’s law"
        ],
        "answer": "Kelvin – Planck’s law"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "For steam nozzle, which of the following ratios with have the value less than unity ?",
        "options": [
            "(pressure at inlet) (pressure at outlet)",
            "specific volume at inlet/ (specific volume at outlet)",
            "temperature of steam at inlet/ (temperature of steam at outlet)",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "specific volume at inlet/ (specific volume at outlet)"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A bell – Coleman cycle is a reversed",
        "options": [
            "Stirling cycle",
            "Brayton cycle",
            "Joule cycle",
            "Carnot cycle"
        ],
        "answer": "Joule cycle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Ericson cycle consists of the following four processes:",
        "options": [
            "two isothermal and two constant volume",
            "two isothermal and two constant isentropic",
            "two isothermal and two constant pressure",
            "two adiabatic and two constant pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "two isothermal and two constant pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A steam nozzle changes",
        "options": [
            "kinetic energy into heat energy",
            "heat energy into potential energy",
            "potential energy into heat energy",
            "heat energy into kinetic energy"
        ],
        "answer": "heat energy into kinetic energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which is not correct for calculating air standard efficiency?",
        "options": [
            "all processes are reversible",
            "specific heat remains unchanged at all temperature",
            "no account of the mechanism of heat transfer is considered",
            "gases dissociate at higher temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "gases dissociate at higher temperature"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "According to Pettlier Thomson effect:",
        "options": [
            "it is impossible to construct a heat engine that operates in a cycle and receives a given quantity of heat from a high temperature body and does an equal amount of work",
            "it is impossible to construct a device that operates in a cycle and produces no effect other than the transfer of heat from a cooler body to hotter body",
            "when two dissimilar metals are heated at one end and cooled at other, e.m.f. that is developed is proportional to difference of temperature at two ends",
            "work can’t be converted into heat"
        ],
        "answer": "work can’t be converted into heat"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "In actual gasses the molecular collisions are :",
        "options": [
            "plastic",
            "elastic",
            "inelastic",
            "in plastic"
        ],
        "answer": "inelastic"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The Beattie – Bridgeman equation of state is quite accurate in case of :",
        "options": [
            "all pressures above atmospheric pressure",
            "densities less than about 0.8 times the critical density",
            "near critical temperature",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "densities less than about 0.8 times the critical density"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following statement about Van de Waals equation is correct?",
        "options": [
            "it is valid for all pressure and temperatures",
            "it represents a straight line on PV versus V plot",
            "it has three roots of identical value at the critical point",
            "the equation is valid for diatomic gases only"
        ],
        "answer": "it has three roots of identical value at the critical point"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The Clapeyron’s equation is applicable to :",
        "options": [
            "1 system in equilibrium",
            "a change of state",
            "a change of state when two phases are in equilibrium",
            "a change of state when water and water vapour are involved"
        ],
        "answer": "a change of state when two phases are in equilibrium"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The vapour pressure is related to the enthalpy of vaporization by the:",
        "options": [
            "Clausius – Claypeyron’s equation",
            "Dalton’s law",
            "Raoult’s law",
            "Maxwell’s law"
        ],
        "answer": "Clausius – Claypeyron’s equation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Solubility of a gas in a liquid at small concentration can be represented by which law?",
        "options": [
            "Henry’s law",
            "Clausius – Clapeyron’s equation",
            "Dalton’s law",
            "Roult’s law"
        ],
        "answer": "Henry’s law"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A compound pressure gauge is used to measure:",
        "options": [
            "complex pressure",
            "variable pressure",
            "average pressure",
            "positive and negative pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "positive and negative pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the engine is used for fighter bomber?",
        "options": [
            "turboprop",
            "turbojet",
            "ramjet",
            "pulsejet"
        ],
        "answer": "turbojet"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The thermal efficiency of gas – vapour cycle as compare to steam turbine or gas turbine",
        "options": [
            "greater than",
            "less than",
            "not comparable",
            "equal"
        ],
        "answer": "greater than"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The process in which heat energy is transferred to thermal energy storage device is known as:",
        "options": [
            "adiabatic",
            "regeneration",
            "inter cooling",
            "heat transfer"
        ],
        "answer": "regeneration"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The absolute zero in Celsius scale is:",
        "options": [
            "100",
            "0",
            "-273",
            "273"
        ],
        "answer": "-273"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "What is the temperature when water and vapour are in equilibrium with the atmospheric pressure?",
        "options": [
            "ice point",
            "steam point",
            "critical point",
            "freezing point"
        ],
        "answer": "steam point"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The temperature of a pure substance at a temperature of absolute zero is:",
        "options": [
            "unity",
            "zero",
            "infinity",
            "100"
        ],
        "answer": "zero"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "When the number of reheat stages in a reheat cycle is increased, the average temperature:",
        "options": [
            "increases",
            "decreases",
            "is constant",
            "is zero"
        ],
        "answer": "increases"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A temperature measurement in an ordinary thermometer which has constant specific humidity.",
        "options": [
            "critical temperature",
            "dew point temperature",
            "dry bulb temperature",
            "wet bulb temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "dew point temperature"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "In a closed vessel, when vaporization takes place, the temperature rises. Due to the rising temperature, the pressure increases until an equilibrium is established between the temperature and pressure. The temperature of equilibrium is called:",
        "options": [
            "dew point",
            "ice point",
            "superheated temperature",
            "boiling point"
        ],
        "answer": "boiling point"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "When hot soup was served in a cup during dinner an engineer was so eager to drink it. Since it was hot, he added cubes of ice to cool the soup and stirred it. He noticed that dew starts to form at the outermost surface of the cup. What is this temperature equal to?",
        "options": [
            "super heated temperature",
            "equal to zero",
            "standard temperature",
            "equal to air’s dew point temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "equal to air’s dew point temperature"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Is the measure of the energy that is no longer available to perform useful work within the current environment.",
        "options": [
            "absolute entropy",
            "absolute enthalpy",
            "fugacity",
            "molar value"
        ],
        "answer": "absolute entropy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A graph of enthalpy versus entropy for steam",
        "options": [
            "Mollier diagram",
            "Moody diagram",
            "steam table",
            "Maxwell diagram"
        ],
        "answer": "Mollier diagram"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The reaction of inertia in an accelerated body is called",
        "options": [
            "kinetic reaction",
            "endothermic reaction",
            "kinematic reaction",
            "dynamic reaction"
        ],
        "answer": "kinetic reaction"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A Mollier chart of thermodynamic properties is shown in which of the following diagrams?",
        "options": [
            "T – S diagram",
            "P – V diagram",
            "h – S diagram",
            "p – h diagram"
        ],
        "answer": "h – S diagram"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The following are included in the first law of thermodynamics for closed system EXCEPT:",
        "options": [
            "heat transferred in and of the system",
            "work done by or on the system",
            "internal energy",
            "kinetic energy"
        ],
        "answer": "internal energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "All processes below are irreversible except one. Which one?",
        "options": [
            "magnetization with hysteresis",
            "elastic tension and release of steel bar",
            "in elastic deformation",
            "heat conduction"
        ],
        "answer": "elastic tension and release of steel bar"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The combination of condition that best describe thermodynamic process is given by which of following? I. Has successive states through which the system passes II. When reversed leaves no change in the system III. When reversed leaves no change in the system or the surroundings IV. States are passes through so quickly that the surroundings do not change",
        "options": [
            "I and II",
            "I and III",
            "I and IV",
            "I and only"
        ],
        "answer": "I and only"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The sum of the energies of all the molecules in a system where energies appear in several complex forms is the:",
        "options": [
            "kinetic energy",
            "potential energy",
            "internal energy",
            "frictional energy"
        ],
        "answer": "internal energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The Carnot refrigeration cycle includes all of the following processes except:",
        "options": [
            "isentropic expansion",
            "isothermal heating",
            "isenthalpic expansion",
            "isentropic compression"
        ],
        "answer": "isenthalpic expansion"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The maximum possible work that can be obtained cycle operating between two reservoirs is found from:",
        "options": [
            "processes irreversibility",
            "availability",
            "Carnot cycle",
            "reversible work"
        ],
        "answer": "Carnot cycle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The following factors are necessary to define thermodynamic cycle except:",
        "options": [
            "the working substance",
            "high and low temperature reservoirs",
            "the time it takes to complete the cycle",
            "the means of doing work on the system"
        ],
        "answer": "the time it takes to complete the cycle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "All of the following terms included in the second for open system except",
        "options": [
            "shaft work",
            "flow work",
            "internal energy",
            "average work"
        ],
        "answer": "average work"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The following terms are included in the first law of thermodynamics for open systems except",
        "options": [
            "heat transferred in and out of the system",
            "work done by or in the system",
            "magnetic system",
            "internal system"
        ],
        "answer": "magnetic system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The following terms are included in the first law of thermodynamics for closed systems except",
        "options": [
            "heat transferred in and out of the system",
            "work done by or on the system",
            "internal energy",
            "kinetic energy"
        ],
        "answer": "kinetic energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following statements about a path function is not true?",
        "options": [
            "on a p – v diagram, it can represent work done",
            "on a t – s diagram, it can represent heat transferred",
            "it is dependent on the path between states of thermodynamic equilibrium",
            "it represents values of p, v, t, and s between states that are path functions"
        ],
        "answer": "it represents values of p, v, t, and s between states that are path functions"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A constant pressure thermodynamic process obeys:",
        "options": [
            "Boyle’s law",
            "Charle’s law",
            "Amagat’s law",
            "Dalto’s law"
        ],
        "answer": "Amagat’s law"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The first and second law of thermodynamics are:",
        "options": [
            "continuity equations",
            "momentum equations",
            "energy equations",
            "equations of state"
        ],
        "answer": "energy equations"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Represents the temperature an ideal gas will attain when it is brought to rest adiabatically.",
        "options": [
            "absolute zero temperature",
            "stagnation temperature",
            "boiling temperature",
            "critical temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "stagnation temperature"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Gauge pressure and absolute pressure differ from each other by:",
        "options": [
            "the system units",
            "atmospheric pressure",
            "the size of the gauge",
            "nothing they mean the same thing"
        ],
        "answer": "atmospheric pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Each of the following are correct values of standard atmospheric pressure except.",
        "options": [
            "1,000 atm",
            "14,962 psi",
            "760 torr",
            "1013 mm Hg"
        ],
        "answer": "1013 mm Hg"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "All of the following are properties of an ideal gas except:",
        "options": [
            "density",
            "pressure",
            "viscosity",
            "temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "viscosity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following is not the universal as constant?",
        "options": [
            "1545 ft – lb / lb mol - °R",
            "8.314 J/ mol. K",
            "8314 KJ / mol. K",
            "8.314 kJ / k mol. K"
        ],
        "answer": "8314 KJ / mol. K"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The following are all commonly quoted values of standard temperatures and pressure except:",
        "options": [
            "32 °F and 14.696 psia",
            "273.15 K and 101.325 kPa",
            "0 °C and 760 mm Hg",
            "0 °F and 29.92 in Hg"
        ],
        "answer": "0 °F and 29.92 in Hg"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The variation of pressure in an isobaric processes is:",
        "options": [
            "linear with temperature",
            "described by the perfect gas law",
            "inversely proportional to temperature",
            "zero"
        ],
        "answer": "zero"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "For fluid flow, the enthalpy is the sum of internal energy and __________.",
        "options": [
            "entropy",
            "work flow",
            "pressure",
            "temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "work flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A thermodynamic processes whose deviation from equilibrium is infinitesimal at all times is _________.",
        "options": [
            "reversible",
            "isentropic",
            "in quasi - equilibrium",
            "isenthalpic"
        ],
        "answer": "in quasi - equilibrium"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which thermodynamic property best describes the molecular activity of a substance?",
        "options": [
            "enthalpy",
            "entropy",
            "internal energy",
            "External energy"
        ],
        "answer": "internal energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Stagnation enthalpy represents the enthalpy of a fluid when, it is brought to rest__________.",
        "options": [
            "isometrically",
            "adiabatically",
            "isothermally",
            "disobarically"
        ],
        "answer": "adiabatically"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "During stagnation process, the kinetic energy of a fluid is converted to enthalpy which results in an:",
        "options": [
            "increase in the fluid specific volume",
            "increase in the fluid pressure",
            "increase in the fluid temperature and pressure",
            "increase in the fluid temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "increase in the fluid temperature and pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The properties of fluid at the stagnation in state are called_____________.",
        "options": [
            "stagnation property",
            "stagnation phase",
            "stagnation state",
            "stagnation vapor"
        ],
        "answer": "stagnation state"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "All of the following are thermodynamic properties except___________.",
        "options": [
            "temperature",
            "pressure",
            "density",
            "modulus of elasticity"
        ],
        "answer": "modulus of elasticity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A liquid boils when its vapor pressure equals",
        "options": [
            "the gage pressure",
            "the critical pressure",
            "the ambient pressure",
            "one standard atmosphere"
        ],
        "answer": "the ambient pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A system composed of ice and water at 0 °C is said be: _____________.",
        "options": [
            "a multiphase material",
            "in thermodynamic equilibrium",
            "in thermal equilibrium",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "all of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The heat of fusion of a pure substance is:",
        "options": [
            "the change in phase from solid to gas",
            "the change in phase from liquid to gas",
            "the energy released in a chemical reaction",
            "the energy required to melt the substance"
        ],
        "answer": "the energy required to melt the substance"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The heat of vaporization involves the change in enthalpy due to:",
        "options": [
            "the change in phase from solid to gas",
            "the change in phase from liquid to gas",
            "the energy released in a chemical reaction",
            "the change in phase from solid to liquid"
        ],
        "answer": "the change in phase from liquid to gas"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The heat of sublimation involves the change in enthalpy due to _____________.",
        "options": [
            "the change in phase from solid to gas",
            "the change in phase from liquid to gas",
            "the energy released in a chemical reaction",
            "the change in phase from solid to liquid"
        ],
        "answer": "the change in phase from solid to gas"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A specific property",
        "options": [
            "defines a specific variable (eg . temperature)",
            "is independent of mass",
            "is an extensive property multiplied by mass",
            "is independent of the phase of the substance"
        ],
        "answer": "defines a specific variable (eg . temperature)"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A material’s specific heat can be defined as:",
        "options": [
            "the ratio of heat required to change temperature of mass by change in temperature",
            "being different for constant pressure constant temperature processes",
            "a function of temperature",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "all of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "If a substance temperature is less than its saturated temperature, the substance is:",
        "options": [
            "sub cooled liquid",
            "wet vapor",
            "saturated vapor",
            "superheated vapor"
        ],
        "answer": "sub cooled liquid"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "If a substance temperature is equal to its saturated temperature, the substance is a_________.",
        "options": [
            "sub cooled liquid",
            "wet vapor",
            "saturated vapor",
            "superheated vapor"
        ],
        "answer": "saturated vapor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "If a substance’s temperature is greater than saturation temperature, the substance is a _________.",
        "options": [
            "sub cooled liquid",
            "wet vapor",
            "saturated vapor",
            "superheated vapor"
        ],
        "answer": "superheated vapor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Critical properties refer to",
        "options": [
            "extremely important properties, such as temperature and pressure",
            "heat required for phase change and important for energy production",
            "property values where liquid and gas phase are indistinguishable",
            "properties having to do with equilibrium conditions,  such as the Gibbs and Helmholtz functions."
        ],
        "answer": "property values where liquid and gas phase are indistinguishable"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "For a saturated vapour, the relationship between temperature and pressure is given by:",
        "options": [
            "the perfect gas law",
            "Van der Waal’s equation",
            "the steam table",
            "a Viral equation of state"
        ],
        "answer": "the steam table"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Properties of a superheated vapor are given by",
        "options": [
            "the perfect gas law",
            "a super heated table",
            "a one to one relationship, such as the properties of saturated steam",
            "a viral equation of state"
        ],
        "answer": "a super heated table"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Properties of non – reacting gas mixtures are given",
        "options": [
            "geometric weighting",
            "volumetric weighting",
            "volumetric weighting for molecular weight, density, and geometric weighting for all properties except entropy",
            "arithmetic average"
        ],
        "answer": "volumetric weighting for molecular weight, density, and geometric weighting for all"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The relationship between the total pressure mixture of non – reacting gases and their partial volume given by:",
        "options": [
            "gravimetric functions",
            "volumetric functions",
            "Dalton’s law",
            "mole fractions"
        ],
        "answer": "volumetric functions"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The relationship between the total pressure mixture of non – reacting gases and the pressure constituent is given by:",
        "options": [
            "gravimetric functions",
            "volumetric functions",
            "Dalton’s law",
            "mole fractions"
        ],
        "answer": "Dalton’s law"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following is the best definition of enthalpy?",
        "options": [
            "the ratio of heat added to the temperature increases in a system",
            "the amount of useful energy in a system",
            "the amount of energy no longer available to the system",
            "the heat required to cause a complete conversion between two phases at a constant temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "the amount of useful energy in a system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following statements is not true for real gases?",
        "options": [
            "molecules occupy a volume not negligible in comparison to the total volume of gas",
            "real gases are subjected to attractive forces between molecules ( eg. Van der Waal’s forces)",
            "the law of corresponding states may be used for real gases",
            "real gases are found only rarely in nature"
        ],
        "answer": "real gases are found only rarely in nature"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The stagnation state is called the isentropic stagnation state when the stagnation process is:",
        "options": [
            "reversible as well dynamic",
            "isotropic",
            "adiabatic",
            "reversible as well as adiabatic"
        ],
        "answer": "reversible as well as adiabatic"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The entropy of fluid remains constant process?",
        "options": [
            "polytropic stagnation process",
            "unsteady stagnation process",
            "combustion process",
            "isentropic stagnation process"
        ],
        "answer": "isentropic stagnation process"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "All the following processes are irreversible except",
        "options": [
            "stirring a viscous fluid",
            "an isentropic deceleration of a moving per fluid",
            "an unrestrained expansion of a gas",
            "phase changes"
        ],
        "answer": "an isentropic deceleration of a moving per fluid"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "All of the following processes are irreversible except:",
        "options": [
            "chemical reactions",
            "diffusion",
            "current flow through an electrical resistance",
            "an isentropic compression of a perfect gas."
        ],
        "answer": "an isentropic compression of a perfect gas."
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "All of the following processes are irreversible except:",
        "options": [
            "magnetization with hysteresis",
            "elastic tension and release of steel bar",
            "in elastic deformation",
            "heat conduction"
        ],
        "answer": "elastic tension and release of steel bar"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following state(s) is/are necessary for a system to be in thermodynamic equilibrium?",
        "options": [
            "chemical equilibrium",
            "thermal equilibrium",
            "mechanical equilibrium",
            "chemical, mechanical, and thermal equilibrium"
        ],
        "answer": "chemical, mechanical, and thermal equilibrium"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Adiabatic heat transfer with in a vapour cycle refers to:",
        "options": [
            "heat t transfer that is atmospheric but not reversible",
            "the transfer of energy from one stream to another in a heat exchanger so that the energy of the input streams equals the energy of the output streams",
            "heat transfer that is reversible but not isentropic",
            "there is no such thing as adiabatic heat transfer"
        ],
        "answer": "the transfer of energy from one stream to another in a heat exchanger so that the"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The work done in an adiabatic process in a system.",
        "options": [
            "is equal to the change in total energy in a closed system",
            "is equal to the total net heat transfer plus the entropy change",
            "is equal to the change in total energy of closed system plus the entropy change",
            "is equal to the change in total energy of closed system plus net heat transfer"
        ],
        "answer": "is equal to the change in total energy of closed system plus net heat transfer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Based on the first law of thermodynamics, which of the following is wrong?",
        "options": [
            "the heat transfer equals the work plus energy change",
            "the heat transfer Carnot exceed the work done",
            "the net transfer equal the net work of the cycle",
            "the net heat transfer equals the change if no work is done"
        ],
        "answer": "the heat transfer Carnot exceed the work done"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Assuming real process, the net entropy change in the universe",
        "options": [
            "must be calculated",
            "equals zero",
            "is negative",
            "is positive"
        ],
        "answer": "is positive"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following types of flow meters is most accurate?",
        "options": [
            "Venturi tube",
            "Pilot tube",
            "Flow nozzle",
            "Foam type"
        ],
        "answer": "Pilot tube"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "What is referred by control volume?",
        "options": [
            "an isolated system",
            "closed system",
            "fixed region in space",
            "reversible process only"
        ],
        "answer": "fixed region in space"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "What is the most efficient thermodynamic cycle?",
        "options": [
            "Carnot",
            "Diesel",
            "Rankine",
            "Brayton"
        ],
        "answer": "Carnot"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "How do you treat a statement that is considered scientific law?",
        "options": [
            "we postulate to be true",
            "accept as summary of experimental observation",
            "we generally observed to be true",
            "believe to be derived from mathematical theorem"
        ],
        "answer": "accept as summary of experimental observation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "An instrument commonly used in most research and engineering laboratories because it is small and fast among the other thermometers",
        "options": [
            "mercury thermometer",
            "liquid – in – glass thermometer",
            "gas thermometer",
            "thermo couple"
        ],
        "answer": "thermo couple"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "In an actual gases, the molecular collisions are",
        "options": [
            "plastic",
            "elastic",
            "inelastic",
            "in plastic"
        ],
        "answer": "inelastic"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following is used in thermal power plant?",
        "options": [
            "Brayton",
            "Reversed Carnot",
            "Rankine",
            "Otto"
        ],
        "answer": "Rankine"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The elongation and compression of a helical spring is an example of",
        "options": [
            "irreversible process",
            "reversible process",
            "isothermal process",
            "adiabatic process"
        ],
        "answer": "reversible process"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Otto cycle consists of",
        "options": [
            "two isentropic and two constant volume processes",
            "two isentropic and two constant pressure processes",
            "two adiabatic and two isothermal processes",
            "two isothermal and two constant volume processes"
        ],
        "answer": "two isentropic and two constant volume processes"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Brayton cycle ha",
        "options": [
            "two isentropic and two constant pressure processes",
            "two isentropic and two constant pressure processes",
            "one constant pressure, one constant volume and two adiabatic processes",
            "two isothermal, one constant volume and one constant pressure processes"
        ],
        "answer": "two isentropic and two constant pressure processes"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A Bell – Coleman cycle is a reversed",
        "options": [
            "Stirling cycle",
            "Joule cycle",
            "Carnot cycle",
            "Otto cycle"
        ],
        "answer": "Joule cycle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A steam nozzle changes",
        "options": [
            "kinetic energy into heat energy",
            "heat energy into potential energy",
            "heat energy into kinetic energy",
            "potential energy into heat energy"
        ],
        "answer": "heat energy into kinetic energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The pilot tube is a device used for measurement of",
        "options": [
            "pressure",
            "flow",
            "velocity",
            "discharge"
        ],
        "answer": "velocity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The continuity equation is applicable to",
        "options": [
            "Viscous, un viscous fluids",
            "Compressibility of fluids",
            "conservation of mass",
            "Steady, un steady flow"
        ],
        "answer": "conservation of mass"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The work done by a force of R Newtons moving in a distance of L meters is converted entirely into kinetic energy and expressed by the equation:",
        "options": [
            "RL = 2MV 2",
            "RL = 2MV",
            "RL = 1 2",
            "RL = 1 2 MV 2 MV"
        ],
        "answer": "RL = 1"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Gas being heated at constant volume is undergoes the process of",
        "options": [
            "isentropic",
            "adiabatic",
            "isometric",
            "isobaric"
        ],
        "answer": "isometric"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Dew point is defined as",
        "options": [
            "the temperature to which the air must be cooled constant pressure to produce saturation",
            "the where the pressure and temperature lines meet",
            "the temperature which dew is formed in the air",
            "the pressure which dew is formed in the air"
        ],
        "answer": "the temperature to which the air must be cooled constant pressure to produce"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "PAST ME BOARD QUESSTION What do you call the changing of an atom of element into an atom of different element with a different atomic mass?",
        "options": [
            "atomization",
            "atomic transmutation",
            "atomic pile",
            "atomic energy"
        ],
        "answer": "atomic transmutation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "What do you call the weight of the column of air above the earth’s surface?",
        "options": [
            "air pressure",
            "aerostatic pressure",
            "wind pressure",
            "atmospheric pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "atmospheric pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "What keeps the moisture from passing through the system?",
        "options": [
            "dehydrator",
            "aerator",
            "trap",
            "humidifier"
        ],
        "answer": "dehydrator"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "What condition exists in an adiabatic throttling process?",
        "options": [
            "enthalpy is variable",
            "enthalpy is constant",
            "entropy is constant",
            "specific volume is constant"
        ],
        "answer": "enthalpy is constant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The specific gravity of a substance is the ratio of density to the density of:",
        "options": [
            "mercury",
            "gas",
            "air",
            "water"
        ],
        "answer": "water"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A compound pressure gauge is used to measure:",
        "options": [
            "complex pressure",
            "variable pressure",
            "compound pressure",
            "positive and negative pressures"
        ],
        "answer": "positive and negative pressures"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Isentropic flow is",
        "options": [
            "perfect gas flow",
            "ideal fluid flow",
            "frictionless reversible flow",
            "reversible adiabatic flow"
        ],
        "answer": "reversible adiabatic flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Under ideal conditions, isothermal, isobaric, and adiabatic processes are:",
        "options": [
            "dynamic processes",
            "stable processes",
            "quasi – static processes",
            "static processes"
        ],
        "answer": "quasi – static processes"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "One watt is:",
        "options": [
            "1 N.m s",
            "1 N.m min",
            "1 N.m hr",
            "1 kN.m s"
        ],
        "answer": "1 N.m"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A temperature above which a given gas cannot be liquefied:",
        "options": [
            "Cyrogenic temperature",
            "Vaporization temperature",
            "Absolute temperature",
            "Critical temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "Critical temperature"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The effectiveness of a body as a thermal radiator on given temperature",
        "options": [
            "absorptivity",
            "emissivity",
            "conductibility",
            "reflectivity"
        ],
        "answer": "emissivity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following occurs in a reversible polytropic process?",
        "options": [
            "enthalpy remains constant",
            "internal energy does not change",
            "some heat transfer occurs",
            "entropy remains constant"
        ],
        "answer": "some heat transfer occurs"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "ME BOARD Oct. 1997 The instrument used to measure atmospheric pressure is:",
        "options": [
            "rota meter",
            "manometer",
            "Venturi",
            "Barometer"
        ],
        "answer": "Barometer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "ME BOARD Oct. 1997 A pneumatic tool is generally powered by",
        "options": [
            "water",
            "electricity",
            "steam",
            "air"
        ],
        "answer": "air"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following gasses can be used to measure the lowest temperature?",
        "options": [
            "nitrogen",
            "helium",
            "oxygen",
            "hydrogen"
        ],
        "answer": "helium"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The triple point of the substance is the temperature and pressure at which:",
        "options": [
            "the solid and liquid phases are in equilibrium",
            "the solid and gaseous phase are in equilibrium",
            "the solid, liquid and gaseous phases are in equilibrium",
            "the solid does not melt, the liquid does not boil and the gas does not condense"
        ],
        "answer": "the solid does not melt, the liquid does not boil and the gas does not condense"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following relations is not applicable in free expansion processes?",
        "options": [
            "heat rejected is zero",
            "work done is zero",
            "change in temperature is zero",
            "heat supplied is zero"
        ],
        "answer": "change in temperature is zero"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Ericson cycle has",
        "options": [
            "two isothermal and two constant pressure processes",
            "two isothermal and two constant volume processes",
            "two isothermal and two constant entropy processes",
            "two adiabatic, one constant volume and constant pressure processes"
        ],
        "answer": "two isothermal and two constant pressure processes"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A Stirling cycle has",
        "options": [
            "two adiabatic and two constant volume processes",
            "two adiabatic and two constant pressure processes",
            "two isothermal and two constant pressure processes",
            "two isothermal and two constant volume processes"
        ],
        "answer": "two isothermal and two constant volume processes"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The temperature of the fluid flowing under pressure through a pipe is usually measured by:",
        "options": [
            "a glass thermometer",
            "an electric resistance thermometer",
            "a thermocouple",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "all of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Specific heat capacity is an SI derived unit described as",
        "options": [
            "J kg",
            "W mK",
            "kJ kgK",
            "J m"
        ],
        "answer": "kJ"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following is mathematically a thermodynamic property?",
        "options": [
            "a point function",
            "discontinuous",
            "a path function",
            "exact differential"
        ],
        "answer": "a point function"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "PAST ME BOARD QUSTION When the expansion or compression of gas takes place “without transfer of heat” to or form the gas, the property is called:",
        "options": [
            "reversible",
            "adiabatic",
            "polytropic",
            "isothermal"
        ],
        "answer": "adiabatic"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Another name for the liquid valve is:",
        "options": [
            "Freon valve",
            "Shut – off valve",
            "King valve",
            "Master valve"
        ],
        "answer": "King valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A liquid whose temperature is lower than the saturation temperature corresponding to the existing pressure:",
        "options": [
            "sub cooled liquid",
            "saturated liquid",
            "pure liquid",
            "compressed liquid"
        ],
        "answer": "sub cooled liquid"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The law that states “entropy of all perfect crystalline solids is zero at absolute zero temperature:",
        "options": [
            "zeroth law of thermodynamics",
            "First law of thermodynamics",
            "Second law of thermodynamics",
            "Third law of thermodynamics"
        ],
        "answer": "Third law of thermodynamics"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "What should be the temperature of both water and steam whenever they are present together?",
        "options": [
            "saturation temperature for the existing pressure",
            "boiling point of water at 101.325 kPa",
            "superheated temperature",
            "one hundred degrees centigrade"
        ],
        "answer": "saturation temperature for the existing pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A manometer is an instrument that is used to measure:",
        "options": [
            "air pressure",
            "heat radiation",
            "condensation water level",
            "air volume"
        ],
        "answer": "air pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "What is the area under the curve of temperature of entropy diagram?",
        "options": [
            "volume",
            "heat",
            "work",
            "entropy"
        ],
        "answer": "heat"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "What do bodies at temperature above absolute emit?",
        "options": [
            "energy",
            "heat of convection",
            "thermal radiation",
            "heat of compression"
        ],
        "answer": "thermal radiation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "In the absence of any irreversibilities, a thermo generator, a device that incorporates both thermo electric effects, will have the efficiency of a/an",
        "options": [
            "Carnot cycle",
            "Otto cycle",
            "Diesel cycle",
            "Rankine cycle"
        ],
        "answer": "Carnot cycle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Both Stirling and Ericson engines are",
        "options": [
            "internal combustion engine",
            "external combustion engines",
            "Carnot engines",
            "Brayton engines"
        ],
        "answer": "external combustion engines"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Nozzles does not involve any work interaction. The fluid through this device experiences:",
        "options": [
            "no change in potential energy",
            "no change in kinetic energy",
            "no change in enthalpy",
            "vacuum"
        ],
        "answer": "no change in potential energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "If the actual kinetic energy of a nozzle is Ka and Ki is the maximum value that can be attained by an isentropic expansion from an initial to final state, then the efficiency of the nozzle is: A.Ki Ka B.Ka−Ki Ka",
        "options": [
            "Ka−Ki Ki",
            "Ka Ki"
        ],
        "answer": "Ka"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The convergent section of a nozzle increased velocity of the flow of the gas. What does it to do pressure?",
        "options": [
            "pressure becomes constant",
            "pressure equals the velocity",
            "it increases the pressure",
            "it decreases the pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "it decreases the pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "In a closed vessel, when vaporization takes place the temperature rise, Due to the rising temperature, pressure increases until an equilibrium is establish between the temperature and pressure temperature of equilibrium is called__________.",
        "options": [
            "dew point",
            "ice point",
            "boiling point",
            "superheated temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "boiling point"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "At steam point, the temperature of water and its vapour at standard pressure are:",
        "options": [
            "extremes or maximum",
            "unity",
            "in equilibrium",
            "undefined"
        ],
        "answer": "in equilibrium"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "When hot soup was served in a cup during dinner, an engineer was so eager to drink it. Since it was hot, he added cubes of ice to cool the soup and stirred it. He noticed that dew starts to form on the outermost surface of the cup. He wanted to check the temperature of the outermost surface of the cup. What is this temperature equal to?",
        "options": [
            "superheated temperature",
            "equal to zero",
            "standard temperature",
            "equal to air’s dew point temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "equal to air’s dew point temperature"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "What do you call a conversion technology that yields electricity straight from sunlight without the aid of a working substance like gas or steam without the use of any mechanical cycle?",
        "options": [
            "power conversion",
            "Stirling cycle conversion",
            "solar thermal conversion",
            "photovoltaic – energy"
        ],
        "answer": "photovoltaic – energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following property of liquid extend resistance to angular or shear deformation:",
        "options": [
            "specific gravity",
            "specific weight",
            "viscosity",
            "density"
        ],
        "answer": "viscosity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "What is the pressure at the exit of a draft tube turbine?",
        "options": [
            "below atmospheric",
            "above atmospheric",
            "atmospheric",
            "vacuum"
        ],
        "answer": "atmospheric"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "When changes in kinetic energy  of a compressed are negligible or insignificant, the work input to adiabatic compressor is__________.",
        "options": [
            "negligible",
            "zero",
            "infinity",
            "equal to change in enthalpy"
        ],
        "answer": "equal to change in enthalpy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "What is the area under the curve of a pressure- volume diagram?",
        "options": [
            "non flow work",
            "steady flow work",
            "heat",
            "power"
        ],
        "answer": "non flow work"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "In Stirling and Ericson cycle, regeneration can",
        "options": [
            "increase efficiency",
            "decrease efficiency",
            "control efficiency",
            "limit efficiency"
        ],
        "answer": "increase efficiency"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The first law of thermodynamics is based on which of the following principles?",
        "options": [
            "conservation of mass",
            "enthalpy – entropy relationship",
            "entropy – temperature relationship",
            "conservation of energy"
        ],
        "answer": "conservation of energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "In two – phase system, 30% moisture means",
        "options": [
            "70% liquid and 30% vapor",
            "70% vapor and 30% liquid",
            "30% liquid and 100% vapor",
            "30% vapor and 100% liquid"
        ],
        "answer": "70% vapor and 30% liquid"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "ME BOARD Apr. 2002 At 101.325 kPa, the boiling point of water is 100 °C, the pressure is decreased, the boiling temperature will:",
        "options": [
            "increase",
            "decrease",
            "remain the same",
            "drop to zero"
        ],
        "answer": "decrease"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following is equivalent to 1 hp in Btu/hr",
        "options": [
            "778 B.2545",
            "746",
            "3.41"
        ],
        "answer": "B"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "What is the pressure above zero?",
        "options": [
            "gage pressure",
            "absolute pressure",
            "vacuum pressure",
            "atmospheric pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "gage pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "One Newton – meter is equal to",
        "options": [
            "1 Joule",
            "1 Btu",
            "1 Calorie",
            "1 Ergs"
        ],
        "answer": "1 Joule"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following is the instrument used to measure fluid velocity?",
        "options": [
            "pilot tube",
            "Orsat apparatus",
            "anemometer",
            "viscosimeter"
        ],
        "answer": "pilot tube"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Cryogenic temperature ranges from:",
        "options": [
            "-150 °F to -359 °F",
            "-250 °F to -459 °F",
            "-100 °F to -300 °F",
            "-200 °F to -400 °F"
        ],
        "answer": "-250 °F to -459 °F"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Steam at 2 kPa is saturated at 17.5°C. In waht _________ will the state be at 40°C if the pressure is 2.0 kPa.",
        "options": [
            "superheated",
            "saturated",
            "sub cooled",
            "supersaturated"
        ],
        "answer": "superheated"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Acceleration is proportional to force.",
        "options": [
            "Newton’s law",
            "Archimedes principle",
            "law of gravitation",
            "theory of relativity"
        ],
        "answer": "Newton’s law"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "Which of the following could be defined as simple push or pull",
        "options": [
            "power",
            "inertia",
            "work",
            "force"
        ],
        "answer": "force"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "The true pressure measured above a perfect vacuum is:",
        "options": [
            "absolute pressure",
            "atmospheric pressure",
            "gauge pressure",
            "vacuum pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "absolute pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "If an initial volume of an ideal gas is compressed to one – half its original volume and to twice its original temperature, the pressure:",
        "options": [
            "doubles",
            "halves",
            "quadruples",
            "triples"
        ],
        "answer": "quadruples"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "When the expansion or compression of gas takes place without transfer of heat to or from the gas, the process is called:",
        "options": [
            "isometric process",
            "isothermal process",
            "isobaric process",
            "adiabatic process"
        ],
        "answer": "adiabatic process"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "A body radiates heat proportional to the fourth power of its absolute temperature:",
        "options": [
            "Stefan – Boltzmann law",
            "Planck’s law",
            "Kirchhoff’s law",
            "Maxwell’s law"
        ],
        "answer": "Stefan – Boltzmann law"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "All substances emit radiation, the quantity and quality of which depends upon the absolute temperature are the properties of the material, composing the radiation body.",
        "options": [
            "Stefan – Boltzmann law",
            "Planck’s law",
            "Kirchhoff’s law",
            "Maxwell’s law"
        ],
        "answer": "Planck’s law"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 1,
        "question": "For body in thermal equilibrium with the environment, the ratio of total emissive power to the absorptivity is constant at any temperature.",
        "options": [
            "Stefan – Boltzmann law",
            "Planck’s law",
            "Kirchhoff’s law",
            "Maxwell’s law"
        ],
        "answer": "Kirchhoff’s law"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Which is not a viscosity rating?",
        "options": [
            "redwood",
            "SSU",
            "Centi poise",
            "entropy degrees API"
        ],
        "answer": "entropy degrees API"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Percent excess air is the difference between the air actually supplied and the theoretically required divided by:",
        "options": [
            "the theoretically air supplied",
            "the actually air supplied",
            "the deficiency of air supplied",
            "the sufficient air supplied"
        ],
        "answer": "the theoretically air supplied"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "What is the apparatus used in the analysis of combustible gases?",
        "options": [
            "calorimeter differential",
            "calorimeter gas",
            "calorimetry",
            "calorimeter"
        ],
        "answer": "calorimeter"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "PAST ME BOARD QUETION Percent excess air is the difference between the actually supplied and the theoretical air divided by:",
        "options": [
            "the sufficient air supplied",
            "the deficiency air supplied",
            "the actually air supplied",
            "the theoretically air supplied"
        ],
        "answer": "the theoretically air supplied"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The viscosity of most commercially available petroleum lubricating oil changes rapidly above",
        "options": [
            "120 °F",
            "180 °F",
            "150 °F",
            "130 °F"
        ],
        "answer": "180 °F"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "When 1 mol carbon combines with 1 mol oxygen",
        "options": [
            "2 mols carbon dioxide",
            "1 mol carbon dioxide",
            "1 mol carbon and 1 mol carbon dioxide",
            "1 mol carbon dioxide"
        ],
        "answer": "1 mol carbon dioxide"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "What are the immediate undesirable products from the petroleum based lubricating oil when subjected to high pressure and temperature?",
        "options": [
            "gums, resins and acids",
            "sulphur",
            "Soots and ashes",
            "Carbon residue"
        ],
        "answer": "gums, resins and acids"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "What kind of boding do common gases that exist in free state as diatomic molecules experiences?",
        "options": [
            "ionic bonds",
            "covalent bonds",
            "metallic bonds",
            "nuclear bonds"
        ],
        "answer": "covalent bonds"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "An Orsat’s apparatus is used for",
        "options": [
            "volumetric analysis of the flue gas",
            "gravimetric analysis of the flue gas",
            "smoke density analysis of the flue gas",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "volumetric analysis of the flue gas"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "A theorem that states that the total property of a mixture of ideal gases is the sum of the properties that the individual gases would have if each occupied the total mixture volume alone as the same temperature.",
        "options": [
            "Gibbs theorem",
            "Dalton’s theorem",
            "Boltzmann’s theorem",
            "Maxwell’s theorem"
        ],
        "answer": "Gibbs theorem"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "A small enough particles suspended in a fluid exhibit small random movements due to the state collision of fluid molecules on the particle’s sum. This motion is called____________.",
        "options": [
            "Boltzmann motion",
            "Rectilinear motion",
            "Kinetic gas motion",
            "Brownian motion"
        ],
        "answer": "Brownian motion"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "When two or more light atoms have sufficient emf (available only at high temperatures and velocities) fuse together to form a heavier nucleus the process called____________.",
        "options": [
            "fusion",
            "fission",
            "the photo electric effect",
            "the Compton effect"
        ],
        "answer": "fusion"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "What is the residue left after combustion of a fuel?",
        "options": [
            "charcoal",
            "ash",
            "scraper",
            "all of the choices"
        ],
        "answer": "ash"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "What is formed during incomplete combustion of carbon in fuels?",
        "options": [
            "carbon dioxide",
            "carbon monoxide",
            "nitrogen oxide",
            "oxygenated fuel"
        ],
        "answer": "carbon monoxide"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "A gas produced by the combustion of fuel oil and cannot be found in the flue gases is:",
        "options": [
            "oxygen",
            "nitrogen",
            "hydrogen",
            "carbon dioxide"
        ],
        "answer": "hydrogen"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Which of the following chemical reactions in which heat is absorbed?",
        "options": [
            "heat reaction",
            "endothermic reaction",
            "exothermic reaction",
            "combustion reaction"
        ],
        "answer": "endothermic reaction"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "A chemical reaction in which heat is given off.",
        "options": [
            "heat reaction",
            "endothermic reaction",
            "exothermic reaction",
            "combustion reaction"
        ],
        "answer": "exothermic reaction"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Colorless, odourless mixture of nitrogen and oxygen with traces of other gases water vapour and said impurities.",
        "options": [
            "air",
            "helium",
            "water gas",
            "nitrite"
        ],
        "answer": "air"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The transfer of air characteristics by horizontal motion is called____________.",
        "options": [
            "convection",
            "air transfer",
            "advection",
            "adhesion"
        ],
        "answer": "advection"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Properties of non – reacting gas mixtures are given by",
        "options": [
            "geometric weighting",
            "volumetric weighting",
            "volumetric weighting for molecular weight and density, and geometric weighting for all other properties except entropy",
            "arithmetic average"
        ],
        "answer": "volumetric weighting for molecular weight and density, and geometric weighting for all"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The process of separating two or more liquids by means of the difference in their boiling point.",
        "options": [
            "Engler distillation",
            "Fractional distillation",
            "Gas scrubbing",
            "Fractional crystallization"
        ],
        "answer": "Fractional distillation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The gaseous products of combustion of a boiler which contains carbon dioxide, carbon monoxide, oxygen, nitrogen and water vapour is called____________.",
        "options": [
            "flue gas",
            "producer gas",
            "product gas",
            "universal gas"
        ],
        "answer": "flue gas"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "A substance whose burning with oxygen yields heat energy such as coal, petroleum and natural gas.",
        "options": [
            "air",
            "fluid",
            "fuel",
            "gas"
        ],
        "answer": "fuel"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Stoichiometric ratio is",
        "options": [
            "chemically correct air – fuel ratio by volume",
            "chemically correct air – fuel ratio by weight",
            "theoretically mixture of air for complete combustion",
            "actual ratio of air to fuel for maximum efficiency"
        ],
        "answer": "chemically correct air – fuel ratio by weight"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "A type of radiation consisting of singly charged particles that generate to intermediate distances.",
        "options": [
            "nuclear radiation",
            "alpha radiation",
            "beta radiation",
            "gamma radiation"
        ],
        "answer": "beta radiation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The increase in velocity past the throat is due to rapid decrease in the:",
        "options": [
            "fluid density",
            "fluid specific volume",
            "fluid temperature",
            "fluid pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "fluid density"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "In an oxidation -  reduction chemical reaction, all of the following occur except:",
        "options": [
            "the exchange of electrons between elements",
            "elements becoming more positive",
            "elements becoming more negative",
            "nuclear fusion"
        ],
        "answer": "nuclear fusion"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The residual oil left after the distillation of gasoline and kerosene from crude petroleum; yellow to brown and used as a diesel fuel and enriching water gas.",
        "options": [
            "diesel oil",
            "gasoline oil",
            "LPG",
            "gas oil"
        ],
        "answer": "gas oil"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "A fuel gas obtained by the destructive distillation of soft coal is called__________.",
        "options": [
            "gas scrub",
            "coal gas",
            "alco gas",
            "water gas"
        ],
        "answer": "coal gas"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Removing of impurities from a gas by bubbling it through a liquid purifying agent is called__________.",
        "options": [
            "gas scrubbing",
            "gas purifying",
            "gas liquefying",
            "gas bubbling"
        ],
        "answer": "gas scrubbing"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "During the fusion process, mass is lost and converted to energy according to:",
        "options": [
            "the Heisenburg  uncertainty principle",
            "the Compton’s law",
            "Einstein’s law",
            "the second law of thermodynamics"
        ],
        "answer": "Einstein’s law"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "A finely divided carbon deposit by the smoke or flame is called__________.",
        "options": [
            "fly ash",
            "soot",
            "residue",
            "all of the choices"
        ],
        "answer": "soot"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Rare gases such as helium, argon, krypton, xenon and radon that are non – reactive are called_____________.",
        "options": [
            "non - reactants",
            "stop gases",
            "insert gases",
            "residual gases"
        ],
        "answer": "insert gases"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Kinematics and dynamic viscosity vary from each of only by a factor equal to the :",
        "options": [
            "fluid density",
            "temperature",
            "pressure",
            "specific gas constant"
        ],
        "answer": "fluid density"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The following properties are different for isomers of the same chemical compound:",
        "options": [
            "density",
            "melting point",
            "number of atoms in a mole of each isomers",
            "specific heat"
        ],
        "answer": "number of atoms in a mole of each isomers"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Atomic weights of the elements in the periodic table are not whole numbers because of:",
        "options": [
            "the existence of isotopes",
            "imprecise measurements during the development of the periodic table",
            "round – off error in calculating atomic weights",
            "the exchange of reference of the atomic mass unit from oxygen – 16 to carbon – 12 in 1961."
        ],
        "answer": "the existence of isotopes"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The tendency of a pure compound to be composed of same elements combined in a definite proportion by mass.",
        "options": [
            "Avogadro’s law",
            "Boyle’s law",
            "The law of definite proportions",
            "Le Chatelier’s principle"
        ],
        "answer": "The law of definite proportions"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "How do you call the process of removing of impurities from a gas by bubbling it through a liquid purifying agent?",
        "options": [
            "gas scrubbing",
            "gas purifying",
            "gas liquefying",
            "gas bubbling"
        ],
        "answer": "gas scrubbing"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "What is the effect of catalyst in a chemical reaction?",
        "options": [
            "absorb the exothermic heat of reaction",
            "provide the exothermic heat of reaction",
            "lower the activation energy",
            "provide the heat of sublimation"
        ],
        "answer": "lower the activation energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The relationship between the concentration of products and reactants in a reversible chemical reaction give by:",
        "options": [
            "the ionization constant",
            "the equilibrium constant",
            "the solubility",
            "Le Chatelier’s principle"
        ],
        "answer": "the equilibrium constant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "What fuel gas obtained by the destructive distillation of soft coal?",
        "options": [
            "gas scrub",
            "coal gas",
            "alcogas",
            "water gas"
        ],
        "answer": "coal gas"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The process of splitting the nucleus into small fragments.",
        "options": [
            "fusion",
            "fission",
            "the photo electric effect",
            "the Compton effect"
        ],
        "answer": "fission"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The ash that is removed from the combustor after the fuel is burn is the:",
        "options": [
            "fly ash",
            "bottom ash",
            "scraper ash",
            "top ash"
        ],
        "answer": "bottom ash"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "A mixture of hydrogen and carbon monoxide made by passing steam over hot coke.",
        "options": [
            "water gas",
            "water vapor",
            "hydrocarbon",
            "air"
        ],
        "answer": "water gas"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "All of the following are true of non – stoichiometric reactions except.",
        "options": [
            "there is an excess of one or more reactants",
            "the percentage yield measures the efficiency of the reaction",
            "non – stoichiometric reactions are rare in the combustion process",
            "in combustion, air is often the excess reactant to assure complete combustion of fuel"
        ],
        "answer": "non – stoichiometric reactions are rare in the combustion process"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "It is the ratio of the volume at the end of heat addition to the volume at the start of heat addition.",
        "options": [
            "compression ratio",
            "air - fuel ratio",
            "volumetric ratio",
            "cut – off ratio"
        ],
        "answer": "cut – off ratio"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Piston rings are made of:",
        "options": [
            "alloy steel",
            "carbon steel",
            "copper",
            "cast iron"
        ],
        "answer": "cast iron"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Loss power is due to:",
        "options": [
            "poor compression",
            "restricted exhaust",
            "clogging of air cleaner",
            "low injection pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "low injection pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "A branch system of pipes to carry waste emission away from the piston chambers of an internal combustion engine is called",
        "options": [
            "exhaust nozzle",
            "exhaust deflection pipe",
            "exhaust pipe",
            "exhaust manifold"
        ],
        "answer": "exhaust manifold"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The type of filter where the filtering elements is replaceable.",
        "options": [
            "paper edge filter",
            "metal edge filter",
            "pressure filter",
            "filter with element"
        ],
        "answer": "metal edge filter"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "When four events take place in one revolution of a crankshaft of an engine, the engine is called:",
        "options": [
            "rotary engine",
            "steam engine",
            "two stroke engine",
            "four stroke engine"
        ],
        "answer": "two stroke engine"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Which of the following does not belong to the group?",
        "options": [
            "air injection system",
            "mechanical injection system",
            "time injection system",
            "gas admission system"
        ],
        "answer": "time injection system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Specific heat capacity is an SI derived unit described as:",
        "options": [
            "J/kg",
            "W/m °K",
            "J/m3",
            "J/kg °K"
        ],
        "answer": "J/kg °K"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "A device whose primary function is to meter the flow refrigerant to the vapour.",
        "options": [
            "sniffer valve",
            "equalizer",
            "thermostatic expansion valve",
            "crossover valve"
        ],
        "answer": "thermostatic expansion valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The internal combustion engines never work in",
        "options": [
            "Rankine cycle",
            "Diesel cycle",
            "Dual combustion cycle",
            "Otto cycle"
        ],
        "answer": "Rankine cycle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The general chemical formula for all hydrocarbons Cn Hm. In different combinations of interest, as steam combustion engine fuel, n varies from:",
        "options": [
            "1 to 26",
            "2 to 54",
            "2 to 26",
            "1 to 54"
        ],
        "answer": "1 to 26"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The general chemical formula for all hydrocarbons is Cn Hm. In different combinations of interest, as internal combustion engine fuel m varies from:",
        "options": [
            "1 to 26",
            "2 to 54",
            "2 to 26",
            "1 to 54"
        ],
        "answer": "2 to 54"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The general chemical formula of a paraffin fuel is",
        "options": [
            "Cn H2n",
            "Cn H2n−6",
            "Cn H2n+2",
            "Cn H2n−2"
        ],
        "answer": "Cn H2n+2"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Naphthenes and olefins are types of hydrocarbons with chemical formula of:",
        "options": [
            "Cn H2n",
            "Cn H2n−6",
            "Cn H2n+2",
            "Cn H2n−2"
        ],
        "answer": "Cn H2n"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Which of the following types of hydrocarbons have chemical formula of Cn H2n−2?",
        "options": [
            "diolefins",
            "aromatics",
            "asphaltics",
            "paraffins"
        ],
        "answer": "diolefins"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Which of the following types of hydrocarbons have chemical formula of Cn H2n−4?",
        "options": [
            "diolefins",
            "aromatics",
            "asphaltics",
            "paraffins"
        ],
        "answer": "asphaltics"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "What is the chemical formula of an aromatic type hydrocarbon fuels?",
        "options": [
            "Cn H2n−6 B.Cn H2n−2",
            "Cn H2n",
            "Cn H2n+2"
        ],
        "answer": "Cn H2n−6"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "At atmospheric condition, hydrocarbon molecules with a low number of carbon atoms, 1 to 4 are.",
        "options": [
            "liquids",
            "atomic",
            "gases",
            "light oils"
        ],
        "answer": "gases"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Hydrocarbons with 5 to 15 carbon atoms are:",
        "options": [
            "more or less volatile light oils",
            "referred to as heavy oils",
            "mixtures of many kinds of hydrocarbons",
            "commercial fuels"
        ],
        "answer": "more or less volatile light oils"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Hydrocarbons with 16 to 26 carbon atoms are referred to as:",
        "options": [
            "light oils",
            "heavy oils",
            "commercial fuels",
            "lubricating oils"
        ],
        "answer": "heavy oils"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "In a four stroke engine if a valve opens 25° before B.D.C. and close 10° after T.D.C. the valve should be:",
        "options": [
            "puppet valve",
            "exhaust valve",
            "inlet valve",
            "spring valve"
        ],
        "answer": "exhaust valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "In a hot wire anemometer the rate of heat loss from sensing element is a function of:",
        "options": [
            "mass rate of flow",
            "pressure",
            "velocity of flow",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "velocity of flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Sticking valve",
        "options": [
            "valve tappet clearance incorrect",
            "valve springs of defective material",
            "valve guides gummed",
            "lubricating oil of poor quality"
        ],
        "answer": "valve springs of defective material"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Detonation of pinging noises is due to:",
        "options": [
            "early timing of fuel injection",
            "late timing of fuel injection",
            "head of piston carbonized",
            "valve springs weak or broken"
        ],
        "answer": "late timing of fuel injection"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The thermal efficiency of a dual cycle engine with fixed compression ratio and fixed quantity of heat and with increase in pressure ratio, will",
        "options": [
            "increase",
            "remain same",
            "decrease",
            "depends on other factors"
        ],
        "answer": "increase"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Scavenging efficiency of a four stroke diesel engine is",
        "options": [
            "in the range 80 – 95 percent",
            "in the range 60 – 80 percent",
            "below 60 percent",
            "between 95% and 100%"
        ],
        "answer": "between 95% and 100%"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Volumetric efficiency of a well designed engine may be in the range of:",
        "options": [
            "75 to 90 percent",
            "60 to 75 percent",
            "30 to 50 percent",
            "below 30 percent"
        ],
        "answer": "75 to 90 percent"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "During idling in a compression ignition engine the air fuel ratio may be of the order of:",
        "options": [
            "30",
            "200",
            "150",
            "100"
        ],
        "answer": "30"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Vapour lock is",
        "options": [
            "lock of vaporization of fuel to atmospheric pressure",
            "excess fuel supply to engine because of faster evaporation",
            "complete or partial stoppage of fuel supply because of vaporization of fuel in supply steam",
            "locking carburettor jets because of vapor pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "complete or partial stoppage of fuel supply because of vaporization of fuel in supply"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Flash point of liquids is the temperature at which:",
        "options": [
            "the fuel emits vapors at rate which produces an inflammable mixture with air",
            "the fuel spontaneously ignites",
            "the fuel ignites with a clearly visible flash",
            "the fuel ignites without a spark"
        ],
        "answer": "the fuel emits vapors at rate which produces an inflammable mixture with air"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The mean effective pressure of a diesel cycle have fixed compression ratio will increase if cut off ratio is:",
        "options": [
            "increased",
            "decreased",
            "independent of compression ratio",
            "depends on other factor"
        ],
        "answer": "increased"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Hot spots",
        "options": [
            "do not exist in engines",
            "are the hottest spot in the engine",
            "are the spots where heavier functions of fuel vaporized",
            "are the defects in S.I. in engines"
        ],
        "answer": "are the spots where heavier functions of fuel vaporized"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Flash point for diesel fuel oil should be:",
        "options": [
            "maximum 49 °C",
            "maximum 490 °C",
            "maximum 200 °C",
            "maximum 300 °C"
        ],
        "answer": "maximum 49 °C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Morse test is conducted on:",
        "options": [
            "single – cylinder engines",
            "multi – cylinder engines",
            "horizontal engines",
            "vertical engines"
        ],
        "answer": "multi – cylinder engines"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Prony brake is used for testing of:",
        "options": [
            "small engines",
            "large engines",
            "engines having small flywheel",
            "high speed engines"
        ],
        "answer": "small engines"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Clog point of an oil refer to:",
        "options": [
            "the point of maximum contamination of oil",
            "the level of impurities beyond which oil ceases to flow",
            "the temperature at which oil solidifies",
            "the temperature at which paraffin and waxes in oil start precipitating"
        ],
        "answer": "the temperature at which paraffin and waxes in oil start precipitating"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Otto cycle consists of:",
        "options": [
            "two isentropic and two constant volumes processes",
            "two isentropic and two constant pressure processes",
            "two adiabatic and two isothermal processes",
            "two isothermal and two constant volume processes"
        ],
        "answer": "two isentropic and two constant volumes processes"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Diesel cycle consist of:",
        "options": [
            "isentropic, isothermal, constant volume constant pressure processes",
            "two constant volume, one constant pressure, one isothermal process",
            "two isentropic, one constant volume and one constant pressure processes",
            "two constant pressure, one constant volume, and one isentropic processes"
        ],
        "answer": "two isentropic, one constant volume and one constant pressure processes"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Which is not correct for calculating air stand efficiency?",
        "options": [
            "all processes are reversible",
            "specific heat remains unchanged at temperature",
            "no account of the mechanism of heat transfer considered",
            "gases dissociate at higher temperatures"
        ],
        "answer": "gases dissociate at higher temperatures"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The king pin inclination is generally:",
        "options": [
            "less than 0.5°",
            "between 1° and 2°",
            "between 2° and 5°",
            "more than 9°"
        ],
        "answer": "between 2° and 5°"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "For balancing single cylinder engine a counter weight is added to:",
        "options": [
            "piston",
            "piston pin",
            "cam",
            "crank"
        ],
        "answer": "crank"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "To measure the clearance between the valve and tappet of an automobile engine we use a___________.",
        "options": [
            "Vernier scale",
            "feeler gauge",
            "pneumatic gauge",
            "slip gauge"
        ],
        "answer": "feeler gauge"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "By supercharging:",
        "options": [
            "power stroke becomes stronger",
            "loss in exhaust gets reduced",
            "engine can be made to run smoother",
            "thermal efficiency of the engine can be improved"
        ],
        "answer": "thermal efficiency of the engine can be improved"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Speedometer drive is generally taken from:",
        "options": [
            "dynamo",
            "flywheel",
            "fan belt",
            "front wheel"
        ],
        "answer": "front wheel"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Odometer is:",
        "options": [
            "an instrument that indicates the condition of battery",
            "an instrument used for measurement of consumption",
            "an instrument used for BHP measurement",
            "an instrument used for distance measurement"
        ],
        "answer": "an instrument used for distance measurement"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Automobile radiator is filled with:",
        "options": [
            "acidic water",
            "alkaline water",
            "hard water",
            "soft water"
        ],
        "answer": "soft water"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The ignition coil acts as:",
        "options": [
            "a capacitor",
            "an inductor",
            "an RC circuit",
            "a step up transformer"
        ],
        "answer": "a step up transformer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The self starting motor for automobile is a:",
        "options": [
            "universal motor",
            "DC shunt motor",
            "DC series motor",
            "synchronous motor"
        ],
        "answer": "DC series motor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Starting motor current may be about",
        "options": [
            "0.15 A",
            "0.5 A",
            "5.1 A",
            "25 A"
        ],
        "answer": "25 A"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "As a rule before the piston are remove, it is essential to remove the:",
        "options": [
            "gudgeon pin",
            "circlip",
            "piston rings",
            "crank shaft"
        ],
        "answer": "piston rings"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Common causes for excessive oil consumption include:",
        "options": [
            "heavy oil and light bearings",
            "high speed and worn engine",
            "short trips and cold weather",
            "frequent oil changes"
        ],
        "answer": "high speed and worn engine"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The device that is used for reducing the exhaust noise is called_____________.",
        "options": [
            "exhaust manifold",
            "exhaust pipe",
            "muffler",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "muffler"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The device that is used to measure the clearance between the valve and tappet of an internal combustion engine is measured by using:",
        "options": [
            "snap gauge",
            "slip gauge",
            "feeler gauge",
            "micrometer"
        ],
        "answer": "feeler gauge"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Which of the following instrument is used measuring specific gravity?",
        "options": [
            "thermometer",
            "hygrometer",
            "anemometer",
            "hydrometer"
        ],
        "answer": "hydrometer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Exhaust gas leakage into the cooling system is likely to occur because of defective:",
        "options": [
            "cylinder head gasket",
            "manifold gasket",
            "water pump",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "cylinder head gasket"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Clutch slippage while clutch is engaged is specially noticeable________________.",
        "options": [
            "during idling",
            "at low speed",
            "during acceleration",
            "during braking"
        ],
        "answer": "during acceleration"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "To engage securely and prevent dragging the clearance between release bearing and release collar in a clutch is generally:",
        "options": [
            "2 – 3 mm",
            "10 – 12 mm",
            "20 – 22 mm",
            "30 – 32 mm"
        ],
        "answer": "2 – 3 mm"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Gudgeon pins are made of:",
        "options": [
            "same material as that of piston",
            "cast iron",
            "hardened and ground steel",
            "none of these"
        ],
        "answer": "none of these"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Latex is:",
        "options": [
            "a plastic",
            "a cover on writes carrying current to spark plugs",
            "a variety of lubricant",
            "a milky juice of rubber"
        ],
        "answer": "a milky juice of rubber"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Cross wires on grooves on tires",
        "options": [
            "decrease the danger of skidding",
            "absorb shocks because of road unevenness",
            "provide good traction",
            "provide better load carrying capacity"
        ],
        "answer": "absorb shocks because of road unevenness"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The diesel fuel pump is designed to supply fuel",
        "options": [
            "just sufficient against the demand of the injector pump",
            "in excess quantity than needed by the injector pump",
            "a constant quantity at all engine speeds",
            "in sufficient quantity in accordance with the engine speed"
        ],
        "answer": "in sufficient quantity in accordance with the engine speed"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The fuel injected into the cylinder in diesel engine when the piston is:",
        "options": [
            "exactly at B.D.C. after compression stroke",
            "exactly T.D.C. before compression stroke",
            "approaching T.D.C. during compression stroke",
            "approaching B.D.C. during exhaust stroke"
        ],
        "answer": "approaching T.D.C. during compression stroke"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "In the cam, the distance between the base circle the nose is known as____________.",
        "options": [
            "flank",
            "nose",
            "lobe",
            "lift"
        ],
        "answer": "lift"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Dirt or gum in fuel nozzle or jets can produce:",
        "options": [
            "excessive fuel consumption",
            "lack of engine power",
            "smoky black exhaust",
            "white exhaust"
        ],
        "answer": "smoky black exhaust"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Oil pan is attached:",
        "options": [
            "to the bottom of the cylinder block",
            "in a separate away from the crank case",
            "at the top of the cylinder block",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "any of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Excess oil consumption in engine may be because of:",
        "options": [
            "leakage of oil through oil pan gasket",
            "poor quality or improper viscosity of engine oil",
            "excessive oil pressure",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "any of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Wheel base of the vehicle is:",
        "options": [
            "distance between front and rear axis",
            "distance between the front tires",
            "extreme length of the vehicles",
            "width of tires"
        ],
        "answer": "distance between front and rear axis"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The percentage of heat released from fuel mixture, in an internal combustion engine which converted into useful work is roughly:",
        "options": [
            "10 percent",
            "10 – 20 percent",
            "20 – 25 percent",
            "40 – 45 percent"
        ],
        "answer": "20 – 25 percent"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The efficiency of hydraulic braking system is:",
        "options": [
            "about 90 percent",
            "60 – 80 percent",
            "50 – 60 percent",
            "40 – 50 percent"
        ],
        "answer": "about 90 percent"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The instrument that is used to check the state charge of a battery is called a_______________.",
        "options": [
            "hydrometer",
            "battery charger",
            "battery eliminator",
            "anemometer"
        ],
        "answer": "hydrometer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "When not in use, the self discharge of an automobile battery in dry weather is generally:",
        "options": [
            "0.5 to 1%",
            "3 to 5%",
            "5 to 7.5%",
            "not more than 10%"
        ],
        "answer": "0.5 to 1%"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "A laminated glass on cracking:",
        "options": [
            "bursts into sharp edged fragments",
            "bursts into granular pieces",
            "sand witched layer taps the fragments",
            "breaks into the farm of crystals"
        ],
        "answer": "sand witched layer taps the fragments"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Wax is applied on car body as:",
        "options": [
            "it is water repellent",
            "it seals off the pores",
            "the surface shines",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "any of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "A spark voltage requires a voltage of:",
        "options": [
            "112 V",
            "124 V",
            "220 V",
            "440 V"
        ],
        "answer": "220 V"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The minimum cranking speed in petrol engine is:",
        "options": [
            "same as the normal operating speed",
            "half of operating speed",
            "one fourth of operating speed",
            "60 – 80 rpm"
        ],
        "answer": "60 – 80 rpm"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Which oil is more viscous?",
        "options": [
            "SAE 30",
            "SAE 50",
            "SAE 80",
            "SAE 40"
        ],
        "answer": "SAE 80"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Engine oil is generally changed after:",
        "options": [
            "100 km",
            "1500 km",
            "1100 km",
            "2500 – 6000 km"
        ],
        "answer": "2500 – 6000 km"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The most probable cause for uneven wear of tires for truck is:",
        "options": [
            "low the pressure",
            "excessive camber",
            "tires overloaded",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "any of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "In a vehicle the most probable cause for hard steering may be:",
        "options": [
            "low tire pressure",
            "bent wheel spindle",
            "tie rod ends tight",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "any of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Poor compression in a two stroke engine cannot be because of:",
        "options": [
            "leaky valves",
            "broken piston rings",
            "leaking cylinder head gasket",
            "poor fits between pistons, rings and cylinder"
        ],
        "answer": "leaky valves"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The number of exhaust manifolds in a V – 8 engine is:",
        "options": [
            "one",
            "four",
            "there is no exhaust manifold",
            "two"
        ],
        "answer": "two"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The device for smoothing out the power impulses from the engine is known as:",
        "options": [
            "clutch",
            "fly wheel",
            "gear box",
            "differential"
        ],
        "answer": "fly wheel"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The firing order in case of four cylinder in the engines is generally_____________.",
        "options": [
            "1 – 2 – 4 – 3",
            "1 – 3 – 4 – 2",
            "1 – 4 – 3 – 2",
            "either B or C"
        ],
        "answer": "either B or C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "In case of four cylinder opposed cylinder engines, firing order is",
        "options": [
            "1 – 4 – 3 – 2",
            "1 – 3 – 4 – 2",
            "1 – 2 – 3 – 4",
            "1 – 2 – 4 – 3"
        ],
        "answer": "1 – 4 – 3 – 2"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "In a four stroke engine, for the combustion of one of fuel, the volume of air needed would approximately",
        "options": [
            "1 cu. m",
            "2 cu. m",
            "5 – 7 cu. m",
            "9 – 10 cu. m"
        ],
        "answer": "9 – 10 cu. m"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Theoretically air needed for the combustion of one kg of fuel is:",
        "options": [
            "100 kg",
            "14.5 kg",
            "16.7 kg",
            "27.4 kg"
        ],
        "answer": "14.5 kg"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Which of the following is the cause of loss power?",
        "options": [
            "poor compression",
            "restricted exhaust",
            "clogging of air cleaner",
            "low injection pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "low injection pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "A valve in the carburettor of a internal combustion engines which regulates the proportion of air gasoline vapors entering the cylinder.",
        "options": [
            "gate valve",
            "choke valve",
            "check valve",
            "globe valve"
        ],
        "answer": "choke valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "What device combines air and fuel for burning in cylinder?",
        "options": [
            "intercooler",
            "regenerator",
            "fuel injection",
            "carburettor"
        ],
        "answer": "carburettor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "A passive restraint device consisting of bags in front of the driver and passenger.",
        "options": [
            "air buoy",
            "air bag",
            "air balloon",
            "air duct"
        ],
        "answer": "air bag"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The heat exchanger used in an Ericson cycle is:",
        "options": [
            "regenerator",
            "combustion chamber",
            "intercooler",
            "recuperator"
        ],
        "answer": "recuperator"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "In Stirling engine, the heat is added during",
        "options": [
            "isothermal processes",
            "isometric processes",
            "isobaric processes",
            "isentropic processes"
        ],
        "answer": "isothermal processes"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "In an Otto engine, the heat  is added during",
        "options": [
            "isothermal processes",
            "isometric processes",
            "isobaric processes",
            "isentropic processes"
        ],
        "answer": "isometric processes"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Exhaust stroke gasoline engine is also known as",
        "options": [
            "supercharging",
            "choking",
            "scavenging",
            "knockling"
        ],
        "answer": "scavenging"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The mechanical efficiency of a device is the ratio of the",
        "options": [
            "mechanical energy input to the mechanical energy output of the device",
            "ideal energy input to the actual energy input",
            "actual energy extracted to the ideal energy extracted",
            "actual to the ideal energy input"
        ],
        "answer": "ideal energy input to the actual energy input"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The smallest subdivision of a compound that can take in a natural state is a/an",
        "options": [
            "atom",
            "molecule",
            "electron",
            "proton"
        ],
        "answer": "molecule"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Elements with different atomic weights but the same atomic number are:",
        "options": [
            "isomers",
            "isotropes",
            "isotopes",
            "isobars"
        ],
        "answer": "isotopes"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "All of the following are characteristics of metals except:",
        "options": [
            "high electrical conductivities",
            "tendency to form positive ions",
            "tendency to form brittle solids",
            "high melting points"
        ],
        "answer": "tendency to form brittle solids"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The following are all characteristics of non – metals except",
        "options": [
            "having little or no luster",
            "appearing o the right end of the periodic table",
            "having low ductility",
            "being reducing agents"
        ],
        "answer": "being reducing agents"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Graduations in the properties of elements from one elements to the next are less pronounced in:",
        "options": [
            "the lanthanide series",
            "periods",
            "groups",
            "active metals"
        ],
        "answer": "groups"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "All of the following are components of a chemical elements except:",
        "options": [
            "protons",
            "neutrons",
            "electrons",
            "ions"
        ],
        "answer": "ions"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Which of the following is not a prefix used in naming isomers?",
        "options": [
            "Para",
            "Meta",
            "Cis",
            "Bi"
        ],
        "answer": "Bi"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "All of the following are types of chemical bonds except:",
        "options": [
            "ionic bonds",
            "covalent bonds",
            "metallic bonds",
            "nuclear bonds"
        ],
        "answer": "nuclear bonds"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The equilibrium distance between elements in ionic bonds is function of all the following except:",
        "options": [
            "ionic change",
            "coordination number",
            "atomic weight",
            "temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "atomic weight"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Which of the following statements is not characteristic of ionic compounds?",
        "options": [
            "they are usually hard, brittle, crystalline solids",
            "they have high melting points",
            "they are non volatile and have low vapor pressures",
            "they are good electrical conductors in the solid phase"
        ],
        "answer": "they are good electrical conductors in the solid phase"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "What kind of bonding do common gases that exists a free state as diatomic molecules experience?",
        "options": [
            "ionic bonds",
            "covalent bonds",
            "metallic bonds",
            "nuclear bonds"
        ],
        "answer": "covalent bonds"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Measure the diffuser’s ability to increase the pressure of the fluid is :",
        "options": [
            "speed recovery factor",
            "pressure recovery factor",
            "volume recovery factor",
            "diffuser recovery factor"
        ],
        "answer": "pressure recovery factor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "A decrease in stagnation pressure will decrease the mass flux through the:",
        "options": [
            "diverging nozzle",
            "converging nozzle",
            "converging – diverging nozzle",
            "none of these"
        ],
        "answer": "diverging nozzle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "What is the main power generating plant that produces the most electricity per unit thermal energy in the fuel input and has the greatest surplus of electricity for most co generation system?",
        "options": [
            "steam engine",
            "steam turbine",
            "gas turbine",
            "diesel engine"
        ],
        "answer": "diesel engine"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Air standard efficiency of a diesel engine depends on:",
        "options": [
            "speed",
            "compression ratio",
            "fuel",
            "torque"
        ],
        "answer": "compression ratio"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "What is meant by brake horse power?",
        "options": [
            "power developed in the engine cylinder",
            "final horse power delivered to the equipment",
            "actual horse power delivered to the engine drive shaft",
            "work required to raise a weight of 33,000 lbs at a height of one foot in one minute of time"
        ],
        "answer": "actual horse power delivered to the engine drive shaft"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Average pressure on a surface when a changing pressure condition exist",
        "options": [
            "back pressure",
            "partial pressure",
            "pressure drop",
            "mean effective pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "mean effective pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "What air pressure is needed for air starting a diesel engine?",
        "options": [
            "350 psi",
            "250 psi",
            "450 psi",
            "150 psi"
        ],
        "answer": "250 psi"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Mechanical energy of pressure transformed into energy of heat:",
        "options": [
            "kinetic energy",
            "enthalpy",
            "heat exchanger",
            "heat of compression"
        ],
        "answer": "enthalpy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Ignition of the air – fuel mixture in the intake of the exhaust manifold",
        "options": [
            "backlash",
            "back fire",
            "exhaust pressure",
            "back pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "back fire"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The total sulphur content in a diesel fuel must not excess_____________.",
        "options": [
            "0.3%",
            "0.5%",
            "0.8%",
            "0.11%"
        ],
        "answer": "0.5%"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Total sulphur content in a diesel fuel oil must not excess.",
        "options": [
            "0.2%",
            "0.5%",
            "0.15%",
            "0.1%"
        ],
        "answer": "0.5%"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The color of lubricating oil:",
        "options": [
            "does not indicate contamination",
            "does not indicate qualities",
            "indicates qualities",
            "indicates viscosity"
        ],
        "answer": "does not indicate qualities"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "There are two broad types in the classification of lubricating oils, these are straight and",
        "options": [
            "active",
            "in active",
            "crooked",
            "additives"
        ],
        "answer": "additives"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Most commercially available petroleum lubricating oil deteriorates starting from operating temperature of:",
        "options": [
            "150 °F",
            "200 °F",
            "300 °F",
            "250 °F"
        ],
        "answer": "200 °F"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "An Orsat apparatus is used for",
        "options": [
            "volumetric analysis of the flue gases",
            "gravimetric analysis of the flue gases",
            "smoke density analysis of the gases",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "volumetric analysis of the flue gases"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The indicator used to determine the anti – knock characteristics of gasoline.",
        "options": [
            "anlline point",
            "cetane number",
            "octane number",
            "diesel number"
        ],
        "answer": "octane number"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Amount of heat liberated by the complete combustion of a uniit weight or volume of fuel is:",
        "options": [
            "heating valve",
            "latent heat",
            "sensible heat",
            "work of compression"
        ],
        "answer": "heating valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Air that controls the rate of combustion in the combustion chamber is known as:",
        "options": [
            "secondary air",
            "excess air",
            "control air",
            "primary air"
        ],
        "answer": "secondary air"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Percentage of excess air is the difference between the air actually supplied and the theoretically recquirment dived by:",
        "options": [
            "actual air supplied",
            "theoretical air supplied",
            "theoretical less actual supplied",
            "deficient air supplied"
        ],
        "answer": "theoretical air supplied"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "When fuel oil has a high viscosity then the fuel oil",
        "options": [
            "will evaporate easily",
            "will have a low specific gravity",
            "will burn without smoke",
            "will flow slowly through pipes"
        ],
        "answer": "will flow slowly through pipes"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Engines using heavy fuels require heating of the fuel so that the viscosity at the injector is:",
        "options": [
            "around 200 SSU",
            "100 SSU or less",
            "200 SSU + 50",
            "150 SSU or slightly higher"
        ],
        "answer": "150 SSU or slightly higher"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "A gas produced by the combustion of fuel oil and cannot be found in the flue gases is:",
        "options": [
            "carbon dioxide",
            "hydrogen",
            "oxygen",
            "nitrogen"
        ],
        "answer": "hydrogen"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Amount of heat liberated by the complete combustion of a unit weight or volume of fuel is:",
        "options": [
            "heating value",
            "latent heat",
            "sensible heat",
            "work of compression"
        ],
        "answer": "heating value"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The products of complete combustion of gaseous hydrocarbons.",
        "options": [
            "carbon dioxide and water",
            "carbon monoxide",
            "carbon monoxide, water and ammonia",
            "water, carbon monoxide and carbon dioxide"
        ],
        "answer": "carbon dioxide and water"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "When the water in the products of combustion is in the vapor state, the heating value is:",
        "options": [
            "lower heating value",
            "higher heating value",
            "gross calorific value",
            "average heating value"
        ],
        "answer": "lower heating value"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "At what temperature where in an oil of any grade becomes cloudy and it freezes, thus its application is limited.",
        "options": [
            "cold point",
            "flash point",
            "pour point",
            "freezing point"
        ],
        "answer": "cold point"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Dry air can be approximated as _______% oxygen and _______% nitrogen by mole numbers.",
        "options": [
            "30% and 70%",
            "70% and 30%",
            "21% and 79%",
            "79% and 21%"
        ],
        "answer": "21% and 79%"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "When H2 O in the products of combustion is in liquid form, the heating value is known as",
        "options": [
            "higher heating value",
            "lower heating value",
            "low and medium heating value",
            "average heating value"
        ],
        "answer": "higher heating value"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Flow of fluids wherein its particles do not have definite paths and the paths of the individual and distinguished particles across one another is:",
        "options": [
            "non -  uniform flow",
            "unsteady flow",
            "laminar flow",
            "turbulent flow"
        ],
        "answer": "turbulent flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "If the composition of hydrocarbon fuel is known, the ratio between the nitrogen and oxygen that is supplied in the air is:",
        "options": [
            "equal",
            "constant",
            "intensity",
            "fixed"
        ],
        "answer": "constant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The property of liquid in which they extend resistance to angular or shear deformation is:",
        "options": [
            "specific gravity",
            "specific weight",
            "viscosity",
            "density"
        ],
        "answer": "viscosity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "A property of lubricating oil that measures the thickness of the oil and will help determine how long oil will flow at a given temperature is known as:",
        "options": [
            "viscosity",
            "flash point",
            "cloud point",
            "cloud point"
        ],
        "answer": "viscosity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The minimum amount of air required for a complete combustion of fuel is called_____________.",
        "options": [
            "dry air",
            "excess air",
            "theoretical air",
            "flue gas"
        ],
        "answer": "theoretical air"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The temperature at which lubricating will form a cloud.",
        "options": [
            "cloud point",
            "pour point",
            "critical point",
            "boilling point"
        ],
        "answer": "cloud point"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The ideal cycle based on the concept that the combustion process is both diesel and gasoline in the combination of heat transfer processes that is constant pressure and constant volume.",
        "options": [
            "Ericson cycle",
            "Dual cycle",
            "Brayton cycle",
            "Rankine cycle"
        ],
        "answer": "Dual cycle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "The unit used for expressing API gravity is:",
        "options": [
            "gm/cc",
            "dimensionless numbers",
            "degrees",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "degrees"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "ASTM coal classification is based on:",
        "options": [
            "proximate analysis",
            "orsat analysis",
            "ultimate analysis",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "proximate analysis"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "API gravity of water is:",
        "options": [
            "zero",
            "10",
            "1.0",
            "100"
        ],
        "answer": "10"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Which of the following variety of coal has highest content?",
        "options": [
            "lignite",
            "bitumious coal",
            "grade 1 steam coal",
            "coking coal"
        ],
        "answer": "lignite"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Which of the following is a petroleum fuel?",
        "options": [
            "benzol",
            "ethyl alcohol",
            "methyl alcohol",
            "naphta"
        ],
        "answer": "naphta"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Diesel engine fuels are rated by:",
        "options": [
            "specific gravity",
            "calorific value",
            "cetane number",
            "ocane number"
        ],
        "answer": "cetane number"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 2,
        "question": "Which of the following needs to be filtered in a diesel engine?",
        "options": [
            "air only",
            "lubricating oil only",
            "air and diesel oil only",
            "air, diesel oil and lubricating oil"
        ],
        "answer": "air, diesel oil and lubricating oil"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "An engine in which the fuel is burned directly within the working cylinder",
        "options": [
            "internal combustion engine",
            "external combustion engine",
            "compression ignition engine",
            "spark ignition engine"
        ],
        "answer": "internal combustion engine"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "An engine in which the fuel is burned outside of the power cylinder",
        "options": [
            "internal cobustion engine",
            "external combustion engine",
            "compression ignition engine",
            "spark ignition engine"
        ],
        "answer": "external combustion engine"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "An engine where the ignition is caused by heat of compression.",
        "options": [
            "internal cobustion engine",
            "external combustion engine",
            "compression ignition engine",
            "spark ignition engine"
        ],
        "answer": "compression ignition engine"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "What temperature is required to ignite the fuel oil?",
        "options": [
            "800 to 1000 F",
            "700 to 900 F",
            "900 to 1100 F",
            "1000 to 1200 F"
        ],
        "answer": "800 to 1000 F"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "What air pressure is reqired to produce the required ignition temperature?",
        "options": [
            "350 to 500 psi",
            "250 to 400 psi",
            "450 to 600 psi",
            "150 to 300 psi"
        ],
        "answer": "350 to 500 psi"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "In a four stroke diesel engine, drawing air into the cylinder is what stroke?",
        "options": [
            "first stroke",
            "second stroke",
            "third stroke",
            "fourth stroke"
        ],
        "answer": "first stroke"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "Compressing air in a four stroke cycle is",
        "options": [
            "first stroke",
            "second stroke",
            "third stroke",
            "fourth stroke"
        ],
        "answer": "second stroke"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "Which of the following stokes is produced by the burning gases.",
        "options": [
            "first stroke",
            "second stroke",
            "third stroke",
            "fourth stroke"
        ],
        "answer": "third stroke"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "Which of the following strokes expels the burned gases?",
        "options": [
            "first stroke",
            "second stroke",
            "third stroke",
            "fourth stroke"
        ],
        "answer": "fourth stroke"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "Clearing a cylinder of exhaust gases by forcing into its current of air which provides clean air for the next compression stroke.",
        "options": [
            "scavenging",
            "supercharging",
            "choking",
            "knocking"
        ],
        "answer": "scavenging"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "Increasing the total amount of charging air in the working cylinder of the engine",
        "options": [
            "scavenging",
            "supercharging",
            "choking",
            "knocking"
        ],
        "answer": "supercharging"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "The portion of the piston which extends below piston pin and serves as a guide for the piston and connecting rod.",
        "options": [
            "piston skirt",
            "piston ring",
            "piston scoring",
            "piston seizure"
        ],
        "answer": "piston skirt"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "Rings located in the grooves of the piston usually near the top and near the bottom.",
        "options": [
            "piston skirt",
            "piston ring",
            "piston scoring",
            "piston seizure"
        ],
        "answer": "piston ring"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "Binding of the piston and the cylinder wall as a result of the lubrication having been destroyed by excessive temperature and friction.",
        "options": [
            "piston skirt",
            "piston ring",
            "piston scoring",
            "piston seizure"
        ],
        "answer": "piston seizure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "Grooves in the cylinder wall or piston or both. It is caused by the piston scraping the cylinder wall in its movement without proper lubrication.",
        "options": [
            "piston skirt",
            "piston ring",
            "piston scoring",
            "piston seizure"
        ],
        "answer": "piston scoring"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "A device which automatically governs or controls the speed of an engine.",
        "options": [
            "servomotor",
            "governor",
            "indicator",
            "speedometer"
        ],
        "answer": "governor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "A combination of liquids which do not mix – or combined chemically.",
        "options": [
            "emulsion",
            "deposition",
            "evaporation",
            "separation"
        ],
        "answer": "emulsion"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "What temperature should be the maximum to which lubricating oil is permitted to rise?",
        "options": [
            "not more than 100 F",
            "not more than 200 F",
            "not more than 300 F",
            "not more than 400 F"
        ],
        "answer": "not more than 100 F"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "What air pressure is needed for air starting a diesel engine?",
        "options": [
            "250 psi",
            "150 psi",
            "350 psi",
            "450 psi"
        ],
        "answer": "250 psi"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "At what temperature will self igniting cartridges ignite?",
        "options": [
            "about 200 F",
            "about 190 F",
            "about 210 F",
            "about 250 F"
        ],
        "answer": "about 190 F"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "The fuel is supplied by one pump and switched to each cylinder by a multi outlet rotating valve or ditributor",
        "options": [
            "distributor system",
            "injector system",
            "non injector system",
            "non distributor system"
        ],
        "answer": "distributor system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "This is virtually a distributor two stage pumping system that is, modified distributor system.",
        "options": [
            "distributor system",
            "injector system",
            "non injector system",
            "non distributor system"
        ],
        "answer": "injector system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "A chamber so proportioned with respect to the cleareance volume proper of the cylinder that only about 30% of the combustion takes places with in the chamber itself.",
        "options": [
            "pre combustion chamber",
            "separate combustion chamber",
            "ante combustion chamber",
            "mixed combustion chamber"
        ],
        "answer": "pre combustion chamber"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "The entire charge is ignited in the separate combustion chamber before the initial expansion takes place, passages and against the moving piston.",
        "options": [
            "pre combustion chamber",
            "separate combustion chamber",
            "ante combustion chamber",
            "mixed combustion chamber"
        ],
        "answer": "separate combustion chamber"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "A chamber so designed that injection takes place directly opposite its outlet, the chamber extending backward from the outlet.",
        "options": [
            "pre combustion chamber",
            "separate combustion chamber",
            "ante combustion chamber",
            "air cell chamber"
        ],
        "answer": "ante combustion chamber"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "Fuel is injected only into the main cylinder, during expansion of the burning gasses in the main chamber, when the pressure therein drops below that of the air in the cell.",
        "options": [
            "pre combustion chamber",
            "separate combustion chamber",
            "ante combustion chamber",
            "air cell chamber"
        ],
        "answer": "air cell chamber"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "What is the temperature of the air in the cylinder when the diesel engine is operating at full load?",
        "options": [
            "between 800 and 1100 F",
            "between 800 and 1000 F",
            "between 900 and 1200 F",
            "between 900 and 1100 F"
        ],
        "answer": "between 800 and 1100 F"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "What are the axhaust gas temerature at normal operating conditions?",
        "options": [
            "between 400 and 700 F",
            "between 500 and 800 F",
            "between 300 and 600 F",
            "between 200 and 500 F"
        ],
        "answer": "between 400 and 700 F"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "How are high speed diesel engines started?",
        "options": [
            "by an electric motor",
            "by compressed air",
            "by a diesel fuel",
            "by an electric spark"
        ],
        "answer": "by an electric motor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "What speeds are considered high speed diesel engine?",
        "options": [
            "100 to 2000 rpm or 3000 rpm",
            "100 to 1000 rpm",
            "100 to 1500 rpm",
            "100 to 1750 rpm"
        ],
        "answer": "100 to 2000 rpm or 3000 rpm"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "It is a device used for atomizing or cracking fuel oil and through which the fuel oil is injected into the working cylinders of diesel engines.",
        "options": [
            "atomizer",
            "fuel spray nozzle",
            "injector",
            "cracker"
        ],
        "answer": "atomizer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "What is the proper seat width of a spray valve?",
        "options": [
            "1/16 in.",
            "1/8 in.",
            "1/32 in.",
            "1⁄4 in."
        ],
        "answer": "1/16 in."
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "A cylindrical vessel connected in the fuel system to absorb the shock of the injection pumps and to provide a reservoir at high pressure for supplying an even flow of fuel oil to the cylinders.",
        "options": [
            "absorber",
            "accumulator",
            "governor",
            "injector"
        ],
        "answer": "accumulator"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "How hot are the exhaust gases",
        "options": [
            "400 to 700 F",
            "300 to 600 F",
            "200 to 500 F",
            "500 to 800 F"
        ],
        "answer": "400 to 700 F"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "Which of the following is an automatic device used foor keeping constant air pressure?",
        "options": [
            "relief valve",
            "unloader",
            "strainer",
            "barometer"
        ],
        "answer": "unloader"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "What is the other term of the diameter of the circular cylinder?",
        "options": [
            "bore",
            "stroke",
            "swept volume",
            "clearance"
        ],
        "answer": "bore"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "What do you call the maximum distance traveled by the piston?",
        "options": [
            "bore",
            "stroke",
            "swept volume",
            "clearance"
        ],
        "answer": "stroke"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "Which of the following is the product of the cylinder area and stroke.",
        "options": [
            "bore",
            "stroke",
            "swept volume",
            "clearance"
        ],
        "answer": "swept volume"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "The ratio of the clearance volume to the swept volume.",
        "options": [
            "fractional clearance",
            "compression ratio",
            "expansion ratio",
            "cut off ratio"
        ],
        "answer": "fractional clearance"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "The piston is at maximum reach from the crankshaft to which of the following?",
        "options": [
            "top dead center",
            "bottom dead center",
            "3⁄4 from top center",
            "3⁄4 from bottom center"
        ],
        "answer": "top dead center"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "The piston is closest to the crankshaft to which of the following?",
        "options": [
            "top dead center",
            "bottom dead center",
            "3⁄4 from top center",
            "3⁄4 from bottom center"
        ],
        "answer": "bottom dead center"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "Which of the following engines where the expanding combustion gases act on one end of the piston?",
        "options": [
            "single acting engine",
            "double acting engine",
            "single expansion engine",
            "double expansion engine"
        ],
        "answer": "single acting engine"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "Wich of the following types of engine where the expanding combustion gases act on both ends of the piston?",
        "options": [
            "single acting engine",
            "double actung engine",
            "single expansion engine",
            "double expansion engine"
        ],
        "answer": "double actung engine"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "The compression ratio of a diesel engine varies from about:",
        "options": [
            "13.5 to 17.5",
            "8 to 10",
            "14 to 19",
            "10.5 to 14.5"
        ],
        "answer": "13.5 to 17.5"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "In standard diesel, thermal efficiency was not much higher than about what percent?",
        "options": [
            "35%",
            "30%",
            "40%",
            "50%"
        ],
        "answer": "35%"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "A closed heat exchanger that transfer heat from compressed air to cooler air.",
        "options": [
            "regenerator",
            "intercooler",
            "aftercooler",
            "reheater"
        ],
        "answer": "aftercooler"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "Which of the following is used to improve cold weather starting?",
        "options": [
            "poppet valve",
            "glow plug",
            "check valve",
            "spark plug"
        ],
        "answer": "glow plug"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "The rated power that the manufacturer claims the engine is able to provide on a continuous basis without incurring damage.",
        "options": [
            "brakepower",
            "continuous duty rating",
            "interminnent rating",
            "power rating"
        ],
        "answer": "continuous duty rating"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "What is the peak power rating that can be produced on an occasional basis?",
        "options": [
            "brakepower",
            "continous duty rating",
            "interminnent rating",
            "power rating"
        ],
        "answer": "interminnent rating"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 3,
        "question": "Which of the following is the value of a property that includes the effect of friction?",
        "options": [
            "brake value",
            "friction value",
            "indicated value",
            "actual value"
        ],
        "answer": "brake value"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "Brayton cycle has:",
        "options": [
            "two isentropic and rtwo constant volume pressure",
            "two isentropic and two constant pressure processes",
            "one constant pressure, one constant volume , and two adiabatic processes",
            "two isothermals, one constant volume and a constant pressure processes"
        ],
        "answer": "two isentropic and two constant pressure processes"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "Brayton cycle cannot be used in reciprocating engines even for same adiabatic compression ratio and work output because:",
        "options": [
            "Otto cycle is highly efficient",
            "Brayton cycle is less efficient",
            "Brayton cycle is foe slow speed engines only",
            "large volume of low pressure air cannot be efficiency handled in reciprocating engines"
        ],
        "answer": "large volume of low pressure air cannot be efficiency handled in reciprocating"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "Which cycle is generally used for gas turbine?",
        "options": [
            "Otto cycle",
            "Dual cycle",
            "Carnot cycle",
            "Brayton cycle"
        ],
        "answer": "Brayton cycle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "When r is the compression ratio, the efficiency of Brayton cycle is given by:",
        "options": [
            "1 – 1/r(k−1)/k",
            "1 – 1/rk−1",
            "1 – 1/rk",
            "1 – 1/r"
        ],
        "answer": "1 – 1/r(k−1)/k"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "A regenerator in a gas turbine:",
        "options": [
            "reduces heat loss during exhaust",
            "allows use of higher compression ratio",
            "improves thermal efficiency",
            "allows use of fuels of interior quality"
        ],
        "answer": "improves thermal efficiency"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "Which of the following compressor is generally used for gas turbines?",
        "options": [
            "lobe type",
            "centrifugal type",
            "axial flow type",
            "reciprocating type"
        ],
        "answer": "axial flow type"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "The constant pressure gas turbine works on the principle of:",
        "options": [
            "carnot cycle",
            "Bell – Coleman cycle",
            "Rankine cycle",
            "Brayton cycle"
        ],
        "answer": "Brayton cycle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "What type of gas turbine is used in air craft?",
        "options": [
            "open cycle type",
            "closed cycle type with reheating",
            "closed type with reheating and regeneration",
            "open cycle type with reheating, regeneration and intercooling"
        ],
        "answer": "open cycle type"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "In a gas turbine combined cycle plant, a waste heat boiler is used to:",
        "options": [
            "heat air from intercooler",
            "gases from regenerator",
            "recover heat from exhaust gases",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "recover heat from exhaust gases"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "Overall efficiency of a gas turbine is:",
        "options": [
            "equal to Carnot cycle efficiency",
            "equal to Rankine cycle efficiency",
            "less than Otto cycle efficiency",
            "more than Otto or Diesel cycle efficiency"
        ],
        "answer": "less than Otto cycle efficiency"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "Which of the following turbine has least weight per bhp development?",
        "options": [
            "Simple open cycle gas turbine",
            "Open cycle gas turbine with inter-cooling and reheating",
            "Open cycle gas turbine with inter-cooling reheating and regenerating",
            "Closed cycle gas turbine"
        ],
        "answer": "Simple open cycle gas turbine"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "Which of the following is/are advantage of closed cycle gas turbine over open cycle gas turbine?",
        "options": [
            "no containing of working substance with combustion gases",
            "inferior quality fuel can be used",
            "low maintenance costs",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "all of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "The range of compression ratio in a gas turbine is :",
        "options": [
            "3 to 5",
            "5 to 8",
            "8 to 12",
            "12 to 20"
        ],
        "answer": "5 to 8"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "A constant volume combustion gas turbine operates on:",
        "options": [
            "Ericson cycle",
            "Joule cycle",
            "Brayton cycle",
            "Atkinson cycle"
        ],
        "answer": "Atkinson cycle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "Heat exchanger used to provide heat transfer between the exhaust gases and the    air prior to its entrance to combustor.",
        "options": [
            "Evaporator",
            "Combustion chamber",
            "Regenerator",
            "Heater"
        ],
        "answer": "Regenerator"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "How does the value for work for unit mass flow of air in the compressor and turbine influenced by the addition of a regenerator?",
        "options": [
            "Slightly increased",
            "Unchanged",
            "Greatly decreased",
            "Greatly increased"
        ],
        "answer": "Unchanged"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "What is the ideal cycle for gas turbine work?",
        "options": [
            "Brayton cycle",
            "Stag combined  cycle",
            "Bottom cycle",
            "Ericson cycle"
        ],
        "answer": "Brayton cycle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "Brayton cycle cannot be used in reciprocating engines even for same adiabatic compression ratio and work output because:",
        "options": [
            "Brayton cycle is highly efficient",
            "Brayton cycle is for low speed engines only",
            "Brayton cycle needs large air-fuel ratio",
            "Large volume of low pressure air cannot be efficient handled in reciprocating engines"
        ],
        "answer": "Large volume of low pressure air cannot be efficient handled in reciprocating engines"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "In order to increase the gas velocity gas turbines generally have fixed nozzles. This is allow the:",
        "options": [
            "Compression of gases",
            "Condensation of gases",
            "Expansion of gases",
            "Evaporation of gases"
        ],
        "answer": "Expansion of gases"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "Combustion turbines or gas turbines are the preferred combustion engines in application much above _________.",
        "options": [
            "8 Mw",
            "9 mW",
            "10 MW",
            "7 MW"
        ],
        "answer": "10 MW"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "Large units gas turbine regularly operate:",
        "options": [
            "In 100 gas to 200 MW range",
            "In 50 to 100 MW range",
            "Over 150 MW",
            "Below 150 MW"
        ],
        "answer": "In 100 gas to 200 MW range"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "Small units gas turbine operate below",
        "options": [
            "20 MW",
            "12 MW",
            "30 MW",
            "24 MW"
        ],
        "answer": "30 MW"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "Heavy duty gas turbine typically have:",
        "options": [
            "Double shafts",
            "Single shafts",
            "Triple shafts",
            "Quadruple shafts"
        ],
        "answer": "Single shafts"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "Which of the following is basically a jet engine that exhausts into a turbine generator?",
        "options": [
            "Aeroderivative gas turbine",
            "Industrial gas turbine",
            "Brayton engine",
            "Joule turbine"
        ],
        "answer": "Aeroderivative gas turbine"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "Most aeroderivative combustion turbine produce less than:",
        "options": [
            "20 MW",
            "30 MW",
            "40 MW",
            "50 MW"
        ],
        "answer": "40 MW"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "The compression ratio based on pressure in the compression stage in a gas turbine is typically:",
        "options": [
            "11 to 16",
            "5 to 8",
            "12 to 18",
            "8 to 14"
        ],
        "answer": "11 to 16"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "The compression ratio based on pressure of heavy duty gas turbine is in the range of ________.",
        "options": [
            "14 to 15",
            "19 to 21",
            "11 to 16",
            "16 to 18"
        ],
        "answer": "14 to 15"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "Aeroderivative combustion turbine have higher compression ratio typically:",
        "options": [
            "14 to 15",
            "19 to 21",
            "11 to 16",
            "16 to 18"
        ],
        "answer": "19 to 21"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "Most heavy duty combustion turbines have how many compression stages?",
        "options": [
            "14 to 16",
            "18 to 20",
            "10 to 12",
            "16 to 18"
        ],
        "answer": "16 to 18"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "The temperature of the gas entering the expander section is typically:",
        "options": [
            "1200 C to 1290 C",
            "1000 C to 1200 C",
            "1500 C to 1490 C",
            "1300 C to 1390 C"
        ],
        "answer": "1200 C to 1290 C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "The exhaust temperature which makes the exhaust an ideal heat source for combined cycles is typically:",
        "options": [
            "540 C to 590 C",
            "600 C to 650 C",
            "300 C to 350 C",
            "440 Cto 490 C"
        ],
        "answer": "540 C to 590 C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "Most combustion turbines have:",
        "options": [
            "2 to 3 expander stages",
            "3 to 4 expander stages",
            "4 to 5 expander stages",
            "1 to 2 expander stages"
        ],
        "answer": "3 to 4 expander stages"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "The exhaust flow rate in modern heavy duty turbines per 100 MW is approximately:",
        "options": [
            "240 to 250 kg/s",
            "140 to 150 kg/s",
            "340 to 350 kg/s",
            "440 to 450 kg/s"
        ],
        "answer": "240 to 250 kg/s"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "The Brayton gas turbine cycle is also known as:",
        "options": [
            "Joule cycle",
            "Stirling cycle",
            "Ericsson cycle",
            "Atkinson cycle"
        ],
        "answer": "Joule cycle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "Approximately how many percent of the turbine power is used to drive the high efficiency compressor?",
        "options": [
            "50 to 75 %",
            "60 to 85 %",
            "45 to 70 %",
            "30 to 55 %"
        ],
        "answer": "50 to 75 %"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "Depending on the turbine construction details, the temperature of the air entering the turbine will be between:",
        "options": [
            "650 C to 1000 C",
            "750 C to 1100 C",
            "550 C to 950 C",
            "850 C to 1200 C"
        ],
        "answer": "650 C to 1000 C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "Which of the following engines are typically used by Turbojet and turboprop?",
        "options": [
            "Open combustors",
            "Closed combustors",
            "Turbo combustors",
            "High combustors"
        ],
        "answer": "Open combustors"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "The full load thermal efficiency of existing heavy duty combustion turbines in simple cycle is approximately:",
        "options": [
            "34 to 36 %",
            "30 to 32 %",
            "40 to 42 %",
            "26 to 28 %"
        ],
        "answer": "34 to 36 %"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "New combustion turbine on the cutting edge of technology ( Advanced turbine system ) are able to achieve",
        "options": [
            "38 to 38.5 %",
            "36 to 36.5 %",
            "40 to 40.5 %",
            "34 to 34.5 %"
        ],
        "answer": "38 to 38.5 %"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "Aeroderivative commonly achieve efficiencies up to:",
        "options": [
            "42 %",
            "38 %",
            "45 %",
            "35 %"
        ],
        "answer": "42 %"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "Which of the following is the typically backwork ratio of gas turbine?",
        "options": [
            "50 to 75 %",
            "40 to 65 %",
            "30 to 55 %",
            "35 to 60 %"
        ],
        "answer": "50 to 75 %"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "Which of the following is an example of a generator?",
        "options": [
            "A counter flow heat exchanger",
            "A cross flow heat exchanger",
            "A mixed flow heat exchanger",
            "A parallel heat exchanger"
        ],
        "answer": "A cross flow heat exchanger"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "Which of the following is an effect of having a regenerator?",
        "options": [
            "Less heat is added",
            "Compressor work is reduced",
            "Turbine work is increased",
            "Compressor work is increased"
        ],
        "answer": "Less heat is added"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "A regenerator in a gas turbine has no effect i:",
        "options": [
            "Compressor and turbine work",
            "Heat added",
            "Thermal efficiency",
            "Combustor"
        ],
        "answer": "Compressor and turbine work"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "In Brayton cycle multiple stages of compression and expansion will _________.",
        "options": [
            "Increase thermal efficiency",
            "Decrease thermal efficiency",
            "Limit thermal efficiency",
            "Control efficiency"
        ],
        "answer": "Increase thermal efficiency"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "In Brayton cycle, reheating and intercooling will __________.",
        "options": [
            "Increase thermal efficiency",
            "Decrease thermal efficiency",
            "Limit thermal efficiency",
            "Control efficiency"
        ],
        "answer": "Increase thermal efficiency"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "In a Brayton cycle, reheating has no effect in:",
        "options": [
            "Heat added",
            "Thermal efficiency",
            "Backwork ratio",
            "Network"
        ],
        "answer": "Heat added"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "In a Brayton cycle, intercooling has no effect:",
        "options": [
            "Turbine work",
            "Thermal efficiency",
            "Backwork ratio",
            "Network"
        ],
        "answer": "Turbine work"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "If Wt is the turbine power and Wc is the compressor power then the backwork ratio is",
        "options": [
            "Wt /Wc",
            "Wc /Wt",
            "Wt −Wc Wt",
            "Wt−Wc Wc"
        ],
        "answer": "Wc /Wt"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "If Wt is the turbine power and Wc is the compressor power then network is:",
        "options": [
            "Wt × Wc",
            "Wc / Wt",
            "Wt − Wc",
            "Wt + Wc"
        ],
        "answer": "Wt − Wc"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 4,
        "question": "Physical limitation usually preclude more than how many stages of intercooling and reheating?",
        "options": [
            "2",
            "3",
            "4",
            "5"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "Which of the following factors does bursting pressure of boiler does’nt depend?",
        "options": [
            "Tensile strength of the shell",
            "Thickness of the shell",
            "Diameter of the shell",
            "Shear strength"
        ],
        "answer": "Shear strength"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "Which of the following factors does working pressure boiler does’nt depends?",
        "options": [
            "Tensile strength of the shell",
            "Thickness of the shell",
            "Factor of safety",
            "Type of fuel being fired"
        ],
        "answer": "Type of fuel being fired"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "Total solid impurities in feed water for a boiler depends upon",
        "options": [
            "Boiler pressure",
            "Quantity of steam to be generated",
            "Type of fuel available",
            "Quantity of steam"
        ],
        "answer": "Boiler pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "A high pressure chamber or a device in which be paths of rapidly moving particles can be observed and photographed.",
        "options": [
            "Cloud chamber",
            "Combustion chamber",
            "Fission chamber",
            "Air chamber"
        ],
        "answer": "Cloud chamber"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "The formation of gas bubbles in a liquid is called",
        "options": [
            "Bubbling",
            "Foaming",
            "Priming",
            "Carryover"
        ],
        "answer": "Foaming"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "How many check valves should be provided between any feed pump and boiler?",
        "options": [
            "1",
            "2",
            "3",
            "4"
        ],
        "answer": "2"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "The water level inside the boiler is indicated by the",
        "options": [
            "Baffles",
            "Fusible plug",
            "Water walls",
            "Water column"
        ],
        "answer": "Water column"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "What is the highest pressure under which distinguishable liquid and vapor phases can exist is equilibrium?",
        "options": [
            "Maximum pressure",
            "Atmosphere",
            "Critical pressure",
            "Peak pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "Critical pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "What is the average fuel – oil temperature range of the oil in the discharge line to the boiler?",
        "options": [
            "180 – 200°F",
            "240 – 260°F",
            "160 – 180°F",
            "140 – 160°F"
        ],
        "answer": "180 – 200°F"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "The lowest permissible water level of a boiler with an internal furnace is ________ the height of the shell.",
        "options": [
            "1⁄2",
            "1/3",
            "1⁄4",
            "1/5"
        ],
        "answer": "1/3"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "In case of steam engine the cut off ratio is the ratio of",
        "options": [
            "Pressure at cut off to supply pressure",
            "Pressure at cut off to exhaust pressure",
            "Pressure at cut off to mean effective pressure",
            "Fraction of piston stroke which the piston has traveled when cut of occurs"
        ],
        "answer": "Fraction of piston stroke which the piston has traveled when cut of occurs"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "In a condensing steam engine",
        "options": [
            "Condensed steam is supplied",
            "Steam condenses inside cylinder",
            "Steam condenses as soon as it leaves the cylinder",
            "Exhaust steam is condensed in a condenser"
        ],
        "answer": "Exhaust steam is condensed in a condenser"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "Flows through the nozzles and diffusers with increasing fluid velocity will create an equivalent",
        "options": [
            "Decrease in the static enthalpy of fluid",
            "Increase in the static enthalpy of fluid",
            "Decrease in the internal energy of fluid",
            "Decrease in the dynamic enthalpy of fluid"
        ],
        "answer": "Decrease in the static enthalpy of fluid"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "The term V2/2cp responds to the temperature rise during such a process and is called the",
        "options": [
            "Kinetic temperature",
            "High temperature",
            "Dynamic temperature",
            "Elevation temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "Dynamic temperature"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "All of the following mechanism can supply heat to a thermodynamics system except",
        "options": [
            "Conduction",
            "Natural convection",
            "Adiabatic expansion",
            "Radiation"
        ],
        "answer": "Adiabatic expansion"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "The flow through the nozzle is",
        "options": [
            "Isentropic",
            "polytropic",
            "Isobaric",
            "Isovolumic"
        ],
        "answer": "Isentropic"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "If the reservoir is sufficiently large, the nozzle inlet velocity is",
        "options": [
            "Maximum",
            "Negative",
            "Positive",
            "Zero"
        ],
        "answer": "Zero"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "Which of the following is the pressure applied at the nozzle discharge section?",
        "options": [
            "Stagnant pressure",
            "Critical pressure",
            "Back pressure",
            "Atmospheric pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "Back pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "When the back pressure is reduced to lowest exit pressure, the mass flow reach a maximum value and the flow is said to be:",
        "options": [
            "Stacked",
            "Choked",
            "Stuck-up",
            "Clog-up"
        ],
        "answer": "Choked"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "An increase stagnation pressure will the mass flux through the:",
        "options": [
            "Diverging nozzle",
            "Converging nozzle",
            "Converging – diverging nozzle",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Converging nozzle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "A converging – diverging nozzle is the standard equipment in:",
        "options": [
            "Subsonic aircraft",
            "Supersonic aircraft",
            "Hypersonic aircraft",
            "Trisonic aircraft"
        ],
        "answer": "Supersonic aircraft"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "For back pressure values, abrupt changes in fluid properties occur in a very thin section of converging – diverging nozzle under supersonic flow conditions, creating",
        "options": [
            "Sound wave",
            "Tidal wave",
            "Shock waves",
            "None of these",
            "Fanno Line",
            "Straight Line",
            "Willan’s Line",
            "Cross Cut Line"
        ],
        "answer": "Fanno Line"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "Is the locus of states which have the same value of stagnation enthalpy and mass flux are called:",
        "options": [
            "Fanno Line",
            "Straight Line",
            "Willan’s Line",
            "Cross Cut Line"
        ],
        "answer": "Fanno Line"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "Combination of mass and momentum equations into a single and plotted in h-s plane yield a curve called:",
        "options": [
            "Fair line",
            "Freh line",
            "Cutting line",
            "Rayleigh line"
        ],
        "answer": "Rayleigh line"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "Generally steam turbines in power station operate at",
        "options": [
            "3000 rpm",
            "1000 rpm",
            "4000 rpm",
            "575 rpm"
        ],
        "answer": "3000 rpm"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "Which of the following shows the relation of the steam consumption and the load of steam turbine – generation?",
        "options": [
            "Dalton’s line",
            "Willan’s line",
            "Jonval’s line",
            "Rankine’s line"
        ],
        "answer": "Willan’s line"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "An inventor proposes to develop electrical power by withdrawing heat from the geyser field of northern California and converting it all to work in power turbines. This scheme will not work because:",
        "options": [
            "The geyser field have only a limited lifetime",
            "The salinity of the steam is too great",
            "It violates the first law of thermodynamics",
            "It violates the second law of thermodynamics"
        ],
        "answer": "It violates the second law of thermodynamics"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "The isentropic efficiency of a turbine is given by",
        "options": [
            "The ratio of actual to ideal energy extracted",
            "The ratio of actual of ideal energy inputted",
            "The ratio of ideal to actual energy extracted",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "The ratio of actual to ideal energy extracted"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "Which of the following is not a main part of a typical coal burner?",
        "options": [
            "Air registers",
            "Nozzle",
            "Atomizer",
            "Ignitor"
        ],
        "answer": "Atomizer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "Measure of ability of a boiler to transfer the heat given by the furnace to the water and steam is:",
        "options": [
            "Grate efficiency",
            "Stroke efficiency",
            "Furnace efficiency",
            "Boiler efficiency"
        ],
        "answer": "Boiler efficiency"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "A goose neck is installed in the line connecting a statement gauge to a boiler to:",
        "options": [
            "Maintain constant steam flow",
            "Protect the gauge element",
            "Prevent steam knocking",
            "Maintain steam pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "Protect the gauge element"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "Which of the following is a great advance of a fire tube boiler?",
        "options": [
            "Steam pressure is not ready",
            "Contains a large volume of water and requires long interval of time to raise steam and not so flexible as to changes in steam demand",
            "Cannot use impure water",
            "Radiation losses are higher because fire is inside the boiler and surrounded by water"
        ],
        "answer": "Contains a large volume of water and requires long interval of time to raise steam and"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "One of the following task which is an example of preventive maintenance is",
        "options": [
            "Cleaning the cup on a rotary cup burner",
            "Cleaning a completely clog oil strainer",
            "Replacing a leaking valve",
            "Replacing a blown fuse"
        ],
        "answer": "Cleaning the cup on a rotary cup burner"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "The carbon dioxide (CO2) percentage in the flue gas of an efficiency fired boiler should be approximately",
        "options": [
            "1 %",
            "12 %",
            "18 %",
            "20 %"
        ],
        "answer": "12 %"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "When droplets of water are carried by steam in the boiler.",
        "options": [
            "Priming",
            "Foaming",
            "Carryover",
            "Embrittlement"
        ],
        "answer": "Priming"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "The process in which heat energy is transferred to a thermal energy storage device is known as:",
        "options": [
            "Adiabatic",
            "Regeneration",
            "Intercooling",
            "Isentropic"
        ],
        "answer": "Regeneration"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "When the boiler pressure increase or when the exhaust pressure decrease, the amount of moisture.",
        "options": [
            "Increase",
            "Decrease",
            "Constant",
            "Zero"
        ],
        "answer": "Increase"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "When the number of reheat stages in a reheat cycle is increased, the average temperature",
        "options": [
            "Increase",
            "Decrease",
            "Is constant",
            "Is zero"
        ],
        "answer": "Increase"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "A heat transfer device that reduce thermodynamics fluid from its vapor phase to its liquid phase such as in vapor compression refrigeration plant or in a condensing steam plant.",
        "options": [
            "Flash vessel",
            "Cooling tower",
            "Condenser",
            "Steam separator"
        ],
        "answer": "Condenser"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "A simultaneous generation of electricity and steam (or heat) in a single power plant.",
        "options": [
            "Gas turbine",
            "Steam turbine",
            "Waste heat recovery",
            "Cogeneration"
        ],
        "answer": "Cogeneration"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "Is one whose pressure is higher than the saturation pressure corresponding to its temperature.",
        "options": [
            "Compressed liquid",
            "Saturated liquid",
            "Saturated vapor",
            "Superheated vapor"
        ],
        "answer": "Compressed liquid"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "In a steam generator with good combustion control, what occurs if the load is increased?",
        "options": [
            "Air temperature leaving air heater decreases",
            "Air temperature entering air heater increases",
            "Furnace pressure is approximately constant",
            "Economizer gas outlet temperature decreases"
        ],
        "answer": "Furnace pressure is approximately constant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "Total solid impurities in feed water for a boiler depends upon",
        "options": [
            "Boiler pressure",
            "Type of fuel available",
            "Quantity of steam to be generated",
            "Quantity of steam"
        ],
        "answer": "Boiler pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "The gaseous state of water.",
        "options": [
            "Water gas",
            "Blue gas",
            "Water vapor",
            "Yellow gas"
        ],
        "answer": "Water vapor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "A liquid boils when its vapor pressure equals",
        "options": [
            "the gage pressure",
            "the critical pressure",
            "the ambient pressure",
            "one standard atmosphere"
        ],
        "answer": "the ambient pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "What are the main components in a combined cycle power plant?",
        "options": [
            "Diesel engine and air compressor",
            "Gas engine and waste heat boiler",
            "Steam boiler and turbine",
            "Nuclear reactor and steam boiler"
        ],
        "answer": "Gas engine and waste heat boiler"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "A change in efficiency of combustion in a boiler can usually be determined by comparing the previously recorded readings with the current readings of the __________.",
        "options": [
            "Stack temperature and CO",
            "Over the fire drop and CO",
            "Ringleman chart and CO2",
            "Stack temperature and CO2"
        ],
        "answer": "Stack temperature and CO2"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "A boiler steam gage should have a range of at least",
        "options": [
            "One half the working steam pressure",
            "1 and 1⁄2 times the maximum allowable working pressure",
            "The working steam pressure",
            "Twice the maximum allowable working pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "1 and 1⁄2 times the maximum allowable working pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "In a water tube boiler, heat and gases of combustion passed:",
        "options": [
            "Through the combustion chamber only",
            "Through the tubes",
            "Away the tubes",
            "Around the tubes"
        ],
        "answer": "Around the tubes"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "A chemical water of feedwater treatment which uses calcium hydroxide and sodium carbonate as reagents.",
        "options": [
            "Thermal treatment",
            "Lime soda treatment",
            "Demineralization process",
            "Ion exchange treatment"
        ],
        "answer": "Lime soda treatment"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "The thermal efficiency of gas-vapor cycle as compared to steam turbine or gas turbine is",
        "options": [
            "Greater than",
            "Less than",
            "Lower than",
            "Equal to"
        ],
        "answer": "Greater than"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "A rapid increase in boiler pressure occur when there is :",
        "options": [
            "Moderate drop in steam load",
            "Constant drop in steam load",
            "Abrupt drop in steam load",
            "Gradual drop in steam load"
        ],
        "answer": "Abrupt drop in steam load"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "The most economical and low maintenance cost condenser.",
        "options": [
            "Water – cooled",
            "Air – cooled",
            "Evaporative",
            "Sub – cooled"
        ],
        "answer": "Air – cooled"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "What is commonly used done to system when the turbine has excessive moisture?",
        "options": [
            "Frosting",
            "Diffusing",
            "Reheating",
            "Dehumidifying"
        ],
        "answer": "Reheating"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "What is the result when the fluid kinetic energy during a stagnation process is transformed to enthalpy?",
        "options": [
            "Decrease in fluid volume",
            "Rise in the temp. and pressure fluid",
            "Rise in fluid’s volume",
            "Decrease in the temp. and pressure of fluid"
        ],
        "answer": "Rise in the temp. and pressure fluid"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "How can the average temperature during heat rejection process of a Rankine cycle be decreased?",
        "options": [
            "Increase boiler pressure",
            "Increase turbine pressure",
            "Increase condenser pressure",
            "Reduce turbine exit pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "Reduce turbine exit pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "Which of the following ascertains the effectiveness and the size of a condenser?",
        "options": [
            "Number of passes",
            "Thickness of the shell",
            "Tube sizes",
            "Heat transfer"
        ],
        "answer": "Heat transfer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "A boiler has a bursting pressure, BP, of 600 kPa and a factor of safety, FS, of 8 is employed in design. As an engineer, would you advice to have a working pressure, WP, of 500 kPa?",
        "options": [
            "No, WP must be higher than 500 kPa",
            "No, WP is only 75 kPa at FS of 8",
            "Yes, since BP is 600 Pa",
            "Yes, to attain better efficiency"
        ],
        "answer": "No, WP is only 75 kPa at FS of 8"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "What cycle is used in vapor cycle of steam power plant?",
        "options": [
            "Brayton cycle",
            "Diesel cycle",
            "Ericsson cycle",
            "Rankine cycle"
        ],
        "answer": "Rankine cycle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 5,
        "question": "Gauge cock in the boiler is designed to determine:",
        "options": [
            "Level of steam",
            "Specific heat",
            "Level of water",
            "Pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "Level of water"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "Refers to the internal heat from the earth.",
        "options": [
            "Geothermal",
            "Thermal energy",
            "Molten heat",
            "Tectonic heat"
        ],
        "answer": "Geothermal"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "A rock – forming crystalline mixed silicate which constitute about 60 % of the earth’s surface.",
        "options": [
            "Soil",
            "Feldspar",
            "Flux",
            "Flint"
        ],
        "answer": "Feldspar"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "A compound rock, a crypto – crystalline from of silica, which is dens, tough, breaking with a conchoidal fracture.",
        "options": [
            "Gravel",
            "Stalactite",
            "Flint",
            "Flux"
        ],
        "answer": "Flint"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "is the process of using injection wells to buble air through groundwater.",
        "options": [
            "Air stripping",
            "Staged combustion",
            "Sparging",
            "Soil washing"
        ],
        "answer": "Sparging"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "A popular term used by utilities to mean upgrading existing plant.",
        "options": [
            "Replanting",
            "Repowering",
            "Recharging",
            "Reorganizing"
        ],
        "answer": "Repowering"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "A dense, fine grained, light colored igneous rock which is rich in silica.",
        "options": [
            "Felsite",
            "Feldspar",
            "Flint",
            "Flux"
        ],
        "answer": "Felsite"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "An opening in lava or in volcanic area through which steam and other hot gases are escaping into the air is called:",
        "options": [
            "Fumarole",
            "Volcanic leaks",
            "Seismic outlets",
            "Seismic leaks"
        ],
        "answer": "Fumarole"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "Tidal power is the power generated from:",
        "options": [
            "Waves of the ocean",
            "Rise and fall tides",
            "Thermal energy of ocean water",
            "Raw sea water"
        ],
        "answer": "Rise and fall tides"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "Convert chemical energy directly into electrical energy.",
        "options": [
            "Fuel oil",
            "Magnetohydrodynamic generator",
            "Battery",
            "Thermoelectric generator"
        ],
        "answer": "Fuel oil"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "Generates a voltage from incident light, usually light the visible region.",
        "options": [
            "Photovoltaic cell",
            "Solar cell",
            "Dry cell",
            "A or B"
        ],
        "answer": "A or B"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "All of the following terms are synonymous quantity of electromagnetic theory except:",
        "options": [
            "Packets",
            "Corpuscles",
            "X-rays",
            "Photons"
        ],
        "answer": "X-rays"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "In geothermal power plant waste water is:",
        "options": [
            "Recirculated after cooling in cooling lowers",
            "Discharged into sea",
            "Evaporated in ponds",
            "Discharge back to earth"
        ],
        "answer": "Discharge back to earth"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "In a liquid-dominated geothermal plant, what process occurs when the saturated steam passes through the turbine?",
        "options": [
            "Isobaric",
            "Polytropic",
            "Isometric",
            "Isentropic"
        ],
        "answer": "Polytropic"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "What do you call a conversion technology that yields electricity straight from sunlight without the aid of a working substance like gas or steam without the use of any mechanical cycle?",
        "options": [
            "Power conversion",
            "Stirling cycle conversion",
            "Solar thermal conversion",
            "Photovoltaic-energy conversion"
        ],
        "answer": "Photovoltaic-energy conversion"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "Tidal plant power is attractive because it has:",
        "options": [
            "Low head and intermittent power",
            "High lead",
            "Cheap energy source",
            "Expensive energy source"
        ],
        "answer": "Cheap energy source"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "What do you call a conversion technology that yield electricity straight from sunlight without the aid of working substance like gas or steam without the use any mechanical cycle?",
        "options": [
            "Power conversion",
            "Stirling cycle conversion",
            "Solar thermal conversion",
            "Photovoltaic-energy conversion"
        ],
        "answer": "Photovoltaic-energy conversion"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "Tidal power plant is attractive because it has:",
        "options": [
            "Low head and intermittent power",
            "High head",
            "Cheap energy source",
            "Expensive energy source"
        ],
        "answer": "Cheap energy source"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "Tidal power is the power generated from:",
        "options": [
            "Waves of the ocean",
            "Rise and fall tides",
            "Thermal energy of the ocean water",
            "Raw sea water"
        ],
        "answer": "Rise and fall tides"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "Converts chemical energy directly into electrical energy.",
        "options": [
            "Fuel cell",
            "Magnetohydrodynamic generator",
            "Battery",
            "Thermoelectric generator"
        ],
        "answer": "Fuel cell"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "Generates a voltage from incident light, usually light in the visible region.",
        "options": [
            "Photovoltaic cell",
            "Solar cell",
            "Dry cell",
            "A or B"
        ],
        "answer": "A or B"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "The statement that the product of the error in the measured determination of a particle’s position and its momentum is of the order of Planck’s constant h is known as:",
        "options": [
            "Bohr’s theory",
            "D’Alembert’s paradox",
            "The Heisenberg uncertainly principle",
            "Planck’s law"
        ],
        "answer": "The Heisenberg uncertainly principle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "The flow process through shock wave is high irreversible and cannot be approximated as being:",
        "options": [
            "Polytropic",
            "Isometric",
            "Hyperbolic",
            "Isentropic"
        ],
        "answer": "Isentropic"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "Beaufort scale is used for measuring what?",
        "options": [
            "Beta and gamma radiations",
            "Wind speed",
            "Insolation",
            "Depth of sea"
        ],
        "answer": "Wind speed"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "Betz law is widely used in:",
        "options": [
            "MHD system",
            "Solar cell",
            "Geothermal power",
            "Wind mills"
        ],
        "answer": "Wind mills"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "Rocks having excessive internal stresses may produces spalling. This rock are called as _________.",
        "options": [
            "Stratified rocks",
            "Popping rocks",
            "Crushed rocks",
            "Swelling rocks"
        ],
        "answer": "Stratified rocks"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "Solar energy arrives at the outside of the earth’s atmosphere at an average rate of _______.",
        "options": [
            "1.354 kW/m2",
            "1.543 kW/m2",
            "2.354 kW/m2",
            "2.543 kW/m2"
        ],
        "answer": "1.354 kW/m2"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "How many percent of solar energy survives absorption and reflection?",
        "options": [
            "40 to 70 %",
            "30 to 60 %",
            "50 to 80 %",
            "20 to 50 %"
        ],
        "answer": "40 to 70 %"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "Solar energy is captured in:",
        "options": [
            "Sun capturer",
            "Solar collector",
            "Sun collector",
            "Green house capturer"
        ],
        "answer": "Solar collector"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "Which of the following solar collector are essential wide, flat boxes with clear plastic or glass covering known as the glazing.",
        "options": [
            "Flat plate collectors",
            "Concentrating collectors",
            "Focusing collector",
            "Evacuated tube collector"
        ],
        "answer": "Flat plate collectors"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "Which of the following collectors use mirrors and a lenses to focus the suns energy on a small absorbs area.",
        "options": [
            "Flat plate collector",
            "Concentrating collector",
            "Non focusing collectors",
            "Evacuated tube collectors"
        ],
        "answer": "Concentrating collector"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "Which of the following collector are more complex to their efficiencies are higher?",
        "options": [
            "Flat plate collector",
            "Concentrating collector",
            "Focusing collectors",
            "Evacuated tube collectors"
        ],
        "answer": "Evacuated tube collectors"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "Which of the following collectors are useful when extremely hot transfer fluid is needed and are general limited to commercial projects?",
        "options": [
            "Flat plate collector",
            "Concentrating collector",
            "Focusing collectors",
            "Evacuated tube collectors"
        ],
        "answer": "Evacuated tube collectors"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "The shading factor in calculating the heat absorbed by the solar collector has a value of approximately”",
        "options": [
            "0.95 to 0.97",
            "0.85 to 0.87",
            "0.75 to 0.77",
            "0.65 to 0.67"
        ],
        "answer": "0.95 to 0.97"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "The ratio of energy absorbed by the transfer fluid to the original incident energy striking the collector.",
        "options": [
            "Collector efficiency",
            "Sun efficiency",
            "Shading factor",
            "Absorptance"
        ],
        "answer": "Collector efficiency"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "As the difference between the ambient air and average plate (or inlet) temperatures increase, what happens to the collector efficiency?",
        "options": [
            "Increase",
            "Decrease",
            "Constant",
            "No effect"
        ],
        "answer": "Decrease"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "Distributed collector system is also known as:",
        "options": [
            "Trough electric system",
            "Central receiver system",
            "Power tower system",
            "Dish/Stirling system"
        ],
        "answer": "Trough electric system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "Center receiver system is also known as:",
        "options": [
            "Trough electric system",
            "Distributed collector",
            "Power tower system",
            "Dish/ Stirling system"
        ],
        "answer": "Power tower system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "Which of the following main approaches to solar energy generating systems describes that parabolic tracking trough concentrator focus sunlight on evacuated glass tubes that run along the collectors focal lines.",
        "options": [
            "Trough electric system",
            "Central receiver system",
            "Power tower system",
            "Dish/Stirling system"
        ],
        "answer": "Trough electric system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "Trough electric technology is relatively mature but due to the flow temperature, average annual thermal efficiencies are only:",
        "options": [
            "10 to 15 %",
            "5 to 10 %",
            "15 to 20 %",
            "25 to 30 %"
        ],
        "answer": "10 to 15 %"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "A field of heliostats or tracking mirror concentrates solar energy onto a receiver on a central tower.",
        "options": [
            "Trough electric system",
            "Distributed collector system",
            "Power tower system",
            "Dish/ Stirling system"
        ],
        "answer": "Power tower system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "In a power tower system typical thermal efficiencies is in the range:",
        "options": [
            "10 to 15 %",
            "5 to 10 %",
            "15 to 20 %",
            "25 to 30 %"
        ],
        "answer": "15 to 20 %"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "A dish engine system has an efficiency of",
        "options": [
            "10 to 15 %",
            "5 to 10 %",
            "14 to 19 %",
            "24 to 28 %"
        ],
        "answer": "24 to 28 %"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "Practical and economic issues limit trough electric system about:",
        "options": [
            "200 MW",
            "100 MW",
            "300 MW",
            "400 MW"
        ],
        "answer": "200 MW"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "Practical and economic issues limit tower electricity system to approximately”",
        "options": [
            "100 to 200 MW",
            "150 to 250 MW",
            "100 to 300 MW",
            "150 to 400 MW"
        ],
        "answer": "100 to 300 MW"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "Thermal efficiency of a geothermal power plant is approximately:",
        "options": [
            "30 %",
            "22 %",
            "35 %",
            "15 %"
        ],
        "answer": "22 %"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "A flash stem cycle can be used if the hot water temperature is approximately:",
        "options": [
            "165 C or higher",
            "150 C or higher",
            "145 C to 200 C",
            "Below 200 C"
        ],
        "answer": "165 C or higher"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "A binary cycle using a separate heat transfer fluid if the temperature of the hot water is between approximately _________.",
        "options": [
            "165 C and 120 C",
            "200 C and 150 C",
            "225 C and 175 C",
            "300 C and higher"
        ],
        "answer": "165 C and 120 C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "For every kilometer of depth, the temperature of the earth’s crust increase by:",
        "options": [
            "30 F",
            "40 F",
            "50 F",
            "20 F"
        ],
        "answer": "30 F"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "Multiple wells produce steam at 690 to 820 kPa temperature of _______.",
        "options": [
            "205 C",
            "155 C",
            "250 C",
            "175 C"
        ],
        "answer": "205 C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "In a hot rock systems, water is injected through injection wells into artificially made fractured rock beds of how many kilometers below the surface?",
        "options": [
            "1 to 6 km",
            "3 to 9 km",
            "4 to 10 km",
            "6 to 11 km"
        ],
        "answer": "1 to 6 km"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 6,
        "question": "NUCLEAR POWER PLANT What is the suggested maximum permissible dose (MPD) of gamma ray exposure for general individuals not working in nuclear setting, by choice, in rem/year?",
        "options": [
            "1",
            "5",
            "1⁄2",
            "3"
        ],
        "answer": "1⁄2"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "The number of protons in the nucleus of an atom of the number of electrons in the orbit of an atom",
        "options": [
            "Atomic volume",
            "Atomic number",
            "Atomic weight",
            "Atomic mass"
        ],
        "answer": "Atomic number"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "The process in which the nucleus splits into a smaller fragments.",
        "options": [
            "Fusion",
            "Fission",
            "Photoelectric effect",
            "Compton’s effect"
        ],
        "answer": "Fission"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "The ability of the substance to absorb neurons is dependent upon which parameter?",
        "options": [
            "Absorption cross section",
            "Scattering cross section",
            "Total cross section",
            "Atomic number"
        ],
        "answer": "Absorption cross section"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "Which of the following is NOT a unit of energy?",
        "options": [
            "Atomic unit",
            "meV",
            "dynes",
            "ergs"
        ],
        "answer": "dynes"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "The process in which a nucleus splits into smaller fragments.",
        "options": [
            "Fusion",
            "Fission",
            "Photoelectric effect",
            "Compton’s effect"
        ],
        "answer": "Fission"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "Which of the following is NOT a unit of energy?",
        "options": [
            "Calories",
            "Joules",
            "Pascals",
            "MeV"
        ],
        "answer": "Pascals"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "The ability of a substance to absorb neurons is dependent upon which parameter?",
        "options": [
            "Absorption cross section",
            "Scattering cross section",
            "Total cross section",
            "Atomic number"
        ],
        "answer": "Absorption cross section"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "Which of the following is NOT a unit of energy?",
        "options": [
            "Atomic unit",
            "MeV",
            "Dynes",
            "Ergs"
        ],
        "answer": "Dynes"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "An electrically charged atom or radial which carries electricity through an electrolyte is called:",
        "options": [
            "Ion",
            "Isotope",
            "Molecule",
            "Hole"
        ],
        "answer": "Ion"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "What is the smallest particle of an element that can enter into a chemical reaction?",
        "options": [
            "Molecule",
            "Ion",
            "Atom",
            "Isotope"
        ],
        "answer": "Atom"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "Beryllium, magnesium, and calcium all belong to which elemental grouping?",
        "options": [
            "Noble elements",
            "Halogens",
            "Lanthanons",
            "Alkaline earth metals"
        ],
        "answer": "Alkaline earth metals"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "the thickness of material required to attenuate radiation to a particular level depends on",
        "options": [
            "The particle",
            "The energy",
            "The shielding material",
            "The particle, its energy, and the shielding material"
        ],
        "answer": "The particle, its energy, and the shielding material"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "Particles that easily stopped within a few millimeter because their double charge generate path ionization and because they are susceptible to electrostatic interaction are:",
        "options": [
            "Alpha neurons",
            "Alpha radiations",
            "Beta radiations",
            "Gamma radiations"
        ],
        "answer": "Alpha radiations"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "Radiation consisting of singly charged particles that generate to intermediate distances are called:",
        "options": [
            "Fast neurons",
            "Alpha radiation",
            "Beta radiations",
            "Gamma radiations"
        ],
        "answer": "Beta radiations"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "Radiation with no charge, which produces no ionization, and which is difficult to attenuate thus posing a major health threat is",
        "options": [
            "Slow neutrons",
            "Alpha radiations",
            "Beta radiations",
            "Gamma radiations"
        ],
        "answer": "Gamma radiations"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "The property of fluid at a location where the Mach number is unity (at the throat) are called:",
        "options": [
            "Critical properties",
            "Sonic properties",
            "Dynamic properties",
            "Stagnation properties"
        ],
        "answer": "Critical properties"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "Gamma attenuation is a effected by:",
        "options": [
            "Their photoelectric effect",
            "Pair production",
            "Compton scattering",
            "The photoelectric effect, pair production, and Compton scattering"
        ],
        "answer": "The photoelectric effect, pair production, and Compton scattering"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "The amount of a radiation shield’s dimensional geometry that reduces to half of its original value is called the _________.",
        "options": [
            "Half-value mass",
            "Half-value thickness",
            "Semi-cross section",
            "Logarithmic decrement"
        ],
        "answer": "Half-value thickness"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "The amount of a radiation shield’s density that reduces radiation to half of its original value is called the _________.",
        "options": [
            "Half – value mass",
            "Half – value thickness",
            "Semi – cross section",
            "Logarithmic decrement"
        ],
        "answer": "Half – value mass"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "Radiation exposure, the measure of gamma radiation at the surface of an object, is measured in:",
        "options": [
            "Rems",
            "Rads",
            "Roentegens",
            "Roentegens per second"
        ],
        "answer": "Roentegens per second"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "Exposure is a measure of ionization surrounding a person, but biological damage is dependent on the amount of energy.",
        "options": [
            "Striking the surface",
            "Passing through the body",
            "Absorbed",
            "Reflected by the surface"
        ],
        "answer": "Absorbed"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "All of the following are practical application of Einstein’s principle of special relative except _______.",
        "options": [
            "Mass increase",
            "Length contraction",
            "Time dilation",
            "Space warping"
        ],
        "answer": "Space warping"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "The postulated that no signal or energy can be transmitted with a speed greater than the speed of light is consistent with _______",
        "options": [
            "The Heisenburg uncertainly principle",
            "The Compton effect",
            "Einstein’s law",
            "Newton’s second law"
        ],
        "answer": "Einstein’s law"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "Total energy of an electron in the same shell is defined by the _________.",
        "options": [
            "Principal quantum number",
            "Azimuthal quantum number",
            "Magnetic quantum number",
            "Hund rule"
        ],
        "answer": "Principal quantum number"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "The direction of a electron’s angular momentum vector is defined by the",
        "options": [
            "Principal quantum number",
            "Azimuthal quantum number",
            "Magnetic quantum number",
            "Electron spin quantum number"
        ],
        "answer": "Magnetic quantum number"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "The electron’s spin angular momentum vector is defined by the",
        "options": [
            "Azimuthal quantum number",
            "Magnetic quantum number",
            "Electron spin quantum number",
            "Hand rule"
        ],
        "answer": "Electron spin quantum number"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "The magnitude of an electron’s angular momentum vector is defined by the",
        "options": [
            "Principal quantum number",
            "Azimuthal quantum number",
            "Electron spin quantum number",
            "Hand rule"
        ],
        "answer": "Azimuthal quantum number"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "The fact that each orbital of a set of equal-energy orbitals must be occupied with an electron before any orbitals has two electrons is specified by which of the following?",
        "options": [
            "Principal quantum number",
            "Azimuthal quantum number",
            "Magnetic quantum number",
            "Hand rule"
        ],
        "answer": "Hand rule"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "The statement that no two electrons can have the same set of four quantum numbers is known as the",
        "options": [
            "Hand rule",
            "Heisenburg uncertainly principle",
            "Pauli exclusion principle",
            "Schrodinger equation"
        ],
        "answer": "Pauli exclusion principle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "All of the following terms describe the radiation lines from transition of electrons in an atom except",
        "options": [
            "Sharp",
            "Principal",
            "Obtuse",
            "Fundamental"
        ],
        "answer": "Obtuse"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "When electrons are not shared equally between two elements, and electrons spend more time with one element than the other, the bonding is called:",
        "options": [
            "Ionic bonding",
            "Polar covalent bonding",
            "Non – polar covalent bonding",
            "Metallic bonding"
        ],
        "answer": "Polar covalent bonding"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "When electrons are shared equally (e.g. when the atom are the same as in diatomic gases), the bonding is called:",
        "options": [
            "Ionic bonding",
            "Polar covalent bonding",
            "Non – polar covalent",
            "Resonance bonding"
        ],
        "answer": "Non – polar covalent"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "All of the following are units of energy except:",
        "options": [
            "Atomic units",
            "MeV",
            "Dynes",
            "Ergs"
        ],
        "answer": "Dynes"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "Einstein reasoned there was a discrete amount of energy needed to remove an electron from a surface, with the rest of the incident photon’s energy contributing to the kinetic energy of the photon., the amount of energy is called:",
        "options": [
            "Binding energy",
            "Work function",
            "Coulomb energy",
            "Fermi energy"
        ],
        "answer": "Work function"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 7,
        "question": "Which of the following is not a postulate of Bohr’s theory of the hydrogen atom?",
        "options": [
            "Electron orbit are discrete and non-radiating and an electron may not remain between these orbits",
            "The energy change experienced by an electron changing from one orbit to another is quantized",
            "Light waves exist simultaneously as high frequency electrical and magnetic waves",
            "Angular momentum is quantized"
        ],
        "answer": "Light waves exist simultaneously as high frequency electrical and magnetic waves"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Which of the following is necessary to generate steam in a boiler?",
        "options": [
            "A container",
            "Heat",
            "Water",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "It is the part of the boiler with water on one side and heat on the other side.",
        "options": [
            "Furnace volume",
            "Fire side",
            "Heating surface",
            "Water side"
        ],
        "answer": "Heating surface"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "A _________ boiler has heat and gases of combustion that pass through tubes surrounded by water.",
        "options": [
            "Fire tube",
            "Cast iron sectional",
            "Water tube",
            "Straight-tube"
        ],
        "answer": "Fire tube"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "A _________ boiler has water in the tubes and heat gases of combustion passing arounf the tubes.",
        "options": [
            "Fire tubes",
            "Cast iron sectional",
            "Water tube",
            "Firebox"
        ],
        "answer": "Water tube"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Which of the following are used in boiler to direct the gases of combustion over the boiler heating surface?",
        "options": [
            "Combustion control",
            "Baffles",
            "Fire tubes",
            "Zone controls"
        ],
        "answer": "Baffles"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The three-basic type of low pressure heating boilers ______, _______, and _______.",
        "options": [
            "Firebox; vertical; locomotive",
            "Scotch marine; wet-top ;dry-top",
            "Straight-tube ;bent-tube ;multiple pass",
            "Fire-tube ;water tube; cast iron sectional"
        ],
        "answer": "Fire-tube ;water tube; cast iron sectional"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "In a low pressure gas system, the gas regulator reduces that city gas pressure to _____ psi.",
        "options": [
            "0",
            "2",
            "1",
            "3"
        ],
        "answer": "0"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "In the ________ air mixes the fuel and burns.",
        "options": [
            "Fire tubes",
            "Combustion chamber",
            "Water tubes",
            "Breeching"
        ],
        "answer": "Combustion chamber"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The function of the steam boiler is to _______.",
        "options": [
            "Produce condensate",
            "Create heat",
            "Produce steam",
            "Burn fuel"
        ],
        "answer": "Produce steam"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Which of the following is the most common type of the water tube boiler?",
        "options": [
            "Firebox",
            "Scotch marine",
            "Vertical",
            "Straight-tube multiple pass"
        ],
        "answer": "Straight-tube multiple pass"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Excess fuel oil in the fuel oil system returns to the:",
        "options": [
            "Combustion chamber",
            "Fuel oil tank",
            "Burner",
            "Suction line"
        ],
        "answer": "Fuel oil tank"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "It is the system that provides the air necessary for combustion.",
        "options": [
            "Feedwater",
            "Steam",
            "Draft",
            "Fuel"
        ],
        "answer": "Draft"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The gasses of combustion leave the boiler through the",
        "options": [
            "Chimney",
            "Blower",
            "Air vent",
            "Breeching"
        ],
        "answer": "Breeching"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Which of the following boiler does not use tubes?",
        "options": [
            "Cast iron sectional",
            "Water tube",
            "Scotch marine",
            "Firebox"
        ],
        "answer": "Cast iron sectional"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Which of the following will make a boiler work more efficiently?",
        "options": [
            "More fuel is added",
            "Fire tubes are decrease in size",
            "The heating surface is increased",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "The heating surface is increased"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "What are the four system necessary to operate a boiler?",
        "options": [
            "Combustion; draft; steam; boiler water",
            "Water; steam; combustion; stoker",
            "Boiler water; fuel; draft; condense",
            "Feedwater; fuel; draft; steam"
        ],
        "answer": "Feedwater; fuel; draft; steam"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The ________ forms a vacuum that draws out of the condensate return the line into the vacuum tank.",
        "options": [
            "Suction line",
            "Main header",
            "Vacuum pump",
            "Heating equipment"
        ],
        "answer": "Vacuum pump"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Which of the following can be a function of the container in a boiler?",
        "options": [
            "Holds the water",
            "Collect the steam that is produced",
            "Transfer heat to the water to produce steam",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "At what temperature will water normally turns to steam?",
        "options": [
            "100°F",
            "200°F",
            "150°F",
            "212°F"
        ],
        "answer": "212°F"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Which of the following is true for cast iron sectional boilers?",
        "options": [
            "Cast iron sectional boilers have fire tubes",
            "These boiler do not require water",
            "Can be expanded in size",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "None of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Which of the following is the most important valve boiler?",
        "options": [
            "Main steam stop",
            "Automatic nonreturn valve",
            "Safety valve",
            "Feedwater stop valve"
        ],
        "answer": "Safety valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The MAWP on a low pressure steam boiler is _______ psi",
        "options": [
            "10",
            "20",
            "15",
            "30"
        ],
        "answer": "15"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Which of the following best defines a total force acting on a boiler?",
        "options": [
            "Area times diameter",
            "Area times pressure",
            "Area times distance",
            "The MAWP times pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "Area times pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The ASME code states the boilers with over _____ square feet heating surface must have two or more safety valve.",
        "options": [
            "200",
            "400",
            "400",
            "500"
        ],
        "answer": "500"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The area of a safety valve 4” in diameter is how many square inches.",
        "options": [
            "2.3562",
            "6.2832",
            "3.1416",
            "12.5664"
        ],
        "answer": "12.5664"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Which of the following is the only valve permitted between the safety valve and the boiler?",
        "options": [
            "os&y gate",
            "os&y globe",
            "automatic nonreturn",
            "no valve are permitted between the boiler and the safety valve"
        ],
        "answer": "no valve are permitted between the boiler and the safety valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The range of the pressure gauge should be _______ time the MAWP of the boiler.",
        "options": [
            "1 to 2",
            "2 to 3",
            "1 1⁄2 to 2",
            "2 1⁄2 to 3"
        ],
        "answer": "1 1⁄2 to 2"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The ASME code only allows ______ safety valve on boiler.",
        "options": [
            "Deadweight",
            "Spring-loaded pop-type",
            "Lever",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Spring-loaded pop-type"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "How much is the total force on a safety valve 2 1⁄2 in diameter and with the steam pressure of 15 psi?",
        "options": [
            "19.5413",
            "73.63125",
            "29.4525",
            "93.7512"
        ],
        "answer": "73.63125"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The steam pressure gauge on the boiler is calibrated to read in:",
        "options": [
            "Inches of vacuum",
            "Absolute pressure",
            "Pounds per square inch",
            "Pressure below atmospheric pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "Pounds per square inch"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Live steam is prevented from entering the bourdon tube of the pressure gauge by which of the following?",
        "options": [
            "Automatic nenreturn valve",
            "os&y valve",
            "inspector’s test cock",
            "siphon"
        ],
        "answer": "siphon"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "What pressure gauge that can read whether vacuum pressure or not.",
        "options": [
            "Compound",
            "Suction",
            "Duplex",
            "Vacuum"
        ],
        "answer": "Compound"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Which of the following best defines a vacuum?",
        "options": [
            "A pressure above gauge",
            "A pressure below atmospheric",
            "A pressure below gauge",
            "A pressure equal to gauge"
        ],
        "answer": "A pressure below atmospheric"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Safety valves are designed to pop open and stay until there is a _______ psi drop in pressure.",
        "options": [
            "0 to 1",
            "5 to 15",
            "2 to 4",
            "Over 15"
        ],
        "answer": "2 to 4"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "What type of boiler that uses safety valves?",
        "options": [
            "Fire tube",
            "Cast iron sectional",
            "Water tube",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The water column is located at the NOWL so lowest visible part of the gauge glass is _______ above the highest surface.",
        "options": [
            "2” to 3”",
            "Just",
            "4” to 5”",
            "Never"
        ],
        "answer": "2” to 3”"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Blowback of a safety valve is to prevent:",
        "options": [
            "Burner cycling",
            "Premature popping",
            "Chattering",
            "Feathering"
        ],
        "answer": "Chattering"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The boiler bottom blowdown line should discharge to a(n) ________.",
        "options": [
            "Sewer",
            "Atmospheric tank",
            "Blowdown tank",
            "Return tank or open sump"
        ],
        "answer": "Blowdown tank"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "If the desired cut-in pressure of the boiler is 6 psi and the desired cut-out pressure is 10 psi, the differential pressure setting must be ______ psi.",
        "options": [
            "2",
            "6",
            "4",
            "8"
        ],
        "answer": "4"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Impurities that build up on the surface of the water in the boiler prevent _______ from breaking through the surface of the water.",
        "options": [
            "Air",
            "CO2",
            "Oxygen",
            "Steam"
        ],
        "answer": "Steam"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "To prevent air pressure from building up in the boiler when filling the boiler with water, the ______ must be open.",
        "options": [
            "Safety valve",
            "Boiler vent",
            "Main steam stop valve",
            "Manhole cover"
        ],
        "answer": "Boiler vent"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "To prevent a vacuum from forming when taking the boiler off-line, which of the following must be opened when pressure is still on the boiler?",
        "options": [
            "Safety valve",
            "Boiler vent",
            "Main steam stop valve",
            "Man hole cover"
        ],
        "answer": "Boiler vent"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The operating range of the boiler is controlled by:",
        "options": [
            "Squastat",
            "Pressure control",
            "Vaporstat",
            "Modulating pressure control"
        ],
        "answer": "Pressure control"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The ________ regulates the high and low fire of the burner.",
        "options": [
            "Aquastat",
            "Pressure control",
            "Vaporstat",
            "Modulating pressure control"
        ],
        "answer": "Modulating pressure control"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The best time to blow down the boiler to remove sludge and sediment is when the boiler is at:",
        "options": [
            "Its highest load",
            "Half its load",
            "Its lightest load",
            "Anytime"
        ],
        "answer": "Its lightest load"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The level of the water in the _______ indicates the water level in the boiler.",
        "options": [
            "Condensate return tank",
            "Gauge glass",
            "Try cocks",
            "Blowdown tank"
        ],
        "answer": "Gauge glass"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "When blowing down a boiler, the quick opening valve should always be opened _______ and close ________.",
        "options": [
            "First; first",
            "Last; first",
            "First; last",
            "Last; last"
        ],
        "answer": "First; last"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Which of the following is added to boiler so that water changes scale-forming into a non adhering sludge?",
        "options": [
            "Oxygen",
            "Slag",
            "Mineral",
            "Chemicals"
        ],
        "answer": "Chemicals"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "A _______ valve is installed before the ________ to allow the steam pressure gauge to be changed if a malfunction occurs.",
        "options": [
            "Globe; safety valve",
            "Globe; U-tube siphon",
            "Gate; siphon",
            "Globe; pigtail siphon"
        ],
        "answer": "Gate; siphon"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "What pressure gauge that reads more pressure than is actually in the boiler.",
        "options": [
            "Broken",
            "Uncalibrated",
            "Slow",
            "Fast"
        ],
        "answer": "Fast"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "According to the ASME code, safety valve on low pressure boilers should be tested by hand at least:",
        "options": [
            "Once a month",
            "Once a year",
            "Once a shift",
            "Twice a year"
        ],
        "answer": "Once a month"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The purpose of the safety valve is prevent the pressure in the boiler from:",
        "options": [
            "Exceeding its MAWP",
            "Causing a boiler explosion",
            "Dropping below its MAWP",
            "Relieving water pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "Exceeding its MAWP"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The term applied when a safety opens and closes rapidly.",
        "options": [
            "Feathering",
            "Chattering",
            "Pressurering",
            "Hudding"
        ],
        "answer": "Chattering"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The safety valve on a low pressure boiler opens when pressure in the boiler exceeds how many psi?",
        "options": [
            "5",
            "15",
            "10",
            "30"
        ],
        "answer": "15"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "After the total force of the steam has lifted the safety valve off its seat, the steam enters the _______.",
        "options": [
            "Huddling chamber",
            "Steam holding tank",
            "Combustion chamber",
            "Main steam line"
        ],
        "answer": "Huddling chamber"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "What causes false water level readings in the gauge glass?",
        "options": [
            "Priming",
            "Foaming",
            "Carryover",
            "Blowing down"
        ],
        "answer": "Foaming"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Fusible plugs are required on _______ boilers by the ASME code.",
        "options": [
            "Coal-fired",
            "Gas-fired",
            "Fuel oil-fired",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "On a pressure control, ________ pressure plus ________ pressure equals ________ pressure.",
        "options": [
            "Differential; cut-out; cut-in",
            "Cut-in; cut-out; differential",
            "Cut-in; differential; cut-in",
            "Cut-in pressures equals cut-out pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "Cut-in; differential; cut-in"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "A burner should always start up in _______ fire and shut down in _______ fire.",
        "options": [
            "Low; low",
            "High; low",
            "Low; high",
            "High; high"
        ],
        "answer": "Low; low"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The water in the boiler is heated, turns to steam, and leaves the boiler through the:",
        "options": [
            "Feedwater line",
            "Main steam line",
            "Main header",
            "Main branch line"
        ],
        "answer": "Main steam line"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "When steams gives up its heat in a heat in a heat exchanger it turns to:",
        "options": [
            "Low pressure steam",
            "Makeup water",
            "Condensate",
            "Exhaust steam"
        ],
        "answer": "Condensate"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "A ________ pump discharge the return water back to the boiler.",
        "options": [
            "Feed",
            "Gear",
            "Return",
            "Vacuum"
        ],
        "answer": "Vacuum"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "How do you call a value that controls the flow of water in one direction only?",
        "options": [
            "Gate",
            "os&y",
            "globe",
            "check"
        ],
        "answer": "check"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The feedwater ________ valve should be located as close to the shell of the boiler as practical.",
        "options": [
            "Check",
            "Nonreturn",
            "Stop",
            "Regulating"
        ],
        "answer": "Stop"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "A ______ after each radiator allows _______ to pass through to the line.",
        "options": [
            "Steam tarp; steam",
            "Water trap; steam",
            "Steam trap; condensate",
            "Water trap; condensate"
        ],
        "answer": "Steam trap; condensate"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "A. ________ valve should be located between the boiler and the valve on the feedwater line.",
        "options": [
            "Stop; check",
            "Stop; regulator",
            "Check; stop",
            "Check; regulator"
        ],
        "answer": "Stop; check"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The feedwater ________ valve opens and closes automatically.",
        "options": [
            "Return",
            "Check",
            "Bypass",
            "Equalizing"
        ],
        "answer": "Check"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The vacuum pump pumps water and discharges air to the:",
        "options": [
            "Expansion tank",
            "Return tank",
            "Compression tank",
            "Atmosphere"
        ],
        "answer": "Atmosphere"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The range of pressure on the vacuum switch is usually",
        "options": [
            "2 to 6 psi",
            "2” to 8",
            "6 to 12 psi",
            "8” to 12”"
        ],
        "answer": "2” to 8"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Top test the vacuum pump, the operator puts the selector switch in the _______ position.",
        "options": [
            "Float",
            "Float or vacuum",
            "Vacuum",
            "Continuous"
        ],
        "answer": "Continuous"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Water added to the boiler to replace water lost due to leaks and blowing down is known as _______ water.",
        "options": [
            "Extra",
            "Boiler",
            "Makeup",
            "Feed"
        ],
        "answer": "Makeup"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Excessive use of cold city water makeup reduces overall efficiency because the water must be _______ before use in the boiler.",
        "options": [
            "Vented",
            "Filtered",
            "Heated",
            "Recirculated"
        ],
        "answer": "Heated"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The vacuum pump selector switch is normally in the position during the heating season.",
        "options": [
            "Float or vacuum",
            "Vacuum only",
            "Float only",
            "Continuous"
        ],
        "answer": "Float or vacuum"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The ________ shuts off the burner in the event of low water.",
        "options": [
            "Low water alarm",
            "Low water fuel cut-off",
            "Feedwater regulator",
            "Automatic low water feeder"
        ],
        "answer": "Low water fuel cut-off"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Water is supplied to the condensate tank by the _______ pump.",
        "options": [
            "Vacuum",
            "Feedwater",
            "Condensate",
            "Return"
        ],
        "answer": "Vacuum"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The feedwater regulator is located at the _______ and is connected to the boiler in the same manner as the ________.",
        "options": [
            "Right side: gauge glass",
            "NOWL; water column",
            "Bottom blowdown",
            "NOWL; safety valve"
        ],
        "answer": "NOWL; water column"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "What maintains a constant water level in the boiler?",
        "options": [
            "Gauge glass",
            "Automatic city water makeup feeder",
            "Water column",
            "Feedwater regulator"
        ],
        "answer": "Feedwater regulator"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The low water fuel cut-off should be tested:",
        "options": [
            "Daily",
            "Semiannually",
            "Monthly",
            "Annualy"
        ],
        "answer": "Daily"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The burner should be ________ when the low water fuel cut-off is blown down.",
        "options": [
            "Off",
            "Tagged out",
            "Firing",
            "Tested"
        ],
        "answer": "Firing"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Which of the following valves must be used as boiler main steam stop valve?",
        "options": [
            "Globe",
            "Check",
            "Gate",
            "os&y gate"
        ],
        "answer": "os&y gate"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Gate valves should always be ________ or ________ closed.",
        "options": [
            "Partially open; completely",
            "Completely open; completely",
            "Wide open; partly",
            "Throttled; completely"
        ],
        "answer": "Completely open; completely"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Steam header valves should be ________ valves.",
        "options": [
            "Globe",
            "Check",
            "Gate",
            "os&y gate"
        ],
        "answer": "Gate"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "When open the os&y valve offers ______ to the flow of steam.",
        "options": [
            "No resistance",
            "Velocity",
            "Throttling action",
            "Full resistance"
        ],
        "answer": "No resistance"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Steam traps are _______ devices.",
        "options": [
            "Manual",
            "Automatic",
            "Electrical",
            "semiautomatic"
        ],
        "answer": "Automatic"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "What valve should be used for throtting flow of material?",
        "options": [
            "Gate",
            "Check",
            "Globe",
            "Non-return"
        ],
        "answer": "Globe"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Steam traps removed ________ and ________ from the steam lines.",
        "options": [
            "Air; water",
            "Water; oil",
            "Air; oil",
            "Air; steam"
        ],
        "answer": "Air; water"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Condensate in the steam can result in:",
        "options": [
            "Carryover",
            "Foaming",
            "Priming",
            "Water hammer"
        ],
        "answer": "Water hammer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Two types of steam trap are the ________ steam trap and the ________ steam trap.",
        "options": [
            "Return; float",
            "Nonreturn; thermostatic",
            "Return; nonreturn",
            "Nonreturn; float"
        ],
        "answer": "Return; nonreturn"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The _______ steam trap is the most common steam trap used.",
        "options": [
            "Thermostatic",
            "Inverted bucket",
            "Return",
            "Nonreturn; float"
        ],
        "answer": "Thermostatic"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Condensate from the nonreturn steam strap is pumped from the condensate return tank of the:",
        "options": [
            "Return tank",
            "Feedwater heater",
            "Vacuum tank",
            "Boiler"
        ],
        "answer": "Boiler"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Steam returning to the vacuum tank could cause the condensate pump to become:",
        "options": [
            "Waterbound",
            "Waterlogged",
            "Steambound",
            "Steamlogged"
        ],
        "answer": "Steambound"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Steam strainer should be located on the line ________ the steam trap.",
        "options": [
            "In front of",
            "Above",
            "After",
            "Along sides of"
        ],
        "answer": "In front of"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "As the steam pressure increases the steam temperature:",
        "options": [
            "Decrease",
            "Remains the same",
            "Increases",
            "Fluctuates"
        ],
        "answer": "Increases"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "When the os&y valve is open the stem is in the _______ position.",
        "options": [
            "Floating",
            "Up",
            "Locked",
            "Down"
        ],
        "answer": "Up"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The thermostatic steam trap opens and closes by a(n):",
        "options": [
            "Float",
            "Electric sensor",
            "Inverted bucket",
            "Flexible bellows"
        ],
        "answer": "Flexible bellows"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "In the float the thermostatic trap the float rises to discharge:",
        "options": [
            "Condensate",
            "Feedwater chemicals",
            "Steam",
            "Water and steam"
        ],
        "answer": "Condensate"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Steam trap that failed to open would cause the heating unit to become:",
        "options": [
            "Steambound",
            "Very hot",
            "Waterlogged",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Waterlogged"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Which of the following whose main function is to remove dirt and impurities that may cause the steam tap to malfunction?",
        "options": [
            "Vacuum pumps",
            "Steam strainers",
            "Globe valves",
            "Steam separators"
        ],
        "answer": "Steam strainers"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "When a steam tap is functioning properly there is a ________ difference in temperature between the trap inlet and discharge.",
        "options": [
            "5°F to10°F",
            "20°F to 30°F",
            "10°F to 20°F",
            "No"
        ],
        "answer": "10°F to 20°F"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "When burning No. 6 fuel oil strainers should be cleaned at least once every to prevent _______ hours.",
        "options": [
            "8",
            "12",
            "10",
            "24"
        ],
        "answer": "24"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "When cleaning the fuel oil strainers the ________ must be carefully replaced to prevent _________ from getting into the system.",
        "options": [
            "Gasket ; fuel oil",
            "Cover; water",
            "Gasket; air",
            "Cover; fuel oil"
        ],
        "answer": "Gasket; air"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The _________ pump draws fuel oil from the fuel oil tank.",
        "options": [
            "Transfer",
            "Condensate",
            "Fuel oil",
            "Circulating"
        ],
        "answer": "Fuel oil"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The ________ valve protects the fuel lines and pump from excessive pressure.",
        "options": [
            "Safety",
            "Relief",
            "Bypass",
            "Stop"
        ],
        "answer": "Relief"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "A high vacuum on the fuel oil suction gauge normally indicates either _______ or _______.",
        "options": [
            "Low viscosity; a clogged vent",
            "A closed discharged valve; hot fuel oil",
            "Cold fuel oil; a dirty suction strainer",
            "Water in the fuel oil; a warm pump"
        ],
        "answer": "Cold fuel oil; a dirty suction strainer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Fuel oil burners deliver the fuel oil to the furnace in a:",
        "options": [
            "Steady stream",
            "Half spray, half steam",
            "Fine spray",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Fine spray"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The rotary cup burner uses ________ and ________ to atomize the fuel oil.",
        "options": [
            "High temperature; pressure",
            "High temperature; air",
            "High pressure; steam",
            "A spinning cup; high velocity air"
        ],
        "answer": "A spinning cup; high velocity air"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "In a low pressure gas burner gas is mixed with air in the _________.",
        "options": [
            "Burner register",
            "Combustion chamber",
            "Mixing chamber before the burner register",
            "Boiler furnace"
        ],
        "answer": "Mixing chamber before the burner register"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "In a high pressure gas mixed with the air on the inside of the:",
        "options": [
            "Burner register",
            "combustion chamber",
            "mixing chamber",
            "boiler funace"
        ],
        "answer": "Burner register"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Regardless of the type of fuel oil used the fuel oil must be _________ before it enters the boilers furnace.",
        "options": [
            "Pressurized",
            "Treated",
            "Atomized",
            "Measured"
        ],
        "answer": "Atomized"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "On the low pressure gas system the manual reset cannot be opened until the:",
        "options": [
            "Vaporstat proves pressure",
            "Pilot is lighted",
            "Boiler is vented",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Pilot is lighted"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Before any repair work is attempted on any gas-fired boiler the:",
        "options": [
            "Insurance inspector must be notified",
            "Main gas cock must be secured",
            "State inspector must be notified",
            "Main solenoid valve should be secured"
        ],
        "answer": "Main gas cock must be secured"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "In a low pressure gas system when the vaporstat proves gas pressure up to the zero- reducing governor the ________ start up.",
        "options": [
            "Induced draft fan",
            "Pressure",
            "Forced draft blower",
            "Gas pump"
        ],
        "answer": "Forced draft blower"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The butterfly on the low pressure gas system is a _______ valve.",
        "options": [
            "Slow-opening",
            "Screw",
            "Quick-opening",
            "Globe"
        ],
        "answer": "Slow-opening"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The amount of gas supplied to the burner in the low pressure gas system is controlled by:",
        "options": [
            "Gas pressure",
            "Steam pressure",
            "The boiler operator",
            "The amount of air passing through the butterfly valve"
        ],
        "answer": "The amount of air passing through the butterfly valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "If low rater develop in the boiler having a low pressure gas system the _______ will secure the gas to the burner.",
        "options": [
            "Whistle valve",
            "Manual reset valve",
            "Vaporstat",
            "Main gas solenoid"
        ],
        "answer": "Main gas solenoid"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Combination gas/fuel oil burners permit the operator to switch from one fuel to another ________.",
        "options": [
            "For economy",
            "Because of a shortage of fuel being used",
            "Because of a failure in the fuel system being used",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Hard coal, known as ________, has a ________ content.",
        "options": [
            "Bituminous; high carbon",
            "Anthracite; high volatile",
            "Bituminous; high volatile",
            "Anthracite; high carbon"
        ],
        "answer": "Anthracite; high carbon"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Soft coal, known as ________, has a ________ content.",
        "options": [
            "Bituminous; high carbon",
            "Anthracite; high volatile",
            "Bituminous; high volatile",
            "Anthracite; high carbon"
        ],
        "answer": "Bituminous; high volatile"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Boiler using soft coal must have _______ furnace volume to reduce the danger of _______.",
        "options": [
            "Small; overfiring",
            "Large; smoking",
            "Small; smoking",
            "Large; overfiring"
        ],
        "answer": "Large; smoking"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "When burning soft coal, if the volatile gases reach the heating surface before they have burned completely ________ and ________ develop.",
        "options": [
            "Smoke; soot",
            "Clinkers; ash",
            "Uneven heat; ash",
            "High temperature; smoke"
        ],
        "answer": "Smoke; soot"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The ________ of fuels oil is the lowest temperature at which it will flow as a liquid.",
        "options": [
            "Fire point",
            "Pour point",
            "Flash poit",
            "Viscosity"
        ],
        "answer": "Pour point"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The ________ is the temperature at which fuel oil given off vapor that flashes when exposed to an open flame.",
        "options": [
            "Fire point",
            "Pour point",
            "Flash point",
            "Viscosity"
        ],
        "answer": "Flash point"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The _______ is the temperature at which fuel oil will burn continuously when to an open flame.",
        "options": [
            "Fire point",
            "Pour point",
            "Flash point",
            "Viscosity"
        ],
        "answer": "Viscosity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "It is defined as the internal resistance of fuel oil flow?",
        "options": [
            "Fire point",
            "Pour point",
            "Flash point",
            "Viscosity"
        ],
        "answer": "Viscosity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "What must be done in order to lower the viscocity of the fuel oil?",
        "options": [
            "Lower its temperature",
            "Increase its temperature",
            "Lower its pour point",
            "Increase its pour point"
        ],
        "answer": "Increase its temperature"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "A leak on the fuel oil suction line between the tank and the suction side of the fuel oil pump would result in:",
        "options": [
            "The suction gauge pulsating",
            "Air entering the suction line",
            "Pulsating of the fire in the boiler",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Air entering the suction line"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Strokes were developed to:",
        "options": [
            "Increase efficiency of  burning coal",
            "Keep furnace temperature constant to protect brickwork",
            "Allow for development of larger coal-fired boiler",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Any foreign matter in the coal feed mechanism of the screw-feed stoker is best removed by:",
        "options": [
            "Emptying the coal hopper",
            "Reversing the stoker",
            "Forcing it through with a heavy shear in",
            "Using the cutoff gate at the bottom of the hopper"
        ],
        "answer": "Using the cutoff gate at the bottom of the hopper"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "In the event of an obstruction clogging the feed screw a _______ is used to prevent of an obstruction clogging the feed screw a _______ is used to prevent damage to transmission.",
        "options": [
            "Slip clutch",
            "Shear pin or key",
            "Fuse",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Shear pin or key"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "In order to bank the stoker it is necessary to secure the _______ while _______ continues to operate,",
        "options": [
            "Combination fan; coal feeder",
            "Coal feeder; forced draft fan",
            "Feedwater; induced draft fan",
            "Boiler stop valve; coal feeder"
        ],
        "answer": "Coal feeder; forced draft fan"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "In a screw-feed stoker, what draft fan supplies air for combustion?",
        "options": [
            "Induced",
            "Forced",
            "Combination",
            "Natural"
        ],
        "answer": "Forced"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "To prevent smoke and to aid in complete combustion in the screw-feed stoker, _______ is provided using a separate damper control.",
        "options": [
            "Underfire air",
            "Retort air",
            "Overfire air",
            "Grate zone air"
        ],
        "answer": "Overfire air"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The ram-feed stroke is a(n) ________ stoker.",
        "options": [
            "Overfeed",
            "Side feed",
            "Travelling grate",
            "Underfeed"
        ],
        "answer": "Underfeed"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The ram-feed stoker provides:",
        "options": [
            "Uniform feed",
            "Quick ash discharge",
            "Even coal distribution",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Combustion is the rapid burning of fuel and oxygen resulting in:",
        "options": [
            "Release of heat",
            "Oxidation",
            "Release of steam",
            "Nitrogen and oxygen"
        ],
        "answer": "Release of heat"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "What combustion occurs when all the fuel is burned using the theoretical amount of air?",
        "options": [
            "Incomplete",
            "Perfect",
            "Complete",
            "Imperfect"
        ],
        "answer": "Perfect"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "It is the burning of all the fuel using the minimum amount of excess air.",
        "options": [
            "Incomplete combustion",
            "Complete combustion",
            "Perfect combustion",
            "Imperfect combustion"
        ],
        "answer": "Complete combustion"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "________ Combustion occurs when all the fuel is not burned resulting in formation of soot and smoke.",
        "options": [
            "Incomplete",
            "Perfect",
            "Complete",
            "Imperfect"
        ],
        "answer": "Incomplete"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Which of the following is required to achieve complete combustion?",
        "options": [
            "Proper atomization",
            "Proper temperature of fuel",
            "Time of complete combustion",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The combustion process must be complete before the gasses combustion come in contact with the:",
        "options": [
            "Atmosphere",
            "Super heater",
            "Heating surface",
            "Main steam outlet"
        ],
        "answer": "Heating surface"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Soot buildup on heating surface:",
        "options": [
            "Acts as an insulation",
            "Prevents heat transfer",
            "Increases temperature of gases of combustion",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "The purpose of automatic combustion controls is to a control ________ and ________.",
        "options": [
            "High fire; low rate",
            "Stoker firing; fuel rate",
            "overfire air; fuel mixture",
            "proper air to fuel mixture; firing rate"
        ],
        "answer": "proper air to fuel mixture; firing rate"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "At 0 psig. How many BTU are necessary to change 1lb of water at 212°F of steam?",
        "options": [
            "144",
            "970",
            "180",
            "1190"
        ],
        "answer": "970"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Radiation is:",
        "options": [
            "The movement of liquid or gases created by a temperature difference",
            "The transfer of heat by direct molecular contact",
            "The weight of the substance compared to unity",
            "A form of heat transfer"
        ],
        "answer": "A form of heat transfer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "steam at 100 psi and 400°F is:",
        "options": [
            "Saturated",
            "Superheated",
            "Wet",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Superheated"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Which of the following most closely defines sensible heat?",
        "options": [
            "An established relationship comparing any substance to the heat content of water",
            "Heat quantity that can be felt or measured by a thermometer",
            "Heat quantity above the point of saturation",
            "Measure heat intensity"
        ],
        "answer": "Heat quantity that can be felt or measured by a thermometer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "What is required to raise the temperature of 1 lb of water from 32° to 212°F?",
        "options": [
            "144 BTU",
            "970.3 BTU",
            "180 BTU",
            "Saturated heat"
        ],
        "answer": "180 BTU"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Increasing the pressure has what effect of the boiling point of water?",
        "options": [
            "No change",
            "Temperature will be raised",
            "Temperature will be lowered",
            "Temperature will increase 2 °F for every psi"
        ],
        "answer": "Temperature will be raised"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Heat absorbed by water when it changes from liquid to steam at the boiling point is called:",
        "options": [
            "Sensible heat",
            "Specific heat",
            "Latent heat",
            "Superheat"
        ],
        "answer": "Latent heat"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 8,
        "question": "Heat may be transferred in how many ways?",
        "options": [
            "One",
            "Three",
            "Two",
            "Four"
        ],
        "answer": "Three"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "In turbine installation, the air is removed from the condenser by _________.",
        "options": [
            "Air pump",
            "Air injector",
            "Air ejector",
            "Air jet"
        ],
        "answer": "Air ejector"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The primary purpose of a turbine in a fluid loop is to:",
        "options": [
            "Add energy to the flow",
            "Add mass to the flow",
            "Extract energy from the flow",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Extract energy from the flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "A vena contracta in a fluid jet issuing through a hole in a plate in located approximately:",
        "options": [
            "10 diameters downstream of the hole",
            "At jets minimum diameter",
            "At the orifice minimum diameter",
            "At the orifice maximum diameter"
        ],
        "answer": "At jets minimum diameter"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The following are all example of indirect (secondary) miscellaneous methods to measure flow except:",
        "options": [
            "Turbine and propeller meters",
            "Magnetic flow meters",
            "Positive displacement meters",
            "Hot – wire anemometers"
        ],
        "answer": "Positive displacement meters"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "One could expect the possibility of Reynolds number similarity of all of the following cases except:",
        "options": [
            "Pumps",
            "Fans",
            "Turbines",
            "Weirs"
        ],
        "answer": "Weirs"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "One could expect the possibility of Froude number similarity of all of the following cases except:",
        "options": [
            "Surface ships",
            "Surface wave motion",
            "Flow over weirs",
            "Closed – pipe turbulent pipe flow"
        ],
        "answer": "Closed – pipe turbulent pipe flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "One could expect the possibility of Froude number similarity in all of the following case except:",
        "options": [
            "Motion of a fluid jet",
            "Flow over spillways",
            "Surge and food waves",
            "Subsonic airfoils"
        ],
        "answer": "Subsonic airfoils"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "In fluid flow, linear momentum is:",
        "options": [
            "A vector quantity equal to the product of mass and velocity",
            "A scalar quantity equal to the product mass and velocity",
            "A scalar quantity equal to the product of force and length of time is applied",
            "The change in impulse"
        ],
        "answer": "A vector quantity equal to the product of mass and velocity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "All of the following fluid phenomena are based on the force momentum principle of a flowing fluid except:",
        "options": [
            "Turbines",
            "Pelton wheel",
            "Diesel automobile engines",
            "Jet engines"
        ],
        "answer": "Diesel automobile engines"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The fact that a fluid’s velocity increase as the cross sectional area of the pipe through which it flow decrease is due to:",
        "options": [
            "Bernouli’s equation",
            "The continuity equation",
            "The momentum eqation",
            "The perfect gas law"
        ],
        "answer": "The continuity equation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "In the absence of any heat work interactions and any changes in potential energy, the stagnation enthalpy of fluid remains constant during ________.",
        "options": [
            "Unsteady flow",
            "Steady flow",
            "Turbulent flow",
            "Variable flow"
        ],
        "answer": "Steady flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "When a falling object reach a speed at which the drag force equals its weight, it has achieved:",
        "options": [
            "Mach one",
            "A laminar boundary layer",
            "A turbulent boundary layer",
            "Terminal velocity"
        ],
        "answer": "A turbulent boundary layer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The coefficient of contraction is the ratio of the:",
        "options": [
            "Area of vena contracta is the ratio of the:",
            "Actual discharge to the theoretical discharge",
            "Actual velocity to the theoretical velocity",
            "Effective head to the actual head"
        ],
        "answer": "Area of vena contracta is the ratio of the:"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The coefficient of discharge is the ratio of the:",
        "options": [
            "Area of vena contracta to the orifice area",
            "Actual discharge to the theoretical discharge",
            "Actual velocity to the theoretical velocity",
            "Effective head to the actual head"
        ],
        "answer": "Actual discharge to the theoretical discharge"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The coefficient of velocity is equal to the:",
        "options": [
            "Product of the coefficient of discharge and the coefficient of contraction",
            "Actual velocity divided by the theoretical velocity",
            "Sum of the coefficient of discharge and the coefficient of contraction",
            "Difference of the coefficient of discharge and the coefficient of contraction"
        ],
        "answer": "Actual velocity divided by the theoretical velocity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "Which of the following is not similarity between a submerged culvert and a siphon?",
        "options": [
            "They both operate full",
            "Torricelli’s equation holds",
            "Both can experience entrance and exit losses",
            "In both, the water flow downhill"
        ],
        "answer": "Torricelli’s equation holds"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "In parallel pipe system originating and terminating in common junctions.",
        "options": [
            "Mass flows through each branch are equal",
            "Pressure drops through each branch are equal",
            "Lengths of each branch are equal",
            "Flow areas of each branch are equal"
        ],
        "answer": "Pressure drops through each branch are equal"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "Flow through multi – loop system may be computed by:",
        "options": [
            "Any closed – form solution of simultaneous equation",
            "The hardy – cross method",
            "Trial and error",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "Flow measuring devices include all of the following except:",
        "options": [
            "Venturi meters",
            "Static pressure probes",
            "Turbine and propeller meters",
            "Magnetic dynamometers"
        ],
        "answer": "Magnetic dynamometers"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "Flow measuring devices include all of the following except:",
        "options": [
            "Orifice plate meters",
            "Hot-wire anemometers",
            "Magnetic flow meters",
            "Mercury barometers"
        ],
        "answer": "Mercury barometers"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "Flow measuring devices include all of the following except:",
        "options": [
            "Flow nozzles",
            "Venture area meters",
            "Pilot tubes",
            "Precision tachometers"
        ],
        "answer": "Precision tachometers"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The following are example of indirect (secondary) measurements flow rates using obstruction meters except:",
        "options": [
            "Variable are meters",
            "Venture meters",
            "Volume tanks",
            "Flow nozzles"
        ],
        "answer": "Volume tanks"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The following are example of indirect (secondary) measurements flow rates using obstruction meters except:",
        "options": [
            "Pilot static meters",
            "Static pressure probes",
            "Weight and mass scales",
            "Direction – sensing probes"
        ],
        "answer": "Weight and mass scales"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "In series pipe systems, all of the following parameters vary from section except:",
        "options": [
            "Pressure drop",
            "Friction loss",
            "Head loss",
            "Mass flow"
        ],
        "answer": "Mass flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "Venturi meter, pilot static gauges, orifice meters, flow nozzle, and differential manometers all depend upon the relationship between:",
        "options": [
            "Flow velocity and friction",
            "Flow velocity and pressure",
            "Friction and pressure",
            "Pressure and mass flow"
        ],
        "answer": "Flow velocity and pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The combination of enthalpy and kinetic energy of fluid is termed as:",
        "options": [
            "Latent enthalpy",
            "Heat enthalpy",
            "Throttling enthalpy",
            "Stagnation enthalpy"
        ],
        "answer": "Stagnation enthalpy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The coefficient of velocity, Cv accounts for the:",
        "options": [
            "Effects on the flow area of contraction, friction and turbulence",
            "Small effect of friction and turbulence of the orifice",
            "Changes in diameters of a converging pipe",
            "Effects of compressibility"
        ],
        "answer": "Small effect of friction and turbulence of the orifice"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "Expansion factors take into account the:",
        "options": [
            "Area of the vena contracta",
            "Small effect of friction and turbulence of the orifice",
            "Changes in diameters of a converging pipe",
            "Effects of compressibility"
        ],
        "answer": "Effects of compressibility"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The matching of scale model and full – scale results for a fluid dynamic phenomena with a free surface requires equality of:",
        "options": [
            "Reynolds number",
            "Weber number",
            "Froude number",
            "Cauchy number"
        ],
        "answer": "Froude number"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The matching of scale model and full – scale results for a fluids dynamic phenomena involving compressible",
        "options": [
            "Reynolds number",
            "Froude number",
            "Cauchy number",
            "Mach number"
        ],
        "answer": "Mach number"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The matching of scale model and full – scale prototype results for a fluid dynamic phenomena involving surface tension requires equality of:",
        "options": [
            "Reynolds number",
            "Weber number",
            "Froude number",
            "Cauchy number"
        ],
        "answer": "Weber number"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The matching of scale model and full – scale prototype results for a fluid dynamic phenomena involving a fully submerged body requires equality of:",
        "options": [
            "Reynolds umber",
            "Weber number",
            "Froude number",
            "Mach number"
        ],
        "answer": "Reynolds umber"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The water hammer phenomenon is primarily what kind of fluid mechanics?",
        "options": [
            "Static (a phenomena independent of time)",
            "Dynamic (a time – dependent phenomena)",
            "Compressible",
            "Incompressible"
        ],
        "answer": "Dynamic (a time – dependent phenomena)"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "All of the following are forms of drag on a body moving through a fluid except:",
        "options": [
            "Skin friction",
            "Wake drag",
            "Profile drag",
            "D’ Alembert’s paradox drag"
        ],
        "answer": "D’ Alembert’s paradox drag"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The magnitude of the drag coefficient of the sphere is water is dependent upon all of the following except:",
        "options": [
            "Fluid density",
            "Fluid velocity",
            "Units of measure ( SI o English Engineering System)",
            "Drag force"
        ],
        "answer": "Units of measure ( SI o English Engineering System)"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The fact that there is no resistance to bodies moving through an ideal non – viscous) fluids is known as:",
        "options": [
            "Reynold’s analogy",
            "D’ Alembert’s paradox",
            "Newton’s second law",
            "The second law of thermodynamics"
        ],
        "answer": "D’ Alembert’s paradox"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "One could expect the possibility of Reynolds number similarity in all of the following cases except:",
        "options": [
            "Submarines",
            "Torpedoes",
            "Seaplane hulls",
            "Supersonic aircraft"
        ],
        "answer": "Seaplane hulls"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The function of a turbine is to:",
        "options": [
            "Transfer heat from one fluid to another",
            "Increase the total energy content of the flow",
            "Extract energy from the flow",
            "Exchange heat to increase energy to the flow"
        ],
        "answer": "Extract energy from the flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "Piitot tube is used to measure the:",
        "options": [
            "Velocity of mass",
            "Velocity of pipe",
            "Flow",
            "Velocity of flow"
        ],
        "answer": "Velocity of flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "Orifice coefficients are used to determine:",
        "options": [
            "Energy losses",
            "Energy gains",
            "Mass losses",
            "Energy losses and mass gains"
        ],
        "answer": "Energy losses"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The coefficient of velocity is the ratio of the:",
        "options": [
            "area of vena contracta to the orifice area",
            "actual discharge to the theoretical discharge",
            "actual discharge velocity to the theoretical velocity",
            "effective head to the actual head"
        ],
        "answer": "actual discharge velocity to the theoretical velocity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The volume flow passes through a venturimeter is:",
        "options": [
            "increasing",
            "decreasing",
            "constant",
            "varying"
        ],
        "answer": "constant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "What must be done to change the direction of rotation of 440 -volt, 3 –phase induction motor?",
        "options": [
            "Reverse lines to start winding",
            "Interchanges any two power leads",
            "Replace any two wires to the rotor",
            "Remove any power leads"
        ],
        "answer": "Interchanges any two power leads"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "A draft tube is a part of which plants?",
        "options": [
            "Diesel engine power plant",
            "Gas turbine power plant",
            "Steam power plant",
            "Hydro – electric power plant"
        ],
        "answer": "Hydro – electric power plant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "In the hydro – electric plant having a medium head and using a Francis turbine, the turbine speed may be regulated through:",
        "options": [
            "Deflector gate",
            "Nozzle",
            "Wicket gate",
            "Forebay"
        ],
        "answer": "Wicket gate"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "A Francis turbine has what flow?",
        "options": [
            "Inward flow reaction",
            "Outward flow reaction",
            "Outward flow reaction",
            "Inward flow impulse"
        ],
        "answer": "Inward flow reaction"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "Which of the following is a type of water turbine?",
        "options": [
            "Parson",
            "Hero",
            "Pelton",
            "Banki"
        ],
        "answer": "Pelton"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "What is the use of a hydraulic jump?",
        "options": [
            "Increase the flow rate",
            "Reduce the flow rate",
            "Reduce the velocity of flow",
            "Reduce the energy of flow"
        ],
        "answer": "Reduce the energy of flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "A Kaplan turbine is:",
        "options": [
            "A high head mixed flow turbine",
            "A inward flow impulse turbine",
            "An outward flow reaction",
            "Low head axial flow tubine"
        ],
        "answer": "Low head axial flow tubine"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The focus of elevation is:",
        "options": [
            "Critical point",
            "Hydraulic gradient",
            "Energy gradient",
            "Friction gradient"
        ],
        "answer": "Hydraulic gradient"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The focus of elevation is which water will rise in the piezometer tube is termed:",
        "options": [
            "Energy gradient",
            "Friction head",
            "Hydraulic gradient",
            "Critical path"
        ],
        "answer": "Hydraulic gradient"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The intake pipe to a hydraulic turbine from a dam is:",
        "options": [
            "Tailrace",
            "Spiral casing",
            "Surge tank",
            "Penstock"
        ],
        "answer": "Penstock"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "A type of water turbine where a jet of water is made to fall on the blades or buckets and due to the impulse of water, the turbine starts to move.",
        "options": [
            "Pelton wheel",
            "Steam turbine",
            "Frances turbine",
            "Reaction turbine"
        ],
        "answer": "Pelton wheel"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The lowest portion to storage basin from where the waters is not drawn is:",
        "options": [
            "Bottom storage",
            "Sub-soil storage",
            "Spring reserve",
            "Dead storage"
        ],
        "answer": "Dead storage"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "In a hydro-electric plant using a Francis turbine with medium head, the speed can be regulated using the",
        "options": [
            "Deflector gate",
            "Nozzle",
            "Wicket gate",
            "Weir"
        ],
        "answer": "Wicket gate"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "In the deep well installation or operation, the difference between static water level and operating water level is known as _________.",
        "options": [
            "Suction lift",
            "Drawdown",
            "Priming level",
            "Clogging"
        ],
        "answer": "Drawdown"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "Which of the following is a characteristic of an impulse turbine?",
        "options": [
            "Steam striking blades on angle",
            "No steam reaction to velocity",
            "Steam striking blades at zero angle",
            "Steam reserving direction"
        ],
        "answer": "Steam striking blades at zero angle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "What is the pressure at the exit of a draft tube in a turbine?",
        "options": [
            "Below atmospheric",
            "Vacuum",
            "Atmospheric",
            "Gage"
        ],
        "answer": "Atmospheric"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "An impulse turbine are used for:",
        "options": [
            "Low head",
            "Medium head",
            "High head",
            "Very low head"
        ],
        "answer": "High head"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "Which of the following is used as high head turbine?",
        "options": [
            "Impulse",
            "Francis",
            "Reaction",
            "Propeller"
        ],
        "answer": "Impulse"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "In pumped storage plant",
        "options": [
            "Power is produced by pumps",
            "Water is stored by pumping to high pressure",
            "Pressure accumulators are used",
            "Downstream water is pumped upstream during offload periods"
        ],
        "answer": "Downstream water is pumped upstream during offload periods"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "What is the pressure at the exit of a draft in a turbine?",
        "options": [
            "Below atmospheric",
            "Vacuum",
            "Atmospheric",
            "Gage"
        ],
        "answer": "Atmospheric"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "An impulse turbine has:",
        "options": [
            "Low head",
            "Medium head",
            "High head",
            "Very low head"
        ],
        "answer": "High head"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "High head turbine is a/an:",
        "options": [
            "Impulse",
            "Francis",
            "Reaction",
            "Propeller"
        ],
        "answer": "Impulse"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The lowest portion to storage basin from where the water is not drawn is",
        "options": [
            "Bottom storage",
            "Sub-oil storage",
            "Spring storage",
            "Dead storage"
        ],
        "answer": "Dead storage"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "In a hydro-electric plant using a Francis with medium head, the speed can be regulated using the",
        "options": [
            "Deflector gate",
            "Nozzle",
            "Wicket gate",
            "Weir"
        ],
        "answer": "Wicket gate"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "In the deep well installation or operation, the difference between static water level and operating water level is called _________.",
        "options": [
            "Suction lift",
            "Drawdown",
            "Priming",
            "Clogging"
        ],
        "answer": "Drawdown"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "Which of the following is a characteristic of an impulse turbine?",
        "options": [
            "Steam striking blades on angle",
            "No steam reaction to velocity",
            "Steam striking blades at zero angle",
            "Steam reversing direction"
        ],
        "answer": "Steam striking blades at zero angle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "A type of water turbine where a jet of water is made to fall on the blades or buckets and due to the impulse of water, the turbine starts to move.",
        "options": [
            "Pelton wheel",
            "Steam turbine",
            "Francis turbine",
            "Reaction turbine"
        ],
        "answer": "Pelton wheel"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The intake pipe to a hydraulic turbine from a dam is:",
        "options": [
            "Tailrace",
            "Spiral casting",
            "Surge tank",
            "Penstock"
        ],
        "answer": "Penstock"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "In the hydro – electric plant having a medium head and using a Francis turbine, the turbine speed may be regulated through:",
        "options": [
            "Deflector gate",
            "Nozzle",
            "Wicket gate",
            "Forebay"
        ],
        "answer": "Wicket gate"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "A Francis turbine has what flow?",
        "options": [
            "Inward flow reaction",
            "Outward flow impulse",
            "Outward flow reaction",
            "Inward flow impulse"
        ],
        "answer": "Inward flow reaction"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "Which of the following is a type of water turbine?",
        "options": [
            "Parson",
            "Hero",
            "Pelton",
            "Banki"
        ],
        "answer": "Pelton"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "A Kaplan turbine is:",
        "options": [
            "A high mixed flow turbine",
            "An inward flow impulse turbine",
            "An outward flow reaction turbine"
        ],
        "answer": "D"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The focus of elevation is:",
        "options": [
            "Critical point",
            "Hydraulic gradient",
            "Energy gradient",
            "Friction gradient"
        ],
        "answer": "Hydraulic gradient"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The locus of elevation to which water will rise in the piezometer tube is termed:",
        "options": [
            "Energy gradient",
            "Friction head",
            "Hydraulic gradient",
            "Critical path"
        ],
        "answer": "Hydraulic gradient"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The primary purpose of a turbine in a fluid loop is to:",
        "options": [
            "Add energy to the flow",
            "Add mass to the flow",
            "Extract energy from the flow",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Extract energy from the flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "A vena contracta in a fluid jet issuing through a hole in a plate is located approximately:",
        "options": [
            "10 diameters downstream of the hole",
            "At jets minimum diameter",
            "At the orifice minimum diameter",
            "At the orifice maximum diameter"
        ],
        "answer": "At jets minimum diameter"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The following are all example of indirect (secondary) miscellaneous methods to measure flow except:",
        "options": [
            "Turbine and propeller meters",
            "Magnetic flow meters",
            "Positive displacement meters",
            "Hot – wire anemometers"
        ],
        "answer": "Positive displacement meters"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "One could expect the possibility of Reynolds number similarity in all of the following cases except:",
        "options": [
            "Pumps",
            "Fans",
            "Turbines",
            "Weirs"
        ],
        "answer": "Weirs"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "One could expect the possibility of Froude number similarity in all of the following causes except:",
        "options": [
            "Surface ships",
            "Surface wave motion",
            "Flow over weirs",
            "Closed – pipe turbulent pipe flow"
        ],
        "answer": "Closed – pipe turbulent pipe flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "One could expect the possibility of Froude number similarity in all of the following causes except:",
        "options": [
            "Motion of a fluid jet",
            "Flow over spillways",
            "Surge and flood waves",
            "Subsonic airfoils"
        ],
        "answer": "Subsonic airfoils"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "In fluid. Linear momentum is:",
        "options": [
            "A vector quantity equal to the product of mass and velocity",
            "A scalar quantity equal to the product mass and velocity",
            "A scalar quantity equal to the product of force and length of time is applied",
            "The charge impulse"
        ],
        "answer": "A vector quantity equal to the product of mass and velocity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "All of the following fluid phenomena are based on the force momentum principle of a flowing fluid except:",
        "options": [
            "Turbines",
            "Pelton wheels",
            "Diesel automobile engines",
            "Jet engines"
        ],
        "answer": "Diesel automobile engines"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The fact that a fluid’s velocity increase as the pipe through which it flow decrease is due to:",
        "options": [
            "Bernoull’s equation",
            "The continuity equation",
            "The momentum equation",
            "The perfect gas law"
        ],
        "answer": "The continuity equation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "In the absence of any heat and work interactions and any changes in potential energy, the stagnation enyhalpy of a fluid remains constant during:",
        "options": [
            "Unsteady law",
            "Steady flow",
            "Turbulent flow",
            "Variable flow"
        ],
        "answer": "Steady flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "When a falling object reaches a speed at which the drag force equals its weight, it has achieved:",
        "options": [
            "Mach one",
            "A laminar boundary layer",
            "A turbulent boundary layer",
            "Terminal velocity"
        ],
        "answer": "A turbulent boundary layer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The coefficient of contraction is the ratio of the:",
        "options": [
            "Area of vena contracta to the orifice area",
            "Actual discharge to the theoretical discharge",
            "Actual velocity to the theoretical velocity",
            "Effective head to the actual head"
        ],
        "answer": "Area of vena contracta to the orifice area"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The coefficient of discharge is the ratio of the",
        "options": [
            "Area of vena contracta to the orifice area",
            "Actual discharge to the theoretical discharge",
            "Actual velocity to the theoretical velocity",
            "Effective head to the actual head"
        ],
        "answer": "Actual discharge to the theoretical discharge"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The coefficient of velocity is equal to the:",
        "options": [
            "Product of the coefficient of discharge and the coefficient of contraction",
            "Actual velocity divided by the theoretical velocity",
            "Sum of the coefficient of discharge and the coefficient of contraction",
            "Difference of the coefficient of discharge and the coefficient of contraction"
        ],
        "answer": "Actual velocity divided by the theoretical velocity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "Which of the following is not a similarity between a submerged culvert and a siphon?",
        "options": [
            "They both operate full",
            "Torricelli’s equation holds",
            "Both can experience entrance and exit losses",
            "In both, the water flows downhill"
        ],
        "answer": "Torricelli’s equation holds"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "In parallel pipe system originating and terminating in common junctions:",
        "options": [
            "Mass flows through each branch are equal",
            "Pressure drops through each branch are equal",
            "Lengths each branch are equal",
            "Flows areas of each branch are equal"
        ],
        "answer": "Pressure drops through each branch are equal"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "Flows through multi – loop system may be computed by:",
        "options": [
            "Any closed – from solution of simultaneous equations",
            "The hardy – cross method",
            "Trial and error",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "Flow measuring devices include all of the following except:",
        "options": [
            "Venture meters",
            "Static pressure probes",
            "Turbine and propeller meters",
            "Magnetic dynamometers"
        ],
        "answer": "Magnetic dynamometers"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "Flow measuring devices include all of the following except:",
        "options": [
            "Orifice plate meters",
            "Hot – wire anemometers",
            "Magnetic flwo meters",
            "Mercury barometers"
        ],
        "answer": "Mercury barometers"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "Flow measuring devices include all of the following except:",
        "options": [
            "Flow nozzles",
            "Venture area meters",
            "Pitot tubes",
            "Precision tachometers"
        ],
        "answer": "Precision tachometers"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The following are examples of indirect (secondary) measurements to measure flow rates using obstruction meters except:",
        "options": [
            "Variable area meters",
            "Venture meters",
            "Volume tanks",
            "Flow nozzle"
        ],
        "answer": "Volume tanks"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The following are examples of indirect (secondary) measurements to measure flow rates using obstruction meters except:",
        "options": [
            "Pitot static meters",
            "Static pressure probes",
            "Weight and mass scales",
            "Direction – sensing probes"
        ],
        "answer": "Weight and mass scales"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "In series pipe system, all of the following parameters vary from section to section except:",
        "options": [
            "Pressure drop",
            "Friction loss",
            "Head loss",
            "Mass flow"
        ],
        "answer": "Mass flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "Venturi meters, pitot static gauges, orifice meters, flow nozzles, and differential manometers all depend upon the relationship between:",
        "options": [
            "Flow velocity and friction",
            "Flow velocity and pressure",
            "Friction and pressure",
            "Pressure and mass flow"
        ],
        "answer": "Flow velocity and pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The combination of enthalpy and kinetic energy of fluid is termed as:",
        "options": [
            "Latent enthalpy",
            "Heat enthalpy",
            "Throtting enthalpy",
            "Stagnation enthalpy"
        ],
        "answer": "Stagnation enthalpy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The coefficient of velocity, Cv, accounts for the:",
        "options": [
            "Effect of the flow area of contraction, friction, and turbulence",
            "Small effect of friction and turbulence of the orifice",
            "Changes in diameters of a converging pipe",
            "Effect of compressibility"
        ],
        "answer": "Small effect of friction and turbulence of the orifice"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "Expansion factor take into accounts the:",
        "options": [
            "Area of the vena contracta",
            "Small effect of friction and turbulence of the orifice",
            "Changes in diameters of a converging pipe",
            "Effects of compressibility"
        ],
        "answer": "Effects of compressibility"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The matching of scale model and full – scale result for a fluid dynamic phenomena involving compressible fluids requires equality of:",
        "options": [
            "Reynolds number",
            "Froude number",
            "Cauchy number",
            "Mach number"
        ],
        "answer": "Mach number"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The matching of scale model and full – scale prototype results for a fluid dynamic phenomena involving surface tension requires equality of:",
        "options": [
            "Reynolds number",
            "Weber number",
            "Froude number",
            "Cauchy number"
        ],
        "answer": "Weber number"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The matching of scale model and full – scale prototype results for a fluid dynamic phenomena involving a fully submerged body requires equality of:",
        "options": [
            "Reynolds number",
            "Weber number",
            "Froude number",
            "Mach number"
        ],
        "answer": "Reynolds number"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The water hammer phenomenon is primarily what kind of fluid mechanics?",
        "options": [
            "Static ( a phenomena independent of time)",
            "Dynamic ( a time – dependent phenomena)",
            "Compressible",
            "Incompressible"
        ],
        "answer": "Dynamic ( a time – dependent phenomena)"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "All of the following are forms of drag on a body moving through a fluid except:",
        "options": [
            "Skin friction",
            "Wake drag",
            "Profile drag",
            "D’ Alembert’s paradox drag"
        ],
        "answer": "D’ Alembert’s paradox drag"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The magnitude of the drag coefficient of a sphere in water is dependent upon all of the following except:",
        "options": [
            "Fluid density",
            "Fluid velocity",
            "Units of measure (SI or English engineering system )",
            "Drag force"
        ],
        "answer": "Units of measure (SI or English engineering system )"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The fact that there is no resistance to bodies moving through an ideal ( non – viscous ) fluids is known as:",
        "options": [
            "Reynold’s anology",
            "D’ Alembert’s paradox",
            "Newton’s second law",
            "The second law of thermodynamics"
        ],
        "answer": "D’ Alembert’s paradox"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "One could except the possibility of Reynolds number similarity in all of the following cases except:",
        "options": [
            "Submarines",
            "Torpedoes",
            "Seaplane",
            "Supersonic aircraft"
        ],
        "answer": "Seaplane"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The function of a turbine is to",
        "options": [
            "Transfer heat from one fluid to anoher",
            "Increase total energy content of the flow",
            "Extract energy from the flow",
            "Exchange heat to increase energy to the flow"
        ],
        "answer": "Extract energy from the flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "Pitot is use to measure the:",
        "options": [
            "Velocity of mass",
            "Velocity of pipe",
            "Flow",
            "Velocity of flow"
        ],
        "answer": "Velocity of flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "Orifice coefficient are used to determine",
        "options": [
            "Energy losses",
            "Energy gains",
            "Mass losses",
            "Energy losses and mass gains"
        ],
        "answer": "Energy losses"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The coefficient of velocity is the ratio of the",
        "options": [
            "Area of vena contracta to the orifice area",
            "Actual discharge to the theoretical discharge",
            "Actual discharge velocity to the theoretical discharge velocity",
            "Effective head to the actual head"
        ],
        "answer": "Actual discharge velocity to the theoretical discharge velocity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "The volume flow passes through a venturimeter is:",
        "options": [
            "Increasing",
            "Decreasing",
            "Constant",
            "Varying"
        ],
        "answer": "Constant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 9,
        "question": "Which of the following devices used to measure the discharge of outflow from vessel?",
        "options": [
            "Pitot tube",
            "Orifice",
            "Pump head",
            "Obstruction meter"
        ],
        "answer": "Orifice"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The area under load curve divided by maximum demand represents:",
        "options": [
            "Load factor",
            "Connected load",
            "Average load",
            "Diversity factor"
        ],
        "answer": "Diversity factor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "What is the reverse capacity of a plant?",
        "options": [
            "Maximum demand – average demand",
            "Plant capacity – maximum demand",
            "Plant capacity – average demand",
            "Plant capacity x (1 – load factor)"
        ],
        "answer": "Plant capacity – maximum demand"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Load curve refers to the plot of:",
        "options": [
            "Load versus generating capacity",
            "Load versus current",
            "Coad versus time",
            "Load versus cost power"
        ],
        "answer": "Coad versus time"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The ratio of maximum load to the rated plant capacity is called _________.",
        "options": [
            "Load factor",
            "utilization factor",
            "maximum load factor",
            "capacity"
        ],
        "answer": "utilization factor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Peak load for a period of time divided by installed capacity is:",
        "options": [
            "capacity factor",
            "demand factor",
            "utilization factor",
            "load factor"
        ],
        "answer": "utilization factor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The ratio of the sum of individual maximum demand of the system to the maximum demand of the whole system is:",
        "options": [
            "diversity factor",
            "utilization factor",
            "power factor",
            "demand factor"
        ],
        "answer": "diversity factor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The ratio between the actual power and the apparent power in any circuit is known as the ________ of that circuit.",
        "options": [
            "Measured power",
            "Capacity",
            "Power",
            "KVAR"
        ],
        "answer": "Power"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The ratio of maximum load to the rated plant capacity.",
        "options": [
            "Load factor",
            "Utilization factor",
            "Maximum load factor",
            "Capacity factor"
        ],
        "answer": "Utilization factor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The ratio of the average load to the peak load over a designated period of time is called",
        "options": [
            "Load factor",
            "Reactive factor",
            "Diversity factor",
            "Plant use factor"
        ],
        "answer": "Load factor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The ratio of the sum of individual maximum demands of the system to the overall maximum demand of the whole system.",
        "options": [
            "Demand factor",
            "Diversity factor",
            "Power",
            "Utilization factor"
        ],
        "answer": "Diversity factor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Load curve refers to the plot of:",
        "options": [
            "Load versus generating capacity",
            "load versus current",
            "load versus time",
            "load versus cost of power"
        ],
        "answer": "load versus time"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Load curve refers to the plot of:",
        "options": [
            "Load versus generating capacity",
            "load versus current",
            "load versus time",
            "load versus cost of power"
        ],
        "answer": "load versus time"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The ratio of maximum load to the rated plant capacity",
        "options": [
            "load factor",
            "utilization factor",
            "maximum load factor",
            "capacity factor"
        ],
        "answer": "utilization factor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The ratio of the average load to the peak load over  designed period of time is called _______.",
        "options": [
            "load factor",
            "reactive factor",
            "diversity factor",
            "plant use factor"
        ],
        "answer": "load factor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Peak load for a period of time divided by installed capacity is ________.",
        "options": [
            "Capacity factor",
            "Demand factor",
            "Utilization factor",
            "Load factor"
        ],
        "answer": "Utilization factor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The area under load curve divided by maximum demand represents",
        "options": [
            "Load factor",
            "Connected load",
            "Average load",
            "Diversity factor"
        ],
        "answer": "Diversity factor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The ratio of the sum of individual maximum demands of the system to the overall maximum demand of the whole system.",
        "options": [
            "Demand factor",
            "Diversity factor",
            "Power factor",
            "Utilization factor"
        ],
        "answer": "Diversity factor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The ratio of the sum of individual maximum demands of the system to the maximum demands of the whole system is known as ________.",
        "options": [
            "Diversity factor",
            "Utilization factor",
            "Power factor",
            "Demand factor"
        ],
        "answer": "Diversity factor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The ratio between the actual power and the apparent power in any circuit is known as the ________ of the circuit.",
        "options": [
            "Measured power",
            "Capacity",
            "Power factor",
            "KVAR"
        ],
        "answer": "Power factor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Yeast as raw material for beer making is added to the equipment called:",
        "options": [
            "Fermenters",
            "Brew kettle",
            "Cooler",
            "Starting tube"
        ],
        "answer": "Fermenters"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "A major cause of air pollution resulting from the burning of fuel oil is:",
        "options": [
            "Nitrous",
            "Hydrogen",
            "Sulfur dioxide",
            "Silicon"
        ],
        "answer": "Sulfur dioxide"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Heavy water is:",
        "options": [
            "B2O",
            "H2O",
            "W2O",
            "D2O"
        ],
        "answer": "D2O"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Scintillation counter are used to detect:",
        "options": [
            "Beta rays",
            "X – rays",
            "Gamma rays",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "All of the following are common types of chemical reactions except",
        "options": [
            "Direct combination",
            "Fission",
            "Decomposition",
            "Double replacement"
        ],
        "answer": "Fission"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Redox reaction can often be type of:",
        "options": [
            "Direct combination",
            "Fission",
            "Decomposition",
            "Double replacement"
        ],
        "answer": "Double replacement"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The fact that the amount of slightly solubla gas absorbed in a liquid is proportional to the partial pressure of the gas is known as:",
        "options": [
            "Dalton’s law",
            "Henry’s law",
            "Raoult’s law",
            "Boyle’s law"
        ],
        "answer": "Henry’s law"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "All of the following pollutants are produced because decaying organic matter except:",
        "options": [
            "Ammonia",
            "Sulfur dioxide",
            "Methane",
            "Hydrogen sulfide"
        ],
        "answer": "Sulfur dioxide"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The velocity of radiations (v) and the frequency of radiations (f) are related to the wavelength of radiations by:",
        "options": [
            "v/f",
            "f/v",
            "vf",
            "v2f"
        ],
        "answer": "v/f"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Swimming pool water needs",
        "options": [
            "Pre – chlorination",
            "Super – chlorination",
            "Dual – chlorination",
            "De – chlorination"
        ],
        "answer": "De – chlorination"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Aeration of water is done for all of the following purposes except for:",
        "options": [
            "Removal of CO2",
            "Removal of bad taste",
            "Increasing the amount of oxygen in water",
            "Removal of temporary hardness"
        ],
        "answer": "Removal of temporary hardness"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Which of the following area of work requires lowed noise level?",
        "options": [
            "Gymnasiums",
            "Library",
            "Lecture halls",
            "Kitchens"
        ],
        "answer": "Library"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Mycotoxins are poisonous chemicals produced by:",
        "options": [
            "Bacteria",
            "Molds",
            "Virus",
            "Algae"
        ],
        "answer": "Molds"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Turbidity in water is due to:",
        "options": [
            "Algae",
            "Fungi",
            "Organic salts",
            "Finally divided particles of clay, silt and organic matter"
        ],
        "answer": "Finally divided particles of clay, silt and organic matter"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Per capita consumption of water is generally taken as:",
        "options": [
            "50 – 100 liters",
            "150 – 300 liters",
            "400 – 500 liters",
            "750 – 1000 liters"
        ],
        "answer": "150 – 300 liters"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Which of the following industries have the highest consumption of water for processing?",
        "options": [
            "Foundry",
            "Automobile industry",
            "Paper mill",
            "Aluminum industry"
        ],
        "answer": "Paper mill"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The ratio activity of water because of stronstium can be removed by:",
        "options": [
            "Aeration",
            "Alum coagulation",
            "Phosphate coagulation",
            "Lime"
        ],
        "answer": "Phosphate coagulation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Chemical use for checking the growth of algae in reservoirs is",
        "options": [
            "Copper sulfate",
            "Alum",
            "Bleaching powder",
            "Brine"
        ],
        "answer": "Bleaching powder"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Which of the following is not pollutant from a sulfuric acid plants?",
        "options": [
            "Sulfur dioxide",
            "Sulfur trioxide",
            "Acid moist",
            "Hydrogen sulfide"
        ],
        "answer": "Hydrogen sulfide"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Which of the following is a cold cathode lamp?",
        "options": [
            "Sodium vapor lamp",
            "High pressure mercury vapor lamp",
            "Low pressure mercury vapor lamp",
            "Neon lamp"
        ],
        "answer": "Neon lamp"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Which has an octane rating of more than 100?",
        "options": [
            "Gobar gas",
            "Methyl alcohol",
            "Benzol",
            "Ethyl alcohol"
        ],
        "answer": "Benzol"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The part per million is identical to:",
        "options": [
            "Grains per gallon",
            "Pounds per cubic foot",
            "Milligrams per kg",
            "Tones per acre foot"
        ],
        "answer": "Milligrams per kg"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "In power plant an electrostatic precipitators is installed between:",
        "options": [
            "Forced draft fan and induced draft fan",
            "Furnace and chimney",
            "Primary air and secondary air",
            "Furnace and forced draft fan"
        ],
        "answer": "Furnace and chimney"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "At present, the number of true elementary particles, which include leptons and quarks, is thought to be:",
        "options": [
            "4",
            "8",
            "10",
            "12"
        ],
        "answer": "12"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The effective size of a target atom that interacts with a moving particle is called its ________.",
        "options": [
            "Length",
            "Width",
            "Cross section",
            "Pseudo – area"
        ],
        "answer": "Cross section"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Most nuclear particles can react with atoms in several different ways including ________.",
        "options": [
            "Absorption",
            "Scattering",
            "Absorption and scattering",
            "Reflection and absorption"
        ],
        "answer": "Absorption and scattering"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The operation that produce highest noise level is:",
        "options": [
            "Welding",
            "Riveting",
            "Machining",
            "Pressing"
        ],
        "answer": "Riveting"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The ratio absorbed by the transfer fluid to the original incident energy striking the collector.",
        "options": [
            "Shading factor",
            "Collector efficiency",
            "Betz coefficient",
            "Transmittance"
        ],
        "answer": "Collector efficiency"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "A swinging support constructed as part of the vessel and that supports the manway cover when it is unbolted and moved aside.",
        "options": [
            "Davit",
            "Handhole",
            "Nozzle neck",
            "Manway arm"
        ],
        "answer": "Davit"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Is the subjective method in which the smoke density is visually compared to the five standardized white-black grids.",
        "options": [
            "Ringelman scale",
            "Dalton scale",
            "Smoke spot scale",
            "Dew point scale"
        ],
        "answer": "Ringelman scale"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The ratio of fugacity at actual conditions to the fugacity at some reference state is known as:",
        "options": [
            "Compressibility",
            "Activity",
            "Gravimetric coefficient",
            "Saturation"
        ],
        "answer": "Activity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "A type of polymer used for detergents, milk bottles, oil containers and toys.",
        "options": [
            "Polyvinyl chloride ( PVC)",
            "Polystyrene (PS)",
            "High density polyethelene (HDPE)",
            "Polypropylene (PP)"
        ],
        "answer": "High density polyethelene (HDPE)"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "A type of polymer used for grocery bags and food wraps.",
        "options": [
            "Polyvinyl chloride ( PVC)",
            "Polystyrene (PS)",
            "Low density polyethelene (HDPE)",
            "Polypropylene (PP)"
        ],
        "answer": "Low density polyethelene (HDPE)"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "A radioactive gas produced from the decay of radium within the rocks beneath building.",
        "options": [
            "Spills",
            "Radon",
            "Smoke",
            "Smog"
        ],
        "answer": "Radon"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Consist of ground – level ozone and peroxyacyl nitrates (PAN).",
        "options": [
            "Smog",
            "Spills",
            "Sulfur oxide",
            "Smoke"
        ],
        "answer": "Smog"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "A term used to mean the corrective steps taken to return the environment to its original condition.",
        "options": [
            "Stabilization",
            "Remediation",
            "Greenhouse effect",
            "Opacity"
        ],
        "answer": "Remediation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The burning of low – sulfur fuel is known as:",
        "options": [
            "Fuel switching",
            "Fuel adding",
            "Fuel binding",
            "Fuel swapping"
        ],
        "answer": "Fuel switching"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The removal of particulate matter from a gas flow by exposing the flow to a liquid or slurry is known as:",
        "options": [
            "Stripping",
            "Spraying",
            "Scrubbing",
            "Absorption"
        ],
        "answer": "Scrubbing"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The drop in a solvent’s vapor pressure and the increase in mole fraction as solute is added is described by:",
        "options": [
            "Dalton’s law",
            "Henry’s law",
            "Raoult’s law",
            "Boyle’s law"
        ],
        "answer": "Raoult’s law"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "All of the following statements are characteristics of bases except _______.",
        "options": [
            "They conduct electricity in aqueous solutions",
            "They turn red litmus paper blue",
            "They have a pH between 0 and 7",
            "They neutralize acid forming salts and water"
        ],
        "answer": "They have a pH between 0 and 7"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "All of the following statements about conjugate acids and bases are true except ________.",
        "options": [
            "A conjugate acids results when a base accept a protons",
            "A conjugate base results when a base accepts a protos",
            "Strong acids tend to give weak conjugate bases",
            "The Bronsted – lowry theory defines bases as protons accepetors"
        ],
        "answer": "A conjugate base results when a base accepts a protos"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Are any solid particulate matter that becomes airbone, with the exception of particulate matter emitted from the exhaust stack of a combustion process.",
        "options": [
            "Dusts or fugitive dusts",
            "Dioxin",
            "Fugitive emissions",
            "CFCs"
        ],
        "answer": "Dusts or fugitive dusts"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Equipment leaks from plant equipments are known as ________.",
        "options": [
            "Fugitive leaks",
            "Fugitive dusts",
            "Fugitive exhausts",
            "Fugitive emissions"
        ],
        "answer": "Fugitive emissions"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "What is a substance that absorbs or retains moisture?",
        "options": [
            "Surface acting agent",
            "Dry ultra-fine coal",
            "Fossil fuel",
            "Humectant"
        ],
        "answer": "Humectant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Is a soluble compound that reduces a liquid’s surface tension or reduces the interfacial tension between a liquid and a solid.",
        "options": [
            "Surface – acting agent or surfactant",
            "Humectant",
            "Oxygenated",
            "CKC"
        ],
        "answer": "Surface – acting agent or surfactant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "A material or substance that is accidentally or intentionally introduced to the environment in a quality that exceeds what occurs naturally.",
        "options": [
            "Waste",
            "Sludge",
            "Pollutant",
            "Biosolids"
        ],
        "answer": "Pollutant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Refers to organic waste produced from biological waterwaste treatment processes.",
        "options": [
            "Toxic waste",
            "Biosolids",
            "Extrinsic waste",
            "Process waste"
        ],
        "answer": "Biosolids"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "A rule which states that any solid waste mixed with hazardous waste becomes harazdous.",
        "options": [
            "The mixture rule",
            "The derived from rule",
            "The environmental rule",
            "The hazard rule"
        ],
        "answer": "The mixture rule"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "A rule which states that any waste derived from the treatment of a hazardous waste remains hazardous waste.",
        "options": [
            "The mixture rule",
            "The treatment rule",
            "The derived from rule",
            "The hazard rule"
        ],
        "answer": "The derived from rule"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Generally refers to sulfur trioxide SO3 in the flue gas.",
        "options": [
            "Acid rain",
            "Acid gas",
            "Hydrochloric acids",
            "Stack gas"
        ],
        "answer": "Acid gas"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "What consists of weak solutions of sulfuric, hydrochloric, and to a lesser extent, nitric acids?",
        "options": [
            "Stack gas",
            "Acid rain",
            "Acid compound",
            "Pollutant"
        ],
        "answer": "Acid rain"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "A fibrous silicate mineral material that is inert, strong and incombustible.",
        "options": [
            "Fiberglass",
            "Plastic",
            "Rubber",
            "Asbestos"
        ],
        "answer": "Asbestos"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "An insulator with superior tensile strength but low heat resistance.",
        "options": [
            "Rubber",
            "Plastic",
            "Fiberglass",
            "Asbestos"
        ],
        "answer": "Fiberglass"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Are highly concentrated liquid wastes produced in landfills.",
        "options": [
            "Aerosols",
            "Leachates",
            "Nitrogen dioxide",
            "Urea"
        ],
        "answer": "Leachates"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "What is the primary cause of smog formation?",
        "options": [
            "Toxins",
            "Dioxins",
            "Oxidants",
            "Nitrogen oxides"
        ],
        "answer": "Nitrogen oxides"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Is a water soluble organic compound prepared from ammonia. It has significant biological and industrial usefulness.",
        "options": [
            "Urea or carbamide urea",
            "Nitrite",
            "Chlorinated organics",
            "Oxidants"
        ],
        "answer": "Urea or carbamide urea"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Are by products of reaction between combustion products.",
        "options": [
            "Photochemical",
            "Oxidants",
            "Organics",
            "Sediments"
        ],
        "answer": "Oxidants"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "“Particulate matter” is defined as all particles that are emitted by a combustion source. What is another term for particulate matter?",
        "options": [
            "Dust",
            "Aerosol",
            "Biosolids",
            "Sediments"
        ],
        "answer": "Aerosol"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Are organic compounds manufactured in oily liquid and solid forms through the late 1970s and subsequently prohibited.",
        "options": [
            "Polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs)",
            "Polyvinyl chloride (PVC)",
            "Trihalomethanes",
            "Plastic"
        ],
        "answer": "Polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs)"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "A type of polymer used for styrofoam cups and “clam shell” fodd containers.",
        "options": [
            "Polyvinyl chloride (PVC)",
            "Polystyrene (PS)",
            "Low density polyethelene (LDPE)",
            "Polypropylene (PP)"
        ],
        "answer": "Polystyrene (PS)"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "A type of polymer used for labels, bottles and housewares.",
        "options": [
            "Polyvinyl chloride (PVC)",
            "Polystyrene (PS)",
            "Low density polyethelene (LDPE)",
            "Polypropylene (PP)"
        ],
        "answer": "Polypropylene (PP)"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "A type of polymer used for clear bottles.",
        "options": [
            "Polyvinyl chloride (PVC)",
            "Polystyrene (PS)",
            "Low density polyethelene (LDPE)",
            "Polypropylene (PP)"
        ],
        "answer": "Polyvinyl chloride (PVC)"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Refers to the high – temperature removal of tarry substance from the interior of the carbon granule leaving a highly porous structure.",
        "options": [
            "Absorbent",
            "Activated",
            "Breakthrough",
            "Adsorbent"
        ],
        "answer": "Activated"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "A substance with high surface area per unit weight, and intricate pore structure, and a hydrophobic surface.",
        "options": [
            "Adsorbent substance",
            "Absorbent substance",
            "Homogeneous substance",
            "Activated substance"
        ],
        "answer": "Adsorbent substance"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Is a high – temperature process that turns incinerator ash into a safe, glass – like material.",
        "options": [
            "Advance oxidation",
            "Biofitration",
            "Vitrification",
            "Bioventing"
        ],
        "answer": "Vitrification"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Refers to the use of compositing and soil beds.",
        "options": [
            "Biofiltration",
            "Biomediation",
            "Bioventing",
            "Bioreactors"
        ],
        "answer": "Biofiltration"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Are open or closed tanks containing dozens or hundreds of slowly rotating disks covered with a biological film microorganisms.",
        "options": [
            "biofilter",
            "bioreaction",
            "biomediator",
            "bioinventor"
        ],
        "answer": "bioreaction"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Refers to the treatment of contaminated in a large plastic – covered tank.",
        "options": [
            "Bioventing",
            "Biological recycling",
            "Biocycle",
            "Bioremediation"
        ],
        "answer": "Bioventing"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "All of the following occur during oxidation of a substance except ________.",
        "options": [
            "Oxidation state increases",
            "Loss of electrons",
            "The substance becomes less negative",
            "Oxidation of the oxidizing agent"
        ],
        "answer": "Oxidation of the oxidizing agent"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "All of the following occur during reduction of a substance except _______.",
        "options": [
            "An increase in negative charge",
            "Loss of electrons",
            "An oxidation state decrease",
            "Reduction of the oxidizing agent"
        ],
        "answer": "Loss of electrons"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "All of the following are units of energy except:",
        "options": [
            "Calories",
            "Joules",
            "Pascal",
            "meV"
        ],
        "answer": "Pascal"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "What do you call the mixture if the solute particles of a solid suspended in a liquid are larger than molecules?",
        "options": [
            "Solution",
            "Suspension",
            "Hydration",
            "Saturated solution"
        ],
        "answer": "Suspension"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "What do you call the mixture when a solvent has dissolved as much solute as it can?",
        "options": [
            "Solution",
            "Mild solution",
            "Hydration",
            "Saturated solution"
        ],
        "answer": "Saturated solution"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The equilibrium constant for weak solution is known as",
        "options": [
            "Ionization constant",
            "Arrhenius exponent",
            "Solubility product",
            "La Chatelier’s constant"
        ],
        "answer": "Ionization constant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "What do you call the mixture if the solute particles of solid suspended in a liquid are larger than the molecules?",
        "options": [
            "Solution",
            "Suspension",
            "Hydration",
            "Saturated solution"
        ],
        "answer": "Suspension"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "What do you call the mixture when a solvent has dissolved as much as solute it can?",
        "options": [
            "Solution",
            "Mild solution",
            "Hydration",
            "Saturated solution"
        ],
        "answer": "Saturated solution"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The equilibrium constant for weak solution is known as:",
        "options": [
            "Ionization constant",
            "Arrhenius exponent",
            "Solubility product",
            "La Chantelier’s constant"
        ],
        "answer": "Ionization constant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "If the solute particles of a solid suspended in a liquid are larger than molecules, the mixture is known as:",
        "options": [
            "Solution",
            "Suspension",
            "Hydration",
            "Saturated solution"
        ],
        "answer": "Suspension"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "When a solvent has dissolved as much solute as it can, the mixture is called:",
        "options": [
            "Solution",
            "Suspension",
            "Hydration",
            "Saturated solution"
        ],
        "answer": "Saturated solution"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "When excess solute in a solution settles to the bottom of the container, the process is called:",
        "options": [
            "Salvation",
            "Deemulsification",
            "Precipitation",
            "Equation"
        ],
        "answer": "Precipitation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "All of the following express units of concentration except:",
        "options": [
            "Normality",
            "Molarity",
            "Formality",
            "Isotropy"
        ],
        "answer": "Isotropy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The desirable temperature inside an air conditioned auditorium is:",
        "options": [
            "0°C",
            "5°C",
            "10°C",
            "20°C"
        ],
        "answer": "20°C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Which of the following acts as ignition accelerator for internal combustion engine fuels?",
        "options": [
            "Acetone peroxide",
            "Hydrogen peroxide",
            "Aromatic compounds",
            "n – heptane"
        ],
        "answer": "Acetone peroxide"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Which of the following does not use ambient air for propulsion?",
        "options": [
            "Turbo jet",
            "Turbo – prop",
            "Pulse jet",
            "Rocket"
        ],
        "answer": "Turbo – prop"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Most observe properties of light and other radiant energy are consistent with waves in nature, but in interaction with matter, electromagnetic energy behaves as through it consists of discrete pieces or",
        "options": [
            "Blocks",
            "Balls",
            "Quanta",
            "Atomic masses"
        ],
        "answer": "Quanta"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The amount of energy absorbed when a substance enters a solution is called the:",
        "options": [
            "Heat of fussion",
            "Heat of sublimation",
            "Endothermic heat of solution",
            "Exothermic heat of solution"
        ],
        "answer": "Endothermic heat of solution"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The absorption of water by a dessicant often demonstrates:",
        "options": [
            "Heat of fussion",
            "Heat of sublimation",
            "Endothermic heat of solution",
            "Exothermic heat of solution"
        ],
        "answer": "Exothermic heat of solution"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "A substance that absorbs moisture from the air is:",
        "options": [
            "Deliquescent",
            "Efflorescent",
            "Effervescent",
            "A precipitant"
        ],
        "answer": "Deliquescent"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The removal of a dissolved gas or other volatile component from liquid by exposing the liquid to air or steam is known as:",
        "options": [
            "Stripping",
            "Gas absorption",
            "Spraying",
            "Scrubbing"
        ],
        "answer": "Stripping"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Which of the following contribute to the deterioration of the Earth’s ozone layer?",
        "options": [
            "Carbon monoxide",
            "Chlorofluorocarbons",
            "Carbon dioxide",
            "Refrigerants"
        ],
        "answer": "Chlorofluorocarbons"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Ozone filters out what type of radiation that damages crops and causes skin cancer?",
        "options": [
            "Tropospheric radiation",
            "Atmospheric radiation",
            "X-rays",
            "Ultraviolet radiation"
        ],
        "answer": "Ultraviolet radiation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "All of the following affect of reaction except:",
        "options": [
            "Exposed surface area",
            "Concentrations",
            "Temperature",
            "Pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "Pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Le Chantelier’s principle predicts the direction of a state of chemical equilibrium based on all of the following factors except:",
        "options": [
            "Temperature",
            "Specific volume",
            "Pressure",
            "Concentration"
        ],
        "answer": "Specific volume"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The amount of energy necessary to cause a reaction to occur is called the _______.",
        "options": [
            "Heat of formation",
            "Heat of solution",
            "Activation of energy",
            "Heat of fusion"
        ],
        "answer": "Activation of energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The equilibrium constant for weak solutions is known as _______.",
        "options": [
            "The ionization constant",
            "The Arrhenius exponent",
            "The solubility product",
            "Le Chantelier’s principle"
        ],
        "answer": "The ionization constant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The speed at which a reaction proceeds to equilibrium is the purview of ________.",
        "options": [
            "Reaction kinetics",
            "Le Chatelier’s principle",
            "Neutralization",
            "Ionization"
        ],
        "answer": "Reaction kinetics"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The color of water is measured:",
        "options": [
            "In terms of pH value",
            "In terms of degree of hardness",
            "In terms of platinum cobalt scale",
            "Ppm of dissolved solids"
        ],
        "answer": "In terms of platinum cobalt scale"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "What turbidimeter that gives direct readings in ppm?",
        "options": [
            "Jackson turbidimeter",
            "Hellige turbidimeter",
            "Baylis turbidimeter",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Jackson turbidimeter"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Which of the following is not a sound absorptive material?",
        "options": [
            "Rugs",
            "Mirrors",
            "Carpets",
            "Heavy Drapes"
        ],
        "answer": "Mirrors"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The total cross section of a target atom is made up of _______.",
        "options": [
            "The absorption cross section",
            "The scattering cross section",
            "The absorption and scattering cross sections",
            "The reflection and absorption cross sections"
        ],
        "answer": "The absorption and scattering cross sections"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Which of the following cannot be a phenomenon of neutron interactions?",
        "options": [
            "Inelastic scattering",
            "Elastic scattering",
            "Fission",
            "Fusion"
        ],
        "answer": "Fusion"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "Which of the following cannot be used to describe neutron kinetic energy levels?",
        "options": [
            "Cold",
            "Thermal",
            "Slow",
            "Freezing"
        ],
        "answer": "Freezing"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "All of the following are words used to describe neutron kinetic energy levels except:",
        "options": [
            "Slow (resonant)",
            "Fast",
            "Supersonic",
            "Relativistic"
        ],
        "answer": "Supersonic"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The reduction of nuclear radiation intensity (called attenuation) is accomplished by:",
        "options": [
            "Matter",
            "Antimatter",
            "Shielding",
            "Neurons"
        ],
        "answer": "Shielding"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 10,
        "question": "The ability of substance to absorb neurons depends upon its ________.",
        "options": [
            "Absorption cross section",
            "Scattering cross section",
            "Total cross section",
            "Atomic number"
        ],
        "answer": "Absorption cross section"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "If the energy of the incident photons is less than the work function:",
        "options": [
            "An electron will be ejected",
            "More than one electron will be ejected",
            "An electron will not be ejected",
            "Less than one electron will be ejected"
        ],
        "answer": "An electron will not be ejected"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "For supersonic, the pressure of fluid must decrease as the fluid flow area of the duct",
        "options": [
            "Increases",
            "Decreases",
            "Remain the same",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Increases"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Density in terms of viscosity is",
        "options": [
            "Kinematic viscosity / dynamic viscosity",
            "Dynamic viscosity / kinematic viscosity",
            "Kinematic viscosity x dynamic viscosity",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Dynamic viscosity / kinematic viscosity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Liquids and gases take the following characteristics (s) of their contents.",
        "options": [
            "Volume",
            "Shape",
            "Shape and volume",
            "Neither shape nor volume"
        ],
        "answer": "Shape"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Which of the following statement about a Newtonian fluid is most accurate?",
        "options": [
            "Shear stress is proportional to strain",
            "Viscosity is zero",
            "Shear stress is multi – valued",
            "Shear stress is proportional rate of strain"
        ],
        "answer": "Shear stress is proportional rate of strain"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The normal stress is the same in all directions at a point in fluid:",
        "options": [
            "Independent of the motion of one fluid layer relative to an adjacent layer",
            "When there is no motion of one fluid layer relative to an adjacent layer",
            "Only if the fluid is frictionless",
            "Only if fluid is frictionless and incompressible"
        ],
        "answer": "When there is no motion of one fluid layer relative to an adjacent layer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Which of the following is not a characteristic of pressure?",
        "options": [
            "It is the same in all direction at a point in the fluid",
            "It acts normal to a surface",
            "It is a shear stress",
            "It is linear with depth"
        ],
        "answer": "It is a shear stress"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The length of mercury column at a place at an altitude will change with respect to that at ground in.",
        "options": [
            "A linear relation",
            "A parabolic relation",
            "Will remain constant",
            "First slowly and then steeply"
        ],
        "answer": "First slowly and then steeply"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "All of the following dimensionless parameters are applicable to the flow fluid problems except the ________.",
        "options": [
            "Reynolds number",
            "Froude number",
            "Mach number",
            "Blot number"
        ],
        "answer": "Blot number"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Mass density of liquid (p) is given by which of the following?",
        "options": [
            "P = mass / volume",
            "P = metric slug / m2",
            "P = kg sec2 / m4",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The speed of sound in all fluids is most closely related to all f the following properties except _________.",
        "options": [
            "Compressibility",
            "Density",
            "Bulk modulus",
            "Thermal conductivity"
        ],
        "answer": "Thermal conductivity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Under which condition, the specific weight of water is 1000 kg/m3?",
        "options": [
            "At normal pressure of 760 mm",
            "At 4°C temperature",
            "At mean sea level",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "All of the following can be characteristics of fluids except __________.",
        "options": [
            "Kinetic viscosity",
            "Surface tension",
            "Bulk modulus",
            "Hysteresis"
        ],
        "answer": "Hysteresis"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Which of the following can be used to measure the flow of water in a pipe of diameter 3000mm?",
        "options": [
            "Venturimeter",
            "Rotameter",
            "Nozzle",
            "Pitot tube"
        ],
        "answer": "Pitot tube"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The pressure at a given depth due to several immiscible liquids is:",
        "options": [
            "The average of the individual pressures",
            "The sum of the individual pressure",
            "Independ of the individual pressures",
            "Unknown"
        ],
        "answer": "The sum of the individual pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The equation of continuity of flow is applicable if:",
        "options": [
            "The flow is one dimensional",
            "The flow is steady",
            "The velocity is uniform over the cross – section",
            "All of the above conditions are together"
        ],
        "answer": "All of the above conditions are together"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Uniform flow takes place when:",
        "options": [
            "Condition remain unchanged with time at any point",
            "Rate of change of velocity of fluid is zero",
            "At every point the velocity vector is identical in magnitude and direction for any given instant",
            "The change in transverse direction is zero"
        ],
        "answer": "At every point the velocity vector is identical in magnitude and direction for any given"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The continuity equation of an ideal fluid flow:",
        "options": [
            "States that the net rate of in – flow into any small volume must be zero",
            "Applies to irrotational flow only",
            "States that the energy remains constant along streamline",
            "State that energy is constant everywhere in the fluid"
        ],
        "answer": "State that energy is constant everywhere in the fluid"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "A pitot tube can be used to measure fluid velocity as described by the Bernoulli’s equation and the relationship between:",
        "options": [
            "Kinetic energy and static pressure",
            "Fluid pressure and height of the fluid",
            "Fluid pressure and impact energy",
            "Pressure and momentum"
        ],
        "answer": "Kinetic energy and static pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "In order to avoid vaporization in the pipe line, the pipe line over the ridge is laid in such a way that it is not more tha:",
        "options": [
            "2.4 m above the hydraulic gradient",
            "6.4 m above the hydraulic gradient",
            "10.0 m above the hydraulic gradient",
            "5.0 above the hydraulic gradient"
        ],
        "answer": "6.4 m above the hydraulic gradient"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The stream function is a useful parameter in describing ___________.",
        "options": [
            "The conservation of mass",
            "The conservation of momentum",
            "The conservation of energy",
            "The equation of state"
        ],
        "answer": "The conservation of mass"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "For high speed flow, the potential energy of the fluids are:",
        "options": [
            "Positive",
            "Negative",
            "Negligible",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Negligible"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "McLeod gauge for low pressure measurement operates on the principle of __________.",
        "options": [
            "Gas law",
            "Boyle’s law",
            "Charles law",
            "Pascal’s law"
        ],
        "answer": "Boyle’s law"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "A Kaplan turbine is",
        "options": [
            "A high head flow turbine",
            "An impulse turbine, inward flow",
            "A reaction turbine, outward flow",
            "Low head axial flow turbine"
        ],
        "answer": "Low head axial flow turbine"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The most common method for calculating frictional energy loss for laminar flowing fluids in noncircular pipes is:",
        "options": [
            "The Darcy equation",
            "The Hagan – Poisevill equation",
            "The Hazen – Williams equation",
            "The Swamee – Jins equation"
        ],
        "answer": "The Darcy equation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Friction factor for both laminar and turbulent flows can be found plotted in a",
        "options": [
            "Steam table",
            "Psychrometric chart",
            "Moody diagram",
            "Mollier diagram"
        ],
        "answer": "Moody diagram"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Which of the following is relative velocity?",
        "options": [
            "The difference between two velocities",
            "Average velocity",
            "Sum of two velocities",
            "Vector difference of two velocities"
        ],
        "answer": "Vector difference of two velocities"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Which of the following is the highest head?",
        "options": [
            "33 inch Hg",
            "31.0 ft. water",
            "1.013 kg kg/cm2",
            "75.0 cm of Hg"
        ],
        "answer": "33 inch Hg"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "For stable equilibrium of floating body its metacenter",
        "options": [
            "Below the center of gravity",
            "Below the center of buoyancy",
            "Above the center of buoyancy",
            "Above the center of gravity"
        ],
        "answer": "Above the center of gravity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Center of pressure of an inclined plane lies ________",
        "options": [
            "At he centroid",
            "Above the centroid",
            "Below the centroid",
            "At metacenter"
        ],
        "answer": "Below the centroid"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The line of action of the buoyant forces always acts through the centroid of the ________",
        "options": [
            "Submerged body",
            "Volume of the floating body",
            "Volume of the fluid vertically above the body",
            "Displaced volume of the fluid"
        ],
        "answer": "Displaced volume of the fluid"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The hydraulic grade line of a pipeline denotes which of the flowing?",
        "options": [
            "Total energy",
            "Pressure energy",
            "Potential energy",
            "The sum of pressure energy and  potential energy"
        ],
        "answer": "The sum of pressure energy and  potential energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The energy grades line of a pipeline denotes which of the following",
        "options": [
            "Total energy",
            "Pressure energy",
            "Potential energy",
            "The sum of pressure energy and potential energy"
        ],
        "answer": "Total energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The presence of friction in the energy grade line will always cause the line to slope",
        "options": [
            "Down in the direction of the flow",
            "Upward in the direction of the flow",
            "Level (no slope)",
            "There is no effect of friction on the energy grade line"
        ],
        "answer": "Down in the direction of the flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The pitot tube is a device used for measurement of",
        "options": [
            "Pressure",
            "Flow",
            "Velocity",
            "Discharge"
        ],
        "answer": "Velocity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Hydrometer is used to find out",
        "options": [
            "Specific gravity of liquids",
            "Specific gravity of solids",
            "Specific gravity of gases",
            "Relative humidity"
        ],
        "answer": "Specific gravity of liquids"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The fluid forces taken into consideration in the Navier strokes equation are:",
        "options": [
            "Gravity, Pressure and viscous",
            "Gravity, pressure turbulent",
            "Pressure, viscous and turbulence",
            "Gravity, viscous and turbulence"
        ],
        "answer": "Gravity, Pressure and viscous"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Permissible velocity of water flowing through concrete tunnel, is generally",
        "options": [
            "4 – 5 m/s",
            "10 – 12 m/s",
            "13 – 16 m/s",
            "20 m/s"
        ],
        "answer": "4 – 5 m/s"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Orifice refers to an opening",
        "options": [
            "With closed perimeter and regulating from through which water flows",
            "With prolonged sides having length of 2 to 3 diameters of opening in the thick wall",
            "With partially full flow",
            "In hydraulic structure with regulation provision"
        ],
        "answer": "In hydraulic structure with regulation provision"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The value of coefficient of discharge in comparison to coefficient of velocity is found to be ________.",
        "options": [
            "More",
            "Less",
            "Same",
            "More/less depending on flow"
        ],
        "answer": "Less"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Weir refers to an opening",
        "options": [
            "Having closed perimeter and of regular form through which water flows",
            "Having prolonged sides with length of 2 to 3 diameters of opening in thick wait",
            "Having partially full flow",
            "In hydraulic structure with regulation provision"
        ],
        "answer": "Having partially full flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Which of the following parameters determine the friction factor of turbulent flow in a rough pipe?",
        "options": [
            "Froude number and relative roughness",
            "Froude number and Mach number",
            "Reynolds number and relative roughness",
            "Mach number and relative roughness"
        ],
        "answer": "Reynolds number and relative roughness"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Power transmitted through a pipe is maximum when the loss of head due to friction is:",
        "options": [
            "One – half of the total head supplied",
            "One – third of the total head supplied",
            "One – fourth of the total head supplied",
            "Equal to the total head supplied"
        ],
        "answer": "One – third of the total head supplied"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "In a nozzle if back pressure is same as inlet pressure; then __________.",
        "options": [
            "No flow takes place",
            "Maximum flow takes place",
            "Flow becomes subsonic in diverging section",
            "Flow becomes supersonic in converging as well as supersonic section"
        ],
        "answer": "No flow takes place"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The flow on two sides of a normal shock wave is called _________.",
        "options": [
            "Sonic",
            "Sub – sonic",
            "Supersonic",
            "Supersonic on one side and sub – sonic on the other side"
        ],
        "answer": "Supersonic on one side and sub – sonic on the other side"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Which of the following is the basic of bernoulli’s law for fluid flow?",
        "options": [
            "Continuity equation",
            "Principle of conversation of energy",
            "Fourier’ law",
            "Principle of conservation of mass"
        ],
        "answer": "Principle of conversation of energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Which of the following is NOT a characteristic of fluid pressure?",
        "options": [
            "It is shear stress",
            "It is the same in all direction at a point in the fluid",
            "It acts normal to a surface",
            "It is linear with depth"
        ],
        "answer": "It is shear stress"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Refers to the compressibility of a fluid, the fractional change in fluid volume per unit change in fluid.",
        "options": [
            "Viscosity",
            "Bulk modulus",
            "Density",
            "Pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "Pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "A pitot tube can be used to measure fluid velocity as described by the Bernoulli equation and the relationship between:",
        "options": [
            "Kinetic energy and static pressure",
            "Fluid pressure and static pressure",
            "Fluid pressure and impact energy",
            "Pressure and momentum"
        ],
        "answer": "Kinetic energy and static pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "the ratio of the area to the wetted perimeter is known as ________.",
        "options": [
            "Flow factor",
            "Hydraulic radius",
            "Kutter’s C",
            "Value of k in darcy – weisbach formula"
        ],
        "answer": "Hydraulic radius"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "What is the coefficient of contraction?",
        "options": [
            "The ratio of the area of vena contracta to the area of the orifice",
            "The ratio of actual discharge to the theoretical discharge",
            "The ratio of the actual velocity to the theoretical velocity",
            "The ratio of the effective head to the actual head"
        ],
        "answer": "The ratio of the area of vena contracta to the area of the orifice"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Where is vena contracta most likely located?",
        "options": [
            "At the orifice",
            "At a distance approximately 1⁄2 the diameter of the orifice",
            "At a distance approximately equal to the diameter of the orifice",
            "At a distance approximately twice the diameter of the orifice"
        ],
        "answer": "At a distance approximately 1⁄2 the diameter of the orifice"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "A substance that is able to flow and yields to any force tending to change its shape without changing its volume such as water and air.",
        "options": [
            "Fluid",
            "Flux",
            "Gas oil",
            "Water gas"
        ],
        "answer": "Fluid"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The velocity of a fluid particle at the center of the pipe section is _________.",
        "options": [
            "Maximum",
            "Minimum",
            "Average",
            "Logarithmic average"
        ],
        "answer": "Maximum"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "For supersonic flow, the pressure of the fluid must increase as the fluid flow area of the duct:",
        "options": [
            "Increases",
            "Decreases",
            "Constant",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Decreases"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Which is incorrect statement regarding apparent shear forces.",
        "options": [
            "It can never be found in frictionless fluid regardless of its motion",
            "It can never be found when the fluid is at rest",
            "It depends upon cohesive forces",
            "It may occur owing to cohesive when the fluid is at rest"
        ],
        "answer": "It may occur owing to cohesive when the fluid is at rest"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The time required for half a quantity of radioactive particles to decay (disintegrate) is called its _________.",
        "options": [
            "Average life",
            "Median life",
            "Time Constant",
            "Half time"
        ],
        "answer": "Half time"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "SI unit of viscosity is:",
        "options": [
            "10 times poise",
            "9.81 times poise",
            "1 / 9.81 times poise",
            "1 / 10 time poise"
        ],
        "answer": "10 times poise"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "For computation convenience, fluid are usually classed as:",
        "options": [
            "Rotational or irrotational",
            "Real or ideal",
            "Laminar or turbulent",
            "Newtonian or non-Newtonian"
        ],
        "answer": "Real or ideal"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Which of the following is not a dimensionless parameter?",
        "options": [
            "Kinetic viscosity",
            "Weber number",
            "Darcy Weisbach friction factor",
            "Froude number"
        ],
        "answer": "Kinetic viscosity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Which of the following is not a characteristic of real fluids?",
        "options": [
            "Finite viscosity",
            "Non – uniform velocity distributions",
            "Compressibility",
            "Experience of eddy currents and turbulence"
        ],
        "answer": "Experience of eddy currents and turbulence"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Which of the following is not the mass density of water?",
        "options": [
            "62.5 lbm/ft3",
            "100 kg/m3",
            "1 g/cm3",
            "1 kg/L"
        ],
        "answer": "100 kg/m3"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The upper critical Reynolds number for pipe flow is:",
        "options": [
            "Of no practical importance to designers",
            "Always used to design pipes for strength",
            "The number at which turbulent flow changes over to laminar flow",
            "The number at which laminar flow changes into turbulent flow"
        ],
        "answer": "Of no practical importance to designers"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Which of the following statements about gauge pressure is most correct? Gauge pressure are measured relative to ________.",
        "options": [
            "Atmospheric pressure",
            "A vacuum",
            "Each other",
            "The surface"
        ],
        "answer": "Atmospheric pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The volumetric change of the fluid caused by a resistance is called ________.",
        "options": [
            "Volumetric strain",
            "Volumetric index",
            "Compressibility",
            "Adhesion"
        ],
        "answer": "Adhesion"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Compressibility of a fluid relates the fractional change in fluid volume per unit change in fluid.",
        "options": [
            "Temperature",
            "Density",
            "Pressure",
            "Viscosity"
        ],
        "answer": "Density"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Property of a fluid wherby its own molecules are attracted is known as _________.",
        "options": [
            "Adhesion",
            "Cohesion",
            "Surface tension",
            "Viscosity"
        ],
        "answer": "Cohesion"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The term subsonic flow refers to a flowing gas with a speed:",
        "options": [
            "Less than the local speed of sound",
            "Equal to the speed of sound",
            "Greater than the speed of sound",
            "Much greater than the speed of sound"
        ],
        "answer": "Less than the local speed of sound"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The pressure at a point in a fluid will not be same in at the directions if the fluid is:",
        "options": [
            "Viscous",
            "Viscous and static",
            "Inviscous and in motion",
            "Viscous and is in motion"
        ],
        "answer": "Viscous and is in motion"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The statement that the hydrostatic pressure at a fluid exerts on an immersed object or on container walls is a function only of fluid depth is",
        "options": [
            "The perfect gas law",
            "D’Alembert’s paradox",
            "The hydrostatic paradox",
            "Boyle’s law"
        ],
        "answer": "The hydrostatic paradox"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Bernoulli’s equation is s/an ___________.",
        "options": [
            "Momentum equation",
            "Conservation of energy equation",
            "Conservation of mass equation",
            "Equation of state"
        ],
        "answer": "Conservation of energy equation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "AN ideal fluid is one that:",
        "options": [
            "Is very viscous",
            "Obeys Newton’s law viscosity",
            "Is assumed in problems in condult flow",
            "Is frictionless and incompressible"
        ],
        "answer": "Is frictionless and incompressible"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The relation between pressure and attitude in the atmospheric is given by the:",
        "options": [
            "Perfect gas law",
            "Conservation of mass",
            "Barometric height relationship",
            "First law of thermodynamics"
        ],
        "answer": "Barometric height relationship"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The fact the buoyant force on a floating object equal to the weight of the water displaced is:",
        "options": [
            "Bernoulli’s law",
            "Archimedes principle",
            "The law of diminishing returns",
            "The conservation of mass"
        ],
        "answer": "Archimedes principle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Which of the following terms does not appear in the steady flow energy equation (the extended Bernoulli’s equation)?",
        "options": [
            "Kinetic energy",
            "Potential energy",
            "Friction losses",
            "Hysteresis losses"
        ],
        "answer": "Hysteresis losses"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Neglecting the force due to inertia, gravity and frictional resistance, the design of a channel can be made by comparing",
        "options": [
            "Weber number",
            "Reynolds number",
            "Froude’s number",
            "Prant’l number"
        ],
        "answer": "Froude’s number"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The difference between stagnation pressure and total pressure is:",
        "options": [
            "Due to height difference",
            "Due to kinetic energy",
            "None of the terms are interchangeable",
            "Important only in supersonic flow"
        ],
        "answer": "None of the terms are interchangeable"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Fully turbulent flow in a pipe is characterized by all of the following except:",
        "options": [
            "A parabolic velocity profile",
            "A momentum exchange due to fluid masses rather than molecules",
            "A maximum velocity at the fluid center line",
            "A 1/7 velocity profile"
        ],
        "answer": "A parabolic velocity profile"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The laminar friction factor of fluid flowing through pipe is a function of all of the following except:",
        "options": [
            "Fluid velocity",
            "Pipe diameter",
            "Pipe roughness",
            "Reynolds number"
        ],
        "answer": "Pipe roughness"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The continuity equation is a applicable to:",
        "options": [
            "Viscous unviscous fluids",
            "Compressibility of fluids",
            "Conservation of mass",
            "Steady unsteady flow"
        ],
        "answer": "Conservation of mass"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The rise or fail of head ‘h’ in a capillary tube of diameter ‘d’ and liquid surface tension ‘s’ and specific weight ‘w’ is given by:",
        "options": [
            "4s/wd",
            "4ds/w",
            "4wd/s",
            "4ws/d"
        ],
        "answer": "4s/wd"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The study of the practical laws of fluid flow and the resistance of open pipes and channels",
        "options": [
            "Fluid mechanics",
            "Hydraulics",
            "Aerodynamics",
            "Thermodynamics"
        ],
        "answer": "Hydraulics"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Which of the following turbine is different from the others?",
        "options": [
            "Fourneyron turbine",
            "Francis turbine",
            "Kaplan turbine",
            "Prelton wheel"
        ],
        "answer": "Prelton wheel"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Running away seed of a Pelton wheel gives:",
        "options": [
            "Actual operating speed",
            "No load speed",
            "Full load speed",
            "No load speed when governor mechanism fails"
        ],
        "answer": "No load speed when governor mechanism fails"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The characteristic length of the Reynold’s number to calculate the friction in noncircular full running pipe is based on the ________.",
        "options": [
            "Run length",
            "Pipe length",
            "Hydraulic diameter (the equivalent diameter)",
            "Wetted circumference"
        ],
        "answer": "Hydraulic diameter (the equivalent diameter)"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The hydraulic radius of noncircular pipe is:",
        "options": [
            "The square root of the flow area",
            "The ratio of the area to the wetted perimeter",
            "The radius of the pipe of equivalent area",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "The ratio of the area to the wetted perimeter"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The Darcy equation can be used for all liquids and flow except:",
        "options": [
            "Water",
            "Alcohol",
            "Gasoline",
            "Air flowing supersonically"
        ],
        "answer": "Air flowing supersonically"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The Hazen – Williams formula for head loss due to friction is based upon:",
        "options": [
            "Rigorous mathematical derivation",
            "Empirical data",
            "Semi – empirical analysis",
            "Screndipity"
        ],
        "answer": "Empirical data"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The extended Bernoulli equation includes all of the following terms except:",
        "options": [
            "Potential energy",
            "Kinetic energy",
            "Nuclear energy",
            "Friction losses"
        ],
        "answer": "Nuclear energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "An equipotential line is one that:",
        "options": [
            "Has no velocity component tangent to it",
            "Has uniformly varying dynamic pressure",
            "Has no velocity component normal to it",
            "Exist in case of rotational flow"
        ],
        "answer": "Exist in case of rotational flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "What is the use of a hydraulic jump?",
        "options": [
            "Increase te flow rate",
            "Reduce the flow rate",
            "Reduce the velocity of flow",
            "Reduce the energy of flow"
        ],
        "answer": "Reduce the energy of flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "What do you call the lowest portion to storage basin from where the water is not drawn?",
        "options": [
            "Bottom storage",
            "Sub soil storage",
            "Spring reserve",
            "Dead storage"
        ],
        "answer": "Dead storage"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The presence of friction in the hydraulic grade line will always cause the line to slope:",
        "options": [
            "Down in the direction of the flow",
            "Upward in the direction do the flow",
            "Level (no slope)",
            "There is no effect of friction on the energy grade line"
        ],
        "answer": "Down in the direction of the flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The presence of a minor loss in the energy grade line will cause the line to slope:",
        "options": [
            "Down in the direction of the flow",
            "Upward in the direction of the flow",
            "Vertically downward",
            "There is no effect of friction on the energy grade line"
        ],
        "answer": "Down in the direction of the flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "What do you call the pressure which the fluid exerts on an immersed objects or container walls?",
        "options": [
            "Normal pressure",
            "Standard liquid pressure",
            "Hydrostatic pressure",
            "Gage pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "Hydrostatic pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Viscosity for a fluid is defined as the constant of proportional between shear and what other variable?",
        "options": [
            "The spatial derivative of velocity",
            "The time derivative of pressure",
            "The time derivative of density",
            "The spatial derivative of density"
        ],
        "answer": "The spatial derivative of velocity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "What is the classification of the fluid flow if the fluid travels parallel to the adjacent do not layers and the paths of the individual particles do not cross each other?",
        "options": [
            "Steady flow",
            "Laminar Flow",
            "Uniform flow",
            "Turbulent flow"
        ],
        "answer": "Laminar Flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Which of the following refers to the measure of a fluid’s sensitivity to changes in viscosity with changes in temperature?",
        "options": [
            "Viscosity index",
            "Coefficient of viscosity",
            "Viscosity ratio",
            "Viscosity factor"
        ],
        "answer": "Viscosity index"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "IF the number is greater than 1 but lesser than 5, what is the standard classification of the travel?",
        "options": [
            "Transonic travel",
            "Subsonic travel",
            "Hypesonic travel",
            "Supersonic travel"
        ],
        "answer": "Supersonic travel"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "What is measured by a Pitot tube?",
        "options": [
            "Volumetric discharge",
            "Mass flow",
            "Pressure",
            "Velocity"
        ],
        "answer": "Velocity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "What is the difference between the energy grade line and the hydraulic grade line?",
        "options": [
            "Potential energy",
            "Pressure energy",
            "Kinetic energy",
            "Friction losses"
        ],
        "answer": "Kinetic energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Kinetic energy is not neglected in calculations of:",
        "options": [
            "High speed flow",
            "Low speed flow",
            "Steady flow",
            "Equilibrium flow"
        ],
        "answer": "High speed flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Discharge losses through orifice are due to:",
        "options": [
            "Friction losses",
            "Minor losses",
            "Both friction and minor losses",
            "Pressure losses"
        ],
        "answer": "Both friction and minor losses"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Which of the following is considered as an important parameter in the study of compressible flow?",
        "options": [
            "Speed of fluid",
            "Speed of sound",
            "Speed of light",
            "Speed of fluid flow"
        ],
        "answer": "Speed of sound"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Is the velocity at which an infinitesimal small pressure wave travels through medium.",
        "options": [
            "Subsonic velocity",
            "Hypersonic velocity",
            "Sonic velocity",
            "Monatomic velocity"
        ],
        "answer": "Sonic velocity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "It is the ratio of the actual velocity of the fluid to the velocity of sound.",
        "options": [
            "Mach number",
            "Froude number",
            "Sonic number",
            "Euler number"
        ],
        "answer": "Mach number"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The flow is called sonic when Mach number is:",
        "options": [
            "Equal to 1",
            "Less than 1",
            "More than 1",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Equal to 1"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The following flow is sub – sonic when Mach no. is:",
        "options": [
            "Greater than 1",
            "Less than 1",
            "More than 1",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Less than 1"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The flow is supersonic when Mach no. is:",
        "options": [
            "Greater than zero",
            "Less than 1",
            "greater than 1",
            "none of these"
        ],
        "answer": "greater than 1"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The flow of transonic when",
        "options": [
            "M = 0",
            "M<1",
            "M>1",
            "M=1"
        ],
        "answer": "M=1"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The pressure decrease as the temperature and velocity increase while the fluid velocity and Mach number:",
        "options": [
            "Increases",
            "Decreases",
            "Remains constant",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Increases"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The Mach number is unity or one at the location of smallest flow area, called the:",
        "options": [
            "Decreasing are",
            "Throat",
            "Increasing area",
            "None of these"
        ],
        "answer": "Throat"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Which of the following is the example of a Newtonian fluid?",
        "options": [
            "Motor oils",
            "Gas",
            "Paints",
            "Clay slurries"
        ],
        "answer": "Gas"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "What is the pressure of water?",
        "options": [
            "150 kg/cm3",
            "Less than 200 kg/cm2",
            "More than 200 kg/cm2",
            "100 kg/cm2"
        ],
        "answer": "More than 200 kg/cm2"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The volumetric change of the fluid caused by a resistance is called:",
        "options": [
            "Volumetric change",
            "Volumetric index",
            "Compressibility",
            "Adhesion"
        ],
        "answer": "Adhesion"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The energy of a fluid flowing at any section in a pipeline is a function of:",
        "options": [
            "Velocity of flow only",
            "Pressure only",
            "Height above a chosen datum, density, internal energy, pressure and velocity of flow",
            "Pressure, height above a chosen datum, velocity of flow, density of liquid"
        ],
        "answer": "Height above a chosen datum, density, internal energy, pressure and velocity of flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "If the fluid travels parallel to the adjacent layers and the paths of individual particles do not cross, the fluid is said to be:",
        "options": [
            "Turbulent",
            "Critical",
            "Dynamic",
            "Laminar"
        ],
        "answer": "Laminar"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "Center of pressure on a inclined plane lies:",
        "options": [
            "At the centroid",
            "Above the centroid",
            "Below the centroid",
            "At the metacenter"
        ],
        "answer": "Below the centroid"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "At any instant, if the number of particles passing every cross – section of the stream is the same, the flow is said to be:",
        "options": [
            "Steady flow",
            "Uniform flow",
            "Continuous flow",
            "Laminar flow"
        ],
        "answer": "Steady flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The ratio of cross – sectional area flow to the wetted perimeter is:",
        "options": [
            "Hydraulic lead",
            "Hydraulic section",
            "Hydraulic mean depth",
            "Hydraulic gradient"
        ],
        "answer": "Hydraulic mean depth"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "If A is the cross – sectional area of the flow and Pw is the wetted perimeter of a pipe, then what is the hydraulic depth. Hd?",
        "options": [
            "Pw – A",
            "Pw / A",
            "A / Pw",
            "Pw x A"
        ],
        "answer": "A / Pw"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "If Q is the volume in gallon; D is height or elevation in it, and m is weight in lbs per gallon, what is the desired energy to lift the water from lower to higher elevation?",
        "options": [
            "E = mD/Q",
            "E = mDQ",
            "E = mQ/D",
            "E = QD/m"
        ],
        "answer": "E = mDQ"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 11,
        "question": "The flow of the convergent section of a nozzle is always subsonic. If the flow subsonic then the Mach number is:",
        "options": [
            "Greater than unity",
            "Less than unity",
            "Near unity",
            "Unity"
        ],
        "answer": "Less than unity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "One of the reasons for insulating the pipes is:",
        "options": [
            "They may not break under pressure",
            "There is minimum corrosion",
            "Capacity to withstand pressure is increased",
            "Heat loss from the surface is minimized"
        ],
        "answer": "Heat loss from the surface is minimized"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "The rate of radiant energy, that is emitted by a surface at any temperature and in small wavelengths is found from the known rate of energy, that under the same conditions will be emitted from a black surface, by multiplying with the absorptivity. The above enunciation is called:",
        "options": [
            "Lambert’s Law",
            "Kirchhoff’s Law",
            "Planck’s Law",
            "Stefan Boltzmann’s Law"
        ],
        "answer": "Kirchhoff’s Law"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "Which of the following is generally used to measure the temperature inside the furnace?",
        "options": [
            "Mercury thermometer",
            "Alcohol thermometer",
            "Ash thermometer",
            "Optical pyrometer"
        ],
        "answer": "Optical pyrometer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "All heat transfer processes:",
        "options": [
            "Involve transfer of energy",
            "Involve temperature difference between the bodies",
            "Obey first law of thermodynamics",
            "Obey second law of thermodynamics"
        ],
        "answer": "Involve temperature difference between the bodies"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "What is thermal diffusivity?",
        "options": [
            "A mathematical formula",
            "A physical property of the material",
            "A configuration for heat conduction",
            "A dimensionless parameter"
        ],
        "answer": "A physical property of the material"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "Which of the following is a unit of thermal diffusivity?",
        "options": [
            "m2/hr",
            "kcal/m2hr",
            "kcal/m2hroC",
            "m2/hroC"
        ],
        "answer": "m2/hr"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "Non-isotropic conductivity is shown by which of the following?",
        "options": [
            "Bass",
            "Copper",
            "Wood",
            "Steel"
        ],
        "answer": "Wood"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "For glass wool thermal conductivity changes from sample to sample due changes in:",
        "options": [
            "Structure",
            "Density",
            "Composition",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "Which of the following is the S.I. unit of thermal conductivity?",
        "options": [
            "W/m-hr-oK",
            "W/moK",
            "KJ/m-hr-oC",
            "W/m-hr-oC"
        ],
        "answer": "W/moK"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "What is the value of the Prandt’l number for air?",
        "options": [
            "10",
            "6.7",
            "67",
            "0.7"
        ],
        "answer": "0.7"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "According to Prevost theory of heat exchange,",
        "options": [
            "It is impossible to transfer heat from low temperature source to high temperature source.",
            "Heat transfer by radiation needs no medium",
            "All bodies above absolute zero emit radiation",
            "Heat transfer in most of the cases occurs by combination of conduction, convection and radiation"
        ],
        "answer": "All bodies above absolute zero emit radiation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "Thermal conductivity of wood depends on which of the following?",
        "options": [
            "Moisture",
            "Temperature",
            "Density",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "A fur coat on an animal will help the animal to remain:",
        "options": [
            "Warm in winter",
            "Cool in winter",
            "Warm in summer",
            "Cool in summer"
        ],
        "answer": "Warm in winter"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "The nature of flow of a fluid inside a tube, whether it is turbulent or laminar, can be ascertained by:",
        "options": [
            "Flow velocity",
            "Surface conditions",
            "Viscosity of fluid",
            "Reynolds number"
        ],
        "answer": "Reynolds number"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "By which of the following modes of heat transfer is the Stefan-Boltzmann law applicable?",
        "options": [
            "Conduction",
            "Radiation",
            "Conduction and radiation combined",
            "Convection and radiation combined"
        ],
        "answer": "Radiation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "At all wave lengths and temperatures the monochromatic emissivity of a white body is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "Zero",
            "0.5",
            "Unity",
            "0.1 to 0.5"
        ],
        "answer": "Zero"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "The radiation from flames is having",
        "options": [
            "Continuous radiation from burning spot particles of microscopic and submicroscopic dimensions",
            "Radiation from suspended larger particles of coal, coke, or ash contributing to flame lumininossity",
            "Infared radiation from water vapor and carbon dioxide",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "The statement that the emissivity and absorptivity of a surface is surrounded by its own temperature are the same for both monochromatic and total radiation is called:",
        "options": [
            "Lambert’s law",
            "Kirchhoff’s law",
            "D’ Alambart’s",
            "Law of emissivity"
        ],
        "answer": "Kirchhoff’s law"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "A reservoir that supplies energy in the form of heat is called:",
        "options": [
            "Source",
            "Sink",
            "Cold reservoir",
            "Heat reservoir"
        ],
        "answer": "Source"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "In regenerator type heat exchanger, heat transfer occurs by:",
        "options": [
            "Direct mixing of hot and cold fluids",
            "A complete separation between hot and cold fluids",
            "Flow of hot and cold fluids alternately over a surface",
            "Generation of heat again and again"
        ],
        "answer": "Flow of hot and cold fluids alternately over a surface"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "Least value of Prandt’l number can be excepted in case of ________.",
        "options": [
            "Liquid metals",
            "Sugar solution",
            "Salt solution",
            "Water"
        ],
        "answer": "Liquid metals"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "“The boiling point of a solution is a linear function of water at the same pressure.” The above statement is called ________.",
        "options": [
            "Dubring’s rule",
            "Petit and Dulong’s law",
            "Fick’s rule",
            "Reynold’s law"
        ],
        "answer": "Dubring’s rule"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "Floating heads are provided in heat exchangers to",
        "options": [
            "Increase the pressure drop",
            "Decrease the pressure drop",
            "Facilitate maintenance",
            "Avoid deformation of tubes because of thermal expansion"
        ],
        "answer": "Avoid deformation of tubes because of thermal expansion"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "What do you call the first stage of crystal formation?",
        "options": [
            "Nucleation",
            "Foaming",
            "Separation",
            "Vortexing"
        ],
        "answer": "Nucleation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "In heat exchanger design, on transfer unit implies:",
        "options": [
            "One fluid which is exchanging with another fluid of the same chemical composition",
            "The section of heat exchanger which will cause temperature drop of one degree centigrade",
            "The section of heat exchanger where heat transfer surface area has been one square meter",
            "Condition when the change in temperature of one steam is numerically equal to the average driving force"
        ],
        "answer": "Condition when the change in temperature of one steam is numerically equal"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "Dritus Boelter equation can be applied in case of fluids flowing in:",
        "options": [
            "Transition region",
            "Turbulent region",
            "Laminar region",
            "Any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Turbulent region"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "In sugar mills can just is evaporated in:",
        "options": [
            "Zigzag tube evaporators",
            "Long vertical tube evaporators",
            "Short vertical tube evaporators",
            "Horizontal tube evaporators"
        ],
        "answer": "Long vertical tube evaporators"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "A 1-2 heat exchanger refers to which of the following?",
        "options": [
            "Single pass on shell side and double pass on tube side",
            "Single pass on tube side and double pass on shell side",
            "Single liquid cools two liquids at different temperature",
            "Two tubes of cold fluid pass through one tube of hot fluid"
        ],
        "answer": "Single pass on shell side and double pass on tube side"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "A correction of LMTD is essential in case of:",
        "options": [
            "Parallel flow heat exchanger",
            "Counter current heat exchanger",
            "Cross flow heat exchanger",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Cross flow heat exchanger"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "Which of the following is used as entrainer in acetic acid – water separation?",
        "options": [
            "Methyl alcohol",
            "Phosphorus",
            "Butyl acetate",
            "Hexane"
        ],
        "answer": "Butyl acetate"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "A type of radiation consisting of singly charged particles that generate to intermediate distances.",
        "options": [
            "Nuclear radiation",
            "Alpha radiation",
            "Beta radiation",
            "Gamma radiation"
        ],
        "answer": "Beta radiation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "An electrically charged atom or radical which carries electricity through an electrolyte is called:",
        "options": [
            "Ion",
            "Isotope",
            "Molecule",
            "Hole"
        ],
        "answer": "Ion"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "The energy of a body that can be traqnsmitted in the form of heat.",
        "options": [
            "Heat energy",
            "Thermal energy",
            "Entropy",
            "Internal energy"
        ],
        "answer": "Thermal energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "In an isometric process, the heat transferred is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "Change in enthalpy",
            "change in entropy",
            "change in internal energy",
            "work nonflow"
        ],
        "answer": "change in internal energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "A substance that is able to absorb liquids or gases and is used for removing them from a given medium or region.",
        "options": [
            "Absorbent",
            "Cohesive",
            "Adsorbent",
            "Adhesive"
        ],
        "answer": "Absorbent"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "Radiant heat transfer is described by:",
        "options": [
            "Newton’s law",
            "Fourier’s law",
            "The logarithmic mean temperature",
            "Kirchhoff’s law"
        ],
        "answer": "Kirchhoff’s law"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "A reservoir that absorbs energy in the form of heat is called ______.",
        "options": [
            "Source",
            "Sink",
            "Cold reservoir",
            "Heat reservoir"
        ],
        "answer": "Sink"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "When the entire heat exchanger is selected as control volume, heat becomes _______.",
        "options": [
            "Unity",
            "zero",
            "Undefined",
            "Indeterminate"
        ],
        "answer": "zero"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "Heat is conducted in the direction of:",
        "options": [
            "Increasing temperature",
            "Decreasing temperature",
            "Increasing and decreasing temperature",
            "Constant temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "Decreasing temperature"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "The heat transfer term in the first law of thermodynamics may be due to any of the following except:",
        "options": [
            "Conduction",
            "Convection",
            "Radiation",
            "Internal heat generation (e.g., chemical reaction)"
        ],
        "answer": "Internal heat generation (e.g., chemical reaction)"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "All heat transfer processes require a medium of energy exchange except:",
        "options": [
            "Conduction",
            "Natural convection",
            "Forced convection",
            "Radiation"
        ],
        "answer": "Radiation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "Thermal conduction is described by:",
        "options": [
            "Newton’s law",
            "The logarithmic mean temperature difference",
            "The Stefan-Boltzmann law",
            "Fourier’s law"
        ],
        "answer": "Fourier’s law"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "Convection is described by which of the following laws?",
        "options": [
            "Newton’s law",
            "The logarithmic mean temperature difference",
            "The Stefan-Boltzmann law",
            "Fourier’s law"
        ],
        "answer": "Newton’s law"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "Radiation heat transfer is described by:",
        "options": [
            "Newton’s law",
            "The logarithmic mean temperature difference",
            "Fourier’s law",
            "Kirchhoff’s law"
        ],
        "answer": "Kirchhoff’s law"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "The equivalent of ratio of emissive power to absorptivity for bodies in thermal equilibrium is described by:",
        "options": [
            "Newton’s law",
            "The logarithmic mean temperature difference",
            "Fourier’s law",
            "Kirchhoff’s law"
        ],
        "answer": "Kirchhoff’s law"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "The temperature potential between temperature at the two ends of a heat exchanger are given by:",
        "options": [
            "The logarithmic mean temperature difference",
            "The Stefan-Boltzmann law",
            "Fourier’s law",
            "Kirchhoff’s law"
        ],
        "answer": "The logarithmic mean temperature difference"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "The function of a heat exchanger is to:",
        "options": [
            "Increase the water temperature entering the boiler and decrease combustion requirements",
            "Transfer heat from one fluid to another",
            "Increase the total energy content of the flow",
            "Exchange heat to increase energy to the flow"
        ],
        "answer": "Transfer heat from one fluid to another"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "The function of a super heater is to:",
        "options": [
            "Increase the water temperature entering the boiler and decrease combustion requirements",
            "Transfer heat from one fluid to another",
            "Increase the total energy content of the flow",
            "Exchange heat to increase energy to the flow"
        ],
        "answer": "Exchange heat to increase energy to the flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "What is the series of processes that eventually bring the system back to its original condition?",
        "options": [
            "reversible process",
            "irreversible process",
            "cycle",
            "isentropic process"
        ],
        "answer": "cycle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "A theoretical body which when heated to incandescence would emit a continuous light-ray spectrum.",
        "options": [
            "Black body radiation",
            "Black body",
            "Blue body",
            "White body"
        ],
        "answer": "Black body"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "Which of the following is the reason for insulating the pipes?",
        "options": [
            "They may not break under pressure",
            "There is minimum corrosion",
            "Capacity to withstand pressure",
            "Heat loss from the surface is minimized"
        ],
        "answer": "Heat loss from the surface is minimized"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "Heat transfer due to density differential",
        "options": [
            "Convection",
            "Nuclear",
            "Conduction",
            "Radiation"
        ],
        "answer": "Convection"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "The term “exposure” in radiological is used as a measure of a gamma ray or an X-ray field in the surface of an exposed object. Since this radiation produces ionization of the air surrounding the object, the exposure is obtained as",
        "options": [
            "number of ions produced per mass of air x coulombs per kg",
            "mass of air x surface area of an exposed object",
            "mass of air over surface area of an exposed object",
            "number of ions produced per mass of air + coulombs per kg"
        ],
        "answer": "number of ions produced per mass of air x coulombs per kg"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "The passing of heat energy from molecule to molecule through a substance",
        "options": [
            "conduction",
            "radiation",
            "conservation",
            "convection"
        ],
        "answer": "conduction"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "The radiant heat transfer depends on:",
        "options": [
            "Temperature",
            "Heat rays",
            "Heat flow from cold to hot",
            "Humidity"
        ],
        "answer": "Heat rays"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "What kind of heat exchanger where water is heated to a point that dissolved gases are liberated?",
        "options": [
            "Evaporator",
            "Condenser",
            "Intercooler",
            "Deaerator"
        ],
        "answer": "Deaerator"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "Past ME Board Examination Heat transfer processes which include a change of phase of a fluid are considered _________.",
        "options": [
            "Convection",
            "Thermal radiation",
            "Conduction",
            "Radiation"
        ],
        "answer": "Convection"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "A hot block is cooled by blowing cool air over its top surface. The heat that is first transferred to the air layer close to the block is by conduction. It is eventually carried away from the surface by ________.",
        "options": [
            "Convection",
            "Radiation",
            "Conduction",
            "Thermal radiation"
        ],
        "answer": "Convection"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "A body that is hot compared to its surroundings illuminates more energy than they give. The heat is transferred from one to another by energy wave motion. What is this mode of heat transfer?",
        "options": [
            "Radiation",
            "Conduction",
            "Convection",
            "Condensation"
        ],
        "answer": "Radiation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "What is the heat transfer due to density differential?",
        "options": [
            "Convection",
            "Conduction",
            "Nuclear",
            "Radiation"
        ],
        "answer": "Convection"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "What do you call the passing of heat energy from molecule to molecule through substance?",
        "options": [
            "Conduction",
            "Conservation",
            "Radiation",
            "Convection"
        ],
        "answer": "Conduction"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "The transmission of heat from one place to another by fluid circulation between the spots of different temperature is called ________.",
        "options": [
            "Convection",
            "Conservation",
            "Radiation",
            "Conduction"
        ],
        "answer": "Convection"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "Which of the following requires the greatest amount of heat per kilogram for a given increase in temperature?",
        "options": [
            "Ice",
            "Water",
            "Steam",
            "Copper"
        ],
        "answer": "Water"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "What do you call the effectiveness of a body as a thermal radiator at a given temperature?",
        "options": [
            "Absorptivity",
            "Conductivity",
            "Emissivity",
            "Reflectivity"
        ],
        "answer": "Emissivity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "The natural direction of the heat between two reservoirs is dependent on which of the following?",
        "options": [
            "Their temperature difference",
            "Their internal energy",
            "Their pressures",
            "Their states, whether solid, liquid and gas"
        ],
        "answer": "Their temperature difference"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "Why are metals good conductors of heat?",
        "options": [
            "Because they contain free electrons",
            "Because their atoms are relatively far apart",
            "Because their atoms collide infrequently",
            "Because they have reflecting surfaces"
        ],
        "answer": "Because they contain free electrons"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "In natural convection a heated portion of a fluids moves because:",
        "options": [
            "Its molecular motions become aligned",
            "Of molecular collisions within it",
            "Its density is less than that of the surrounding fluid",
            "Of currents in the surrounding fluid"
        ],
        "answer": "Its density is less than that of the surrounding fluid"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "In order to emit electromagnetic radiation, an object must be at a temperature:",
        "options": [
            "Above 0 K",
            "Above 0°C",
            "Above that of its surroundings",
            "High enough for it to glow"
        ],
        "answer": "Above 0 K"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "The rate at which an object radiates electromagnetic energy does depend on its:",
        "options": [
            "Surface area",
            "Mass",
            "Temperature",
            "Ability to absorb radiation"
        ],
        "answer": "Mass"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "Sublimation refers to:",
        "options": [
            "The vaporization of a solid without first becoming liquid",
            "The melting of a solid",
            "The vaporization of a solid",
            "The condensation of a gas into liquid"
        ],
        "answer": "The vaporization of a solid without first becoming liquid"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "In the process of freeze dying, ice goes directly into water vapor. What is the temperature at which this process can take place?",
        "options": [
            "Below the triple point of water",
            "At the triple point of water",
            "Above the triple point of water",
            "Any of the above, depending on the pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "Below the triple point of water"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "What usually happen when a vapor condenses into a liquid?",
        "options": [
            "It evolves heat",
            "It generates heat",
            "Its temperature increases",
            "It boils with temperature less than 100°C"
        ],
        "answer": "It evolves heat"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "In a cooling tower, the water is cooled mainly by:",
        "options": [
            "Condensation",
            "Convection",
            "Evaporation",
            "Conduction"
        ],
        "answer": "Evaporation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "How do you classify a body that has an emissivity factor of 0.7?",
        "options": [
            "Gray body",
            "Black body",
            "White body",
            "Theoretical body"
        ],
        "answer": "Gray body"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "At what particular condition that no more heat can that be removed from a substance and the temperature can no longer be lowered?",
        "options": [
            "Freezing point",
            "Absolute zero",
            "Critical point",
            "Ground zero"
        ],
        "answer": "Absolute zero"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "What refers to the heat transfer wherein the heat is transferred from one point to another by actual movement of substance?",
        "options": [
            "Conduction",
            "Radiation",
            "Convection",
            "Absorption"
        ],
        "answer": "Convection"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "The ratio of the radiation of actual body to the radiation of a blackbody is known as ________.",
        "options": [
            "Emittance",
            "Reflectance",
            "Absorptance",
            "Transmittance"
        ],
        "answer": "Emittance"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "Which of the following is the usual geometric view factor for a black body?",
        "options": [
            "Zero",
            "Infinity",
            "One",
            "Indeterminate"
        ],
        "answer": "One"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "What happens to the heat transferred radially across insulated pipe per unit area?",
        "options": [
            "The heat will flow at constant rate",
            "Decreases with the increase in thermal conductivity",
            "Decreases from pipe wall to insulated surface",
            "Partially increases from pipe wall to insulated surface"
        ],
        "answer": "Decreases from pipe wall to insulated surface"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "What do you call a change of phase directly from vapor to solid without passing through the liquid state?",
        "options": [
            "Sublimation",
            "Solidification",
            "Vaporization",
            "Deposition"
        ],
        "answer": "Deposition"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "Which of the following is the Stefan-Boltzmann constant?",
        "options": [
            "5.77 x 10ˉ W/m2K",
            "7.67 x 10ˉ W/m2K",
            "4.78 x 10ˉ W/m2K",
            "5.67 x 10ˉ W/m2K"
        ],
        "answer": "5.67 x 10ˉ W/m2K"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "What is the usual value of transmissivity for opaque materials?",
        "options": [
            "0",
            "Indeterminate",
            "1",
            "Infinity"
        ],
        "answer": "0"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "A body whose emissivity is less than 1 is known as a real body. What is the other term for real body?",
        "options": [
            "Gray body",
            "White body",
            "Black body",
            "Theoretical body"
        ],
        "answer": "Gray body"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "What refers to an ideal body that absorbs all of the radiant energy that intrudes on it and also emits the maximum possible energy when acting as a source?",
        "options": [
            "White body",
            "Black body",
            "Gray body",
            "Red hot body"
        ],
        "answer": "Black body"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "The thermal resistance for one dimensional steady conduction heat transfer through cylindrical wall in the radial direction is expressed in which of the following functions?",
        "options": [
            "Linear",
            "Exponential",
            "Logarithm",
            "Trigonometric"
        ],
        "answer": "Logarithm"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "The law which states that “the ratio of the emissive powers to absorptivities are equal when the two bodies are in thermal equilibrium” is known as:",
        "options": [
            "Stefan-Boltzmann law",
            "Newton’s law of convection",
            "Fourier’s law",
            "Kirchhoff’s law of radiation"
        ],
        "answer": "Kirchhoff’s law of radiation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "It refers to the ratio of the internal thermal resistance of a solid to the boundary layer thermal resistance (or external resistance of the body).",
        "options": [
            "Biot number",
            "Prandtl number",
            "Nusselt number",
            "Reynolds number"
        ],
        "answer": "Biot number"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "It refers to the ratio of the rate of heat transferred by conduction to the rate of energy stored.",
        "options": [
            "Reynolds number",
            "Fourier’s number",
            "Biot number",
            "Prandtl number"
        ],
        "answer": "Fourier’s number"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "A hot block is cooled by blowing cool air over its top surface. The heat that is first transferred to the air layer close to the block is by conduction. It is eventually carried away from the surface by:",
        "options": [
            "Conduction",
            "Radiation",
            "Thermal",
            "Convection"
        ],
        "answer": "Convection"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "It is term used to describe the energy of a body that can be transmitted in the form of heat.",
        "options": [
            "Enthalpy",
            "Thermal energy",
            "Entropy",
            "Internal energy"
        ],
        "answer": "Thermal energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "Which of the following is the equivalent heat transferred of a gas undergoing isometric process?",
        "options": [
            "Change in enthalpy",
            "Change in entropy",
            "Change in internal energy",
            "Work nonflow"
        ],
        "answer": "Change in internal energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "What do you call a substance that is able to absorb liquids or gases and is usually used for removing liquids (or gases) from a given medium or region?",
        "options": [
            "Absorbent",
            "Liquefier",
            "Adsorbent",
            "Adhesive"
        ],
        "answer": "Absorbent"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "In which direction that heat is transferred through conduction?",
        "options": [
            "Increasing temperature",
            "Decreasing temperature",
            "Increasing and decreasing temperature",
            "Constant temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "Decreasing temperature"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "Which of the following statements is based on Prevost theory of heat exchange?",
        "options": [
            "All bodies above absolute zero emit radiation",
            "The substance moves because of the decrease in its density which is caused by increase of temperature",
            "The substance moves because of the application of mechanical power such as a fan",
            "Heat transfer in most of the cases occurs in combination of conduction, convection and radiation"
        ],
        "answer": "All bodies above absolute zero emit radiation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "Which of the following is the emissivity of white body ?",
        "options": [
            "Zero",
            "0.5",
            "1",
            "0<e<1"
        ],
        "answer": "Zero"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "The mechanism of heat transfer in which there is no medium (i.e. water, air, solid concrete) required for the heat energy to travel is:",
        "options": [
            "Conduction",
            "Radiation",
            "Convection",
            "Diffusion"
        ],
        "answer": "Radiation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "The temperature potential between temperature at the two ends of a heat exchanger are given by:",
        "options": [
            "The algorithmic mean temperature difference",
            "The Stefan-Boltzmann law",
            "Fourier’s law",
            "Kirchhoff’s law"
        ],
        "answer": "The algorithmic mean temperature difference"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "Which of the following best describe function of heat exchanger?",
        "options": [
            "Increase the water temperature entering the system",
            "Transfer heat from one fluid to another",
            "Evaluate the total energy content of the flow",
            "Exchange heat to increase energy to the flow"
        ],
        "answer": "Transfer heat from one fluid to another"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 13,
        "question": "What refers to a form of energy associated with the kinetic random motion of large number of molecules?",
        "options": [
            "Heat",
            "Heat of fusion",
            "Entropy",
            "Internal energy",
            "10%",
            "30%",
            "20%",
            "5%",
            "The heat transfer coefficient will increase",
            "The heat transfer coefficient will decrease",
            "The heat transfer coefficient remains constant",
            "None of the above",
            "Forced convection",
            "Natural convection",
            "Forced conduction",
            "Thermal radiation",
            "The heat flow will increase",
            "The heat flow remains constant",
            "The heat flow will decrease",
            "The heat flow will partially increase and then will decrease",
            "Temperature gradient",
            "Thickness gradient",
            "Viscosity gradient",
            "Dielectric gradient",
            "Nusselt’s number",
            "Prandtl number",
            "Reynold’s number",
            "Dimensional measurement",
            "Thermal efficiency",
            "Thermal diffusivity",
            "Thermal conductivity",
            "Thermal radiography",
            "The heat transfer coefficient of one metals is of higher",
            "One metal is of lower temperature as compared to the other",
            "One metal is of higher temperature as compared to the other",
            "The thermal conductivity of one metal is high as compared to the other",
            "The heat transfer coefficient also increases",
            "The heat transfer coefficient will decrease",
            "The heat transfer coefficient remains constant",
            "The heat transfer coefficient partially increases the decreases",
            "Radiation",
            "Conduction",
            "Convection",
            "Condensation",
            "White body",
            "Opaque body",
            "Black body",
            "Transparent body",
            "Fire escape",
            "Fire exit",
            "Fire shield",
            "Fire wall",
            "Regenerator",
            "Economizer",
            "Condenser",
            "Reheater",
            "Conduction",
            "Convection",
            "Radiation",
            "Evaporation",
            "Cryogenics",
            "Thermo-kinetics",
            "Thermodynamics",
            "Ergonomics",
            "Temperature",
            "Pressure",
            "Internal energy",
            "Entropy",
            "The average mean temperature difference",
            "The algorithmic mean temperature difference",
            "The trigonometric mean temperature difference",
            "The exponential temperature difference",
            "Greater than one",
            "Less than one",
            "Equal to one",
            "Greater than zero but less than one",
            "Only in liquids",
            "Only in solids",
            "Only in liquids and gases",
            "In solids, liquid and gases",
            "Steam is less dense than boiling water",
            "The steam has higher specific heat",
            "Steam contains more internal energy",
            "Steam is everywhere thus it strikes greater force",
            "It absorbs heat",
            "It rejects heat",
            "Its temperature increases",
            "Its temperature decreases",
            "Mercury",
            "Gasoline",
            "Water",
            "Alcohol",
            "Above zero Celsius",
            "Above zero kelvin",
            "Above of the temperature of the surroundings",
            "High enough for it to glow",
            "White",
            "Red",
            "Orange",
            "Yellow",
            "Metals contain free electrons",
            "Metals have atoms the frequently collide one another",
            "Metals have reflecting surfaces",
            "Atoms in metals are very far to each other",
            "The thickness of the slab",
            "The area of the slab",
            "The temperature difference between two faces",
            "The specific heat of the material",
            "To transferring the heat by using moving fluids",
            "To transfer heat from hot to cold body by using a forced-draft fan",
            "To transfer heat by allowing molecules to vibrate one to another",
            "To transfer heat with or without a medium",
            "Because it contains many tiny pocket of air",
            "Styrofoam is a white object",
            "The structure of Styrofoam is very unstable and heat cannot flow",
            "Styrofoam structure is very dense",
            "It warms the surrounding",
            "The surrounding temperature decreases",
            "It neither warm nor cold the surrounding",
            "The surroundings will be dehumidified",
            "Temperature of the radiating body",
            "The emissivity of the radiation surface",
            "The area of the radiating body",
            "The thickness of the radiating body",
            "Metals",
            "Rocks",
            "Glass",
            "Asbestos",
            "Watt",
            "Btu per hour",
            "Cal/s",
            "Btu/Hp-hr",
            "Chemical composition",
            "Physical state or texture",
            "Temperature and pressure",
            "Gravitational pull",
            "1.7",
            "2.4",
            "1.3",
            "2.4",
            "Thermal conductivities of solids",
            "Thermal conductivities of gases",
            "Thermal conductivities of metals",
            "Thermal conductivities of liquids",
            "Approaches infinity",
            "Decreases except for ferrous metals",
            "Almost constant except for ferromagnetic materials",
            "Increases except for steel",
            "Gasoline",
            "Glycerin",
            "Water",
            "Alcohol",
            "Condenser",
            "Boilers",
            "Evaporators",
            "Water hammer",
            "Parallel flow",
            "Cross flow",
            "Counter flow",
            "Mixed flow",
            "The thermal conductivity will also increase",
            "The thermal conductivity decreases",
            "The thermal conductivity remains constant",
            "The thermal conductivity partially increases then decreases",
            "Thermograph",
            "Thermometer",
            "Pyrometer",
            "Potentiometer",
            "Only in gases",
            "Only in liquids",
            "Only in gases and liquids",
            "Only in gases and solids",
            "Forced convection",
            "Natural  convection",
            "Density convection",
            "Radial convection"
        ],
        "answer": "Natural  convection"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following could be used to check a leak in an ammonia system?",
        "options": [
            "Litmus paper",
            "Halide torch",
            "Sulfur stick",
            "A and C"
        ],
        "answer": "A and C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Ammonia leaks in the condenser can be detected by :",
        "options": [
            "smelling the discharge water",
            "applying litmus paper to the circulating water",
            "adding oil peppermint to the system and tracing the smell",
            "applying a soapy solution to the condenser heads and looking for bubbles"
        ],
        "answer": "applying litmus paper to the circulating water"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A sulfur stick burning in the presence of ammonia will give off a _______.",
        "options": [
            "dense yellow smoke",
            "dense red smoke",
            "dense white smoke",
            "dense green smoke"
        ],
        "answer": "dense white smoke"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "An ammonia leak will turn litmus paper ________.",
        "options": [
            "blue",
            "green",
            "red",
            "yellow"
        ],
        "answer": "blue"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "In an ammonia system the oil gauge must be kept.",
        "options": [
            "closed except when checking oil level",
            "open at all times",
            "close when machine is shut down",
            "open when machine is shut down"
        ],
        "answer": "closed except when checking oil level"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Valves and piping in an ammonia system are made of :",
        "options": [
            "brass",
            "bronze",
            "iron",
            "copper"
        ],
        "answer": "iron"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The relief valve on an ammonia machine is located :",
        "options": [
            "on the discharge pipe from the condenser",
            "on the discharge pipe from the compressor",
            "in the compressor head",
            "A and B"
        ],
        "answer": "in the compressor head"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "When purging an ammonia condenser into a bucket of water, one can tell when the air is out of ammonia starts to come through by the :",
        "options": [
            "smell of the ammonia being liberated from the water",
            "color of the water turning green",
            "color of the water turning bluish",
            "change of bubbling sound of air to the crackling sound of ammonia"
        ],
        "answer": "change of bubbling sound of air to the crackling sound of ammonia"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The crossover connection in an ammonia system can be used to _______.",
        "options": [
            "hot-gas defrost",
            "pump air out of the system",
            "add refrigerant to the system",
            "reduce the pressure on the discharge side of the condenser"
        ],
        "answer": "hot-gas defrost"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "How is an ammonia system purged so that operator will not be overcome by the fumes?",
        "options": [
            "Into a bucket of lube oil",
            "Back into the compressor",
            "Into a bucket of water",
            "Into the atmospheric line"
        ],
        "answer": "Into a bucket of water"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Thermal expansion valves are usually of the :",
        "options": [
            "diaphragm",
            "magnetic type",
            "bellows type",
            "A or C"
        ],
        "answer": "A or C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "When checking zinc plates in a condenser, one should :",
        "options": [
            "install all new plates",
            "clean the plates and renew worn out ones",
            "ground each plate to the shell",
            "paint the plates with red lead"
        ],
        "answer": "ground each plate to the shell"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The scale trap is located between the :",
        "options": [
            "compressor and oil separator",
            "expansion valve and evaporators coil",
            "king (liquid) valve and expansion valve",
            "evaporator coils and compressor"
        ],
        "answer": "king (liquid) valve and expansion valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "When the evaporator coils are located in the icebox, the system is known as :",
        "options": [
            "indirect system",
            "direct system",
            "high-pressure system",
            "low-pressure system"
        ],
        "answer": "direct system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The purge valve is located :",
        "options": [
            "on the receiver discharge",
            "in the highest part of the system",
            "in the lowest part of the system",
            "on the evaporators coils"
        ],
        "answer": "in the highest part of the system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The solenoid valve is :",
        "options": [
            "a pressure-controlled stop valve",
            "a temperature-controlled stop valve",
            "a Freon-controlled check valve",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "a temperature-controlled stop valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The thermal expansion valve is located between the :",
        "options": [
            "solenoid valve and evaporator coils",
            "charging valve and the solenoid valve",
            "receiver and the king valve",
            "king valve and the solenoid valve"
        ],
        "answer": "solenoid valve and evaporator coils"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The purpose of the scale trap is to :",
        "options": [
            "dissolved scale and dirt in the system",
            "remove insoluble gases from the refrigerant",
            "remove dirt, scale and metal chips from the refrigerant",
            "control the amount of scale going to the compressor"
        ],
        "answer": "remove dirt, scale and metal chips from the refrigerant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The oil separator (trap) is located between the :",
        "options": [
            "compressor discharge valve and the condenser",
            "receiver and the expansion valve",
            "receiver and the king valve",
            "condenser and the receiver"
        ],
        "answer": "compressor discharge valve and the condenser"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The charging connection in a refrigerating system is located :",
        "options": [
            "before the receiver",
            "between the condenser and the receiver",
            "between the receiver and the king valve",
            "between the king valve and the solenoid valve"
        ],
        "answer": "between the king valve and the solenoid valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The dehydrator is located between the",
        "options": [
            "condenser and receiver",
            "receiver and the expansion valve",
            "condenser and the king valve",
            "receiver and the king valve"
        ],
        "answer": "receiver and the expansion valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The charging valve is located between the :",
        "options": [
            "king valve and the expansion valve",
            "evaporator coils and the compressor",
            "compressor and the receiver",
            "receiver and the condenser"
        ],
        "answer": "king valve and the expansion valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The solenoid valve is located between the :",
        "options": [
            "thermal expansion valve and the evaporator",
            "scale trap and the thermal expansion valve",
            "king valve and the scale trap",
            "automatic and manual expansion valves"
        ],
        "answer": "scale trap and the thermal expansion valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A device used to keep moisture from passing through the system is called :",
        "options": [
            "humidifier",
            "dehydrator",
            "aerator",
            "trap"
        ],
        "answer": "dehydrator"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The relief valve is located on the :",
        "options": [
            "discharge side on the condenser",
            "outlet of the evaporator coils",
            "receiver tank",
            "discharge side of the compressor"
        ],
        "answer": "discharge side of the compressor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The dehydrator is used :",
        "options": [
            "to remove moisture from the system",
            "when adding refrigerant to the system",
            "to remove air from the system",
            "A and B"
        ],
        "answer": "A and B"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following is another name for the liquid valve?",
        "options": [
            "Freon valve",
            "king valve",
            "shutoff valve",
            "master valve"
        ],
        "answer": "king valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If no gasket are used in the piping joints of a Freon system, the joints must be :",
        "options": [
            "welded joints",
            "finished joints",
            "ground joints",
            "soldered joints"
        ],
        "answer": "ground joints"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A device for holding open the suction valve and drawing gas from the suction manifold and returning it to the suction line without compressing it is called _____.",
        "options": [
            "relief valve",
            "suction line by-pass",
            "cylinder unloader",
            "discharge line by-pass"
        ],
        "answer": "cylinder unloader"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The solenoid valve can be typed as a ____.",
        "options": [
            "bellows valve",
            "bimetallic valve",
            "thermal valve",
            "magnetic valve"
        ],
        "answer": "magnetic valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The bulb for the thermal expansion valve is located",
        "options": [
            "near the evaporator coil outlet",
            "in the middle of evaporator coils",
            "near the evaporator coil inlet",
            "on the bottom row of evaporator coils"
        ],
        "answer": "near the evaporator coil outlet"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The elements of a thermostat switch are usually of the ____.",
        "options": [
            "pilot-valve type",
            "bimetal type",
            "diaphragm type",
            "valve type"
        ],
        "answer": "bimetal type"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The expansion valve is located between the",
        "options": [
            "compressor and condenser",
            "evaporator and compressor",
            "receiver and evaporator",
            "condenser and receiver"
        ],
        "answer": "receiver and evaporator"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The oil separator is located between the",
        "options": [
            "condenser and dehydrator",
            "compressor and condenser",
            "evaporator and compressor",
            "solenoid valve and thermal expansion valve"
        ],
        "answer": "compressor and condenser"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Zinc rods are found in the",
        "options": [
            "salt-water side of condenser",
            "compressor crankcase",
            "evaporator coils",
            "refrigerant side of condenser"
        ],
        "answer": "salt-water side of condenser"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A double-trunk piston is used to",
        "options": [
            "prevent oil from mixing with the refrigerant",
            "absorb some of the side thrust",
            "prevent gas from getting to crankcase",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "all of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following gasket materials should be used on a Freon system?",
        "options": [
            "Asbestos",
            "Metallic",
            "Rubber",
            "A and B"
        ],
        "answer": "A and B"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Many pressure gauges on a Freon system have two dials or graduations on one gauge. The two dials represent",
        "options": [
            "suction and discharge pressure",
            "pressure and temperature",
            "liquid and gas pressure",
            "cooling water inlet and outlet temperatures"
        ],
        "answer": "pressure and temperature"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A double-pipe condenser has ________.",
        "options": [
            "two pipes for cooling water and one for refrigerant",
            "a small pipe inside a larger pipe, the cooling water passing through the small pipe and the refrigerant through the large pipe",
            "two piping system side by side, one with cooling water and one with refrigerant",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "a small pipe inside a larger pipe, the cooling water passing through the small pipe and"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "When there is a Freon leak, the halide torch will burn",
        "options": [
            "orange",
            "green",
            "blue",
            "white"
        ],
        "answer": "green"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Large leaks in a Freon system cannot always be detected with halide torch because it changes color with the slightest amount of Freon present. A large leak can be detected easier by applying _____.",
        "options": [
            "sheets of litmus paper to all joints and watch for color change",
            "a soapsuds solution, mixed with a little glycerin to hold the solution together, and watch for bubbles",
            "a thin layer of mineral oil to all joints and watch for bubbles",
            "a lighted candle at the joints and watch for leaky spots blowing candle flame"
        ],
        "answer": "a soapsuds solution, mixed with a little glycerin to hold the solution together, and"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The relief valve on a CO2 machine is located",
        "options": [
            "next to the king valve",
            "in the compressor head",
            "on the discharge pipe between the compressor and the discharge valve",
            "on the discharge pipe from the condenser"
        ],
        "answer": "on the discharge pipe between the compressor and the discharge valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The discharge pressure of the compressor should be :",
        "options": [
            "the pressure which corresponds to a temperature from 5 ̊F to 15  ̊F below that of the condenser discharge",
            "the pressure which corresponds to a temperature equal to that of the condenser discharge",
            "the pressure which corresponds to a temperature from 5 ̊F to 15  ̊F higher than the condenser discharge",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "the pressure which corresponds to a temperature from 5 ̊F to 15  ̊F higher than the"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The purpose of relief valves on the refrigerant machines is to :",
        "options": [
            "by-pass the compressor when dehydrating",
            "prevent overloading in the iceboxes",
            "prevent excessive pressure in case of stoppage on the discharge side of the system",
            "A and B"
        ],
        "answer": "prevent excessive pressure in case of stoppage on the discharge side of the system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A leaky suction valve can usually be detected by",
        "options": [
            "a higher suction pressure",
            "a fluctuating suction pressure gauge",
            "closing the suction valve having no effect on the suction pressure",
            "any f the above"
        ],
        "answer": "any f the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Too low suction pressure could be caused by",
        "options": [
            "too much oil in the system",
            "shortage of refrigerant gas",
            "dirty scale traps",
            "an y of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "an y of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What do you call a system in which the evaporator coils are located in a brine solution and the brine is pumped through the icebox?",
        "options": [
            "an indirect system",
            "a double-evaporator system",
            "a direct system",
            "a low-pressure system"
        ],
        "answer": "an indirect system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Before securing a compressor to do a maintenance work on it, be sure to",
        "options": [
            "purge the system",
            "have space parts ready",
            "pump down the system",
            "B and C"
        ],
        "answer": "B and C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Obstruction of the expansion valve is usually caused by",
        "options": [
            "scale",
            "congealed oil in the system",
            "water in the system",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "any of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Excess frost on the evaporator coils",
        "options": [
            "does not affect the system",
            "take load off compressor",
            "reduces efficiency of the plant",
            "keeps the icebox cooler"
        ],
        "answer": "reduces efficiency of the plant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Air circulation in the icebox is accomplished by the use of which of the following?",
        "options": [
            "hollow sidewalls",
            "diffuser fans",
            "louver doors",
            "air vents to deck"
        ],
        "answer": "diffuser fans"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The cooling-water side of the condenser should be opened for inspection every",
        "options": [
            "six months",
            "two years",
            "year",
            "three months"
        ],
        "answer": "three months"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Some causes of a noisy compressor are",
        "options": [
            "worn bearings, pins, etc.",
            "slugging due to flooding back of refrigerant",
            "too much oil in the crankcase",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "any of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If the thermal expansion valve becomes inoperative, the iceboxes will have to be controlled by the ____.",
        "options": [
            "king valve",
            "manual expansion valve",
            "manual solenoid valve",
            "solenoid valve"
        ],
        "answer": "manual expansion valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Sweating of the crankcase is caused by which of the following?",
        "options": [
            "too much oil in the system",
            "insufficient superheat",
            "too much superheat",
            "expansion valve hung up"
        ],
        "answer": "too much oil in the system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following is the usual cause of slugging ?",
        "options": [
            "too much refrigerant in the system",
            "too much oil in the system",
            "expansion valve not operating properly",
            "too much cooling water to condenser"
        ],
        "answer": "expansion valve not operating properly"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What operates a low-pressure cutout switch?",
        "options": [
            "bellows",
            "spring tension",
            "a magnet",
            "water pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "bellows"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following must be checked up if an automatic Freon system will not start up?",
        "options": [
            "high-pressure cutout",
            "reset mechanism",
            "low-pressure cutout",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "all of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following is the probable cause of hot suction line ?",
        "options": [
            "insufficient lubrication",
            "too much refrigerant",
            "insufficient refrigerant",
            "expansion valve closed too much"
        ],
        "answer": "insufficient refrigerant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What do you call the device that is used as a low-pressure control and high-pressure cutout on a compressor?",
        "options": [
            "pressure controller",
            "controller switch",
            "cutout",
            "cutout switch"
        ],
        "answer": "pressure controller"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If the solenoid valve closed by accident, the compressor would be stopped by which of the following?",
        "options": [
            "automatic tip",
            "low-pressure cutout switch",
            "low-water cutout switch",
            "high-pressure cutout switch"
        ],
        "answer": "low-pressure cutout switch"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The purpose of the low-pressure cutout switch is to :",
        "options": [
            "cut out the compressor at a set pressure",
            "maintain a preset suction pressure to the compressor",
            "maintain liquid refrigerant at the suction of the compressor",
            "cut compressor in and out a preset pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "cut compressor in and out a preset pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If the cooling water to the condenser suddenly fails?",
        "options": [
            "an alarm will ring to notify the engineer",
            "the compressor will shut down",
            "the expansion valve will close",
            "the solenoid valve will close"
        ],
        "answer": "the compressor will shut down"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The most likely cause of high superheat would be",
        "options": [
            "too much refrigerant",
            "expansion valve open too wide",
            "expansion valve closed too much",
            "back-pressure valve is set to high"
        ],
        "answer": "expansion valve closed too much"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What do you call the liquid reaching the compressor through the suction?",
        "options": [
            "superheating",
            "overflowing",
            "flooding back",
            "recycling"
        ],
        "answer": "flooding back"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The suction pressure switch is operated by which of the following?",
        "options": [
            "electric current",
            "pressure on a bellows",
            "a relay cutout",
            "thermocouple"
        ],
        "answer": "pressure on a bellows"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If the compressor short-cycles on the high-pressure cutout, which of the following would you check?",
        "options": [
            "check for too much refrigerant in the system",
            "if plenty og cooling water is running through but it is not picking up heat, the condenser tubes need cleaning",
            "be sure system is getting cooling water",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "all of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A Freon unit will tend to short-cycle when operating under :",
        "options": [
            "normal conditions",
            "heavy foads",
            "light loads",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "light loads"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Air is remove from the system by",
        "options": [
            "opening the purge valve",
            "increasing the amount of cooling water",
            "running the refrigerant through an aerator",
            "running the refrigerant through a deaerator"
        ],
        "answer": "opening the purge valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Short-cycling means that the machine",
        "options": [
            "run to slow",
            "stops and starts frequently",
            "run too fast",
            "ground out frequently"
        ],
        "answer": "stops and starts frequently"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The suction pressure in a Freon system should be",
        "options": [
            "the pressure which corresponds with a temperature about 20 ̊F above the temperature of the icebox",
            "the pressure which corresponds with a temperature about 20 ̊F below the temperature of the icebox",
            "the pressure which corresponds with a temperature of the icebox",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "the pressure which corresponds with a temperature about 20 ̊F below the"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If any of the electrically controlled devices in a Freon system malfunction, which of the following valve will also automatically shut off?",
        "options": [
            "king valve",
            "condenser cooling-water inlet valve",
            "expansion valve",
            "solenoid valve"
        ],
        "answer": "solenoid valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A leaky discharge valve can usually be detected by",
        "options": [
            "a drop in icebox temperature",
            "a discharge pressure lower than normal",
            "a fluctuating high-pressure gauge",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "any of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The dehydrating agent in a Freon system is usually",
        "options": [
            "sodium chloride",
            "calcium chloride",
            "activated alumina",
            "slaked lime"
        ],
        "answer": "activated alumina"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If the compressor short-cycles on the low-pressure cutout, the trouble might be :",
        "options": [
            "too much frost on the evaporator coils",
            "dirty traps and strainers",
            "lack of refrigerant",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "any of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If an electrically operated compressor failed to start the cause might be :",
        "options": [
            "a blown fuse",
            "burned out holding coils in solenoid valve",
            "an open switch",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "any of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The high-pressure side of the system is sometimes referred to as the",
        "options": [
            "hot side",
            "suction side",
            "cold side",
            "cooling side"
        ],
        "answer": "hot side"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If the compressor were to run continuously without lowering the temperature, the trouble would probably be :",
        "options": [
            "leaky discharge valves",
            "insufficient refrigerant in the system",
            "leaks in the system",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "any of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following would cause a high head pressure?",
        "options": [
            "a suction valve not open enough",
            "too much  cooling water",
            "insufficient cooling water",
            "icebox door left open"
        ],
        "answer": "insufficient cooling water"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If frost forms on the cylinders, the cause would be",
        "options": [
            "charging valve left open",
            "expansion valve not open wide enough",
            "expansion valve open too wide",
            "dehydrator not working properly"
        ],
        "answer": "expansion valve open too wide"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following would cause low head pressure?",
        "options": [
            "insufficient cooling water",
            "too much cooling water",
            "insufficient refrigerant gas",
            "B and C"
        ],
        "answer": "B and C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Too high suction pressure could be cause by",
        "options": [
            "leaky suction vlaves",
            "expansion valve bulb not working properly",
            "expansion valve open too wide",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "any of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following would cause high pressure?",
        "options": [
            "air in the condenser",
            "insufficient cooling water",
            "dirty condenser",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "any of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "an excessive high  head pressure could be caused by",
        "options": [
            "an insufficient cooling water to the condenser",
            "insufficient cooling water to the evaporator coils",
            "solenoid valve shutoff",
            "too much cooling water to the condenser"
        ],
        "answer": "an insufficient cooling water to the condenser"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following would cause high preesure?",
        "options": [
            "expansion valve open too wide",
            "dirty dehydrator",
            "king valve not open wide enough",
            "expansion valve not open wide enough"
        ],
        "answer": "expansion valve open too wide"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If a compressor runs continuously, the cause might be a",
        "options": [
            "clogged scale trap",
            "defective thermal bulb",
            "stuck high-pressure switch",
            "stuck low-pressure switch"
        ],
        "answer": "stuck low-pressure switch"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Low suction pressure is caused by",
        "options": [
            "expansion  valve causing flooding back",
            "solenoid valve not functioning properly",
            "leaky compressor suction valves",
            "air in the system"
        ],
        "answer": "solenoid valve not functioning properly"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "How is a Freon system purged?",
        "options": [
            "with a reefer pump",
            "the same as an ammonia system",
            "back to the extra supply tank",
            "the same as a CO2 system"
        ],
        "answer": "the same as a CO2 system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If the compressor discharge temperatures is higher than the receiver temperature :",
        "options": [
            "add more refrigerant to the system",
            "decrease the amount of cooling water to the condenser",
            "increase the amount of cooling water to the condenser",
            "remove some of the refrigerant from the system"
        ],
        "answer": "decrease the amount of cooling water to the condenser"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "How is a CO2 system purged",
        "options": [
            "when CO2 comes out of the purge  valve, frost will from on a piece of metal held near the outlet",
            "through the king valve",
            "pumped out with a suction pump",
            "the CO2 will come out of the purge valve in liquid form"
        ],
        "answer": "when CO2 comes out of the purge  valve, frost will from on a piece of metal held near"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If the head pressure is too high :",
        "options": [
            "the relief valve should open and let excess refrigerant pass to receiver",
            "close in on the suction valve",
            "the relief should open before the high-pressure cutout",
            "the high-pressure cutout switch should operate before the relief valve opens"
        ],
        "answer": "the high-pressure cutout switch should operate before the relief valve opens"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The system should be purged",
        "options": [
            "while starting up",
            "after the system has been shut down for a few hours",
            "while system is operating",
            "once a week"
        ],
        "answer": "after the system has been shut down for a few hours"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If the compressor had been running satisfactorily for a long period of time but suddenly the compartment temperature started to rise, the trouble might be",
        "options": [
            "a refrigerant leak has developed",
            "the expansion valve may contain frozen water",
            "the solenoid valve has jammed shut",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "any of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If the compressor had been running satisfactorily for a long period of time but the oil level was rising slowly, one should:",
        "options": [
            "check the dehydrator cartridge",
            "check to see if there is too much refrigerant in the system",
            "shut down the compressor and check the oil level with the machine stopped",
            "drain out sufficient oil to bring it down to the proper running level"
        ],
        "answer": "shut down the compressor and check the oil level with the machine stopped"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The purpose of oil trap is :",
        "options": [
            "to add oil to the compressor",
            "to remove oil from the refrigerating gas",
            "to remove oil from the charging tank",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "to remove oil from the refrigerating gas"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Too much oil in the compressor would :",
        "options": [
            "absorb too much refrigerant from the system",
            "deposit oil on the condenser tubes",
            "damage the expansion valve",
            "cause leakage through the shaft seals"
        ],
        "answer": "absorb too much refrigerant from the system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The oil level in the compressor should be checked",
        "options": [
            "just before starting the compressor",
            "after a long period of operation",
            "after an extended lay-up period",
            "while the compressor is in operation"
        ],
        "answer": "after a long period of operation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The agent used in an indirect reefer system is",
        "options": [
            "calcium chloride",
            "potassium chloride",
            "sodium chloride",
            "A or C"
        ],
        "answer": "A or C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Air can be prevented from getting into the system by",
        "options": [
            "running the refrigerant through an aerator",
            "keeping the dehydrator clean at all times",
            "keeping all glands and stuffing boxes on the high-pressure side tight",
            "keeping all glands and stuffing boxes on the low-pressure side tight"
        ],
        "answer": "keeping all glands and stuffing boxes on the low-pressure side tight"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following would not cause high suction pressure ?",
        "options": [
            "suction valve not adjusted properly",
            "expansion valve stuck open",
            "leaky suction valve",
            "insufficient refrigeration"
        ],
        "answer": "insufficient refrigeration"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Water in the refrigerant is liable to",
        "options": [
            "freeze on the expansion valve seat and cut the flow of refrigerant",
            "clog the oil trap",
            "freeze in the king (liquid) valve",
            "emulsify the oil in the compressor"
        ],
        "answer": "freeze on the expansion valve seat and cut the flow of refrigerant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The function of the expansion valve is to :",
        "options": [
            "regulate the amount of liquid refrigerant to the expansion coils",
            "change the refrigerant to a liquid",
            "shut off the flow refrigerant to the condenser",
            "change the high-pressure liquid to a low-pressure liquid"
        ],
        "answer": "regulate the amount of liquid refrigerant to the expansion coils"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "When heavy electrical currents are involved, the thermostat will be operated by a :",
        "options": [
            "pressure pipe",
            "fusetron",
            "relay",
            "small circuit breaker"
        ],
        "answer": "relay"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Before securing a compressor to do maintenance work on it, be sure to :",
        "options": [
            "have a gas mask handy",
            "make arrangements to have perishables taken care of",
            "notify the engineer",
            "A and B"
        ],
        "answer": "A and B"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "When securing a Freon system for repairs.",
        "options": [
            "pump down to 1 to 2 pounds pressure",
            "pump down to a slight vacuum",
            "pump down to 10 to 15 pounds pressure",
            "remove all refrigerant from the system"
        ],
        "answer": "pump down to 1 to 2 pounds pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "When charging Freon system, all the valves should be in their normal position except the :",
        "options": [
            "solenoid valve",
            "purge valve",
            "king valve",
            "expansion valve"
        ],
        "answer": "king valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The purpose of the receiver is to :",
        "options": [
            "cool the refrigerant gas",
            "separate the oil from the refrigerant",
            "store the refrigerant",
            "condense the refrigerant"
        ],
        "answer": "store the refrigerant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The solenoid valve controls the",
        "options": [
            "amount of refrigerant entering the evaporator coils",
            "amount of refrigerant going to the expansion valve",
            "amount of refrigerant going to the compressor",
            "pressure of the refrigerant going to the evaporator coils"
        ],
        "answer": "amount of refrigerant going to the expansion valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The purpose of the evaporator is to",
        "options": [
            "absorb latent heat of vaporization",
            "absorb latent heat of fusion",
            "transfer latent heat of vaporization",
            "transfer latent heat of fusion"
        ],
        "answer": "absorb latent heat of vaporization"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The purpose of the dehydrator is to",
        "options": [
            "add more refrigerant to the system",
            "remove oil from the refrigerant",
            "remove moisture from the crankcase oil",
            "remove moisture from the refrigerant"
        ],
        "answer": "remove moisture from the refrigerant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The principle of mechanical refrigeration is",
        "options": [
            "the conversion of a liquid to a gas",
            "the absorption of temperature under heat , pressure. Compression and expansion",
            "the compression of a liquid under temperature and expansion",
            "the absorption of heat under temperature, compression, pressure and expansion"
        ],
        "answer": "the absorption of heat under temperature, compression, pressure and expansion"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A thermostat is a",
        "options": [
            "temperature-operated switch",
            "pressure-operated switch",
            "superheat-operated switch",
            "back pressure-operated switch"
        ],
        "answer": "temperature-operated switch"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The thermal expansion valve responds to the",
        "options": [
            "amount of superheat in the vapor",
            "amount of superheat in the liquid",
            "temperature in the evaporator coils",
            "pressure in the evaporator coils"
        ],
        "answer": "amount of superheat in the vapor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The expansion valve on a Freon system controls the",
        "options": [
            "superheat of the gas leaving the compressor",
            "back pressure in the evaporator",
            "temperature of the icebox",
            "superheat of the gas leaving the evaporator"
        ],
        "answer": "superheat of the gas leaving the evaporator"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Oil is added to a Freon compressor by",
        "options": [
            "shutting down the machine and pouring in through the crankcase inspection plate opening",
            "pumping in with an electric-driven pump",
            "pumping in with a hand pump",
            "pouring through oil hole in base"
        ],
        "answer": "pumping in with a hand pump"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "When adding oil to a Freon system, one must be sure that",
        "options": [
            "the condenser is shut down",
            "all air is removed from the pump fitting",
            "there is not too high suction pressure",
            "the discharge pressure is not too high"
        ],
        "answer": "all air is removed from the pump fitting"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "To help a person who had been overexposed to ammonia gas, one would :",
        "options": [
            "apply cold compresses",
            "apply artificial respiration",
            "douse with cold water",
            "wrap in warm blankets"
        ],
        "answer": "apply artificial respiration"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Ammonia will corrode",
        "options": [
            "brass",
            "copper",
            "bronze",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "all of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A refrigerating unit of one ton capacity can remove",
        "options": [
            "100 Btu’s per min.",
            "288 Btu’s per min.",
            "200 Btu’s per min.",
            "500 Btu’s per min."
        ],
        "answer": "200 Btu’s per min."
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The refrigerant with the lowest boiling point is",
        "options": [
            "NH3",
            "F12",
            "CO2",
            "F22"
        ],
        "answer": "CO2"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A ton of refrigeration is equal to the removal of",
        "options": [
            "288,000 Btu per 24 hrs.",
            "28,800 Btu per 24 hrs.",
            "28,000 Btu per 24 hrs.",
            "280,000 Btu per 24 hrs."
        ],
        "answer": "288,000 Btu per 24 hrs."
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The boiling point of Freon-12 at atmospheric pressure is",
        "options": [
            "+22  ̊F",
            "-22  ̊F",
            "+22  ̊C",
            "-20  ̊C"
        ],
        "answer": "-22  ̊F"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "the boiling point of CO2 at atmospheric pressure is",
        "options": [
            "- 110 ̊F",
            "+ 110 ̊F",
            "+ 110 ̊C",
            "– 110  ̊C"
        ],
        "answer": "- 110 ̊F"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The boiling point of NH3 at atmospheric pressure is",
        "options": [
            "+ 28 ̊C",
            "+ 28 ̊F",
            "- 28 ̊C",
            "- 28 ̊F"
        ],
        "answer": "- 28 ̊F"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following would you apply if a person got Freon in his eyes",
        "options": [
            "clean water",
            "soapy water",
            "sodium bicarbonate",
            "sterile mineral oil"
        ],
        "answer": "sterile mineral oil"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A double-seated valve allows the valve to be",
        "options": [
            "packed only in the closed position",
            "packed in the wide open or closed position",
            "operated as a suction or discharge valve",
            "removed for replacement without shutting down"
        ],
        "answer": "packed in the wide open or closed position"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The amount of CO2 or Freon in a cylinder is measured by",
        "options": [
            "pressure",
            "weight",
            "volume",
            "psi"
        ],
        "answer": "weight"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The latent heat of fusion of ice is :",
        "options": [
            "500 Btu",
            "188 Btu",
            "144 Btu",
            "970 Btu"
        ],
        "answer": "144 Btu"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Latent heat",
        "options": [
            "can be measured with a pyrometer",
            "cannot be measured with a thermometer",
            "changes as the refrigerant cools",
            "can be measured with a thermometer"
        ],
        "answer": "cannot be measured with a thermometer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Absolute zero is",
        "options": [
            "144 ̊ below zero on the Fahrenheit scale",
            "the same as zero on the Fahrenheit scale",
            "970 ̊ below zero on the Fahrenheit scale",
            "460 ̊ below zero on the Fahrenheit scale"
        ],
        "answer": "460 ̊ below zero on the Fahrenheit scale"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A ton of refrigeration is equal to the cooling effect of",
        "options": [
            "2,000 lbs. of ice melting in 24 hrs",
            "2,000 lbs. of water being converted to ice",
            "2,000 lbs. of ice melting in 12 hrs",
            "2,240 lbs. of ice melting in 24 hrs"
        ],
        "answer": "2,000 lbs. of ice melting in 24 hrs"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following best described a Freon ?",
        "options": [
            "odorless",
            "non-poisonous",
            "colorless",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "all of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What is another name of discharge pressure?",
        "options": [
            "absolute pressure",
            "head pressure",
            "suction pressure",
            "condenser pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "head pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following is the oil used in a refrigeration system?",
        "options": [
            "vegetable oil",
            "straight mineral oil",
            "lube oil SAE 20",
            "lube oil SAE 10"
        ],
        "answer": "straight mineral oil"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "One disadvantage of CO2 system is the fact that",
        "options": [
            "it is difficult to a condense the refrigerant if the circulating water temperature is too high",
            "it takes more refrigerant to keep the iceboxes cold",
            "due to high pressure it is difficult to keep oil from mixing with the refrigerant",
            "it is difficult to condense the refrigerant  if the circulating water temperature is too low"
        ],
        "answer": "it is difficult to a condense the refrigerant if the circulating water temperature is too"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The disadvantage of a CO2 system over an ammonia system is the fact that ________.",
        "options": [
            "the pipes and fittings of a CO2 system must be of the high-pressure type",
            "the CO2 system operates at a much higher pressure",
            "the CO2 system requires a larger prime mover",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "all of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A good refrigerant should be :",
        "options": [
            "non-inflammable",
            "non-poisonous",
            "non-explosive",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "all of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What tonnage of refrigerating machine is required if the refrigerating system extracted 48,000 Btu per hour?",
        "options": [
            "2 tons",
            "5 tons",
            "4 tons",
            "3 tons"
        ],
        "answer": "4 tons"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What is the combination of a wet and dry bulb thermometer is called a",
        "options": [
            "hygrometer",
            "psychrometer",
            "hydrometer",
            "A or B"
        ],
        "answer": "A or B"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A pressure controller is usually operated by the movement of a",
        "options": [
            "bellows",
            "siphon",
            "diaphragm",
            "A or C"
        ],
        "answer": "A or C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The critical temperature of a refrigerant is :",
        "options": [
            "the temperature at which it will freeze",
            "the temperature above which it cannot be liquefied",
            "the temperature below which it cannot be liquefied",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "the temperature above which it cannot be liquefied"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If the critical temperature of a refrigerant is too close to the desired condensing temperature, the equipment must necessarily be of :",
        "options": [
            "extra heavy construction",
            "the direct expansion type",
            "light construction",
            "the indirect expansion type"
        ],
        "answer": "extra heavy construction"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A good refrigerant should have a",
        "options": [
            "high sensible heat",
            "low sensible heat",
            "high latent heat",
            "latent heat"
        ],
        "answer": "high latent heat"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following is the most common method of heat flow in refrigeration?",
        "options": [
            "conduction",
            "expulsion",
            "radiation",
            "convection"
        ],
        "answer": "convection"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "From which of the following processes where the largest quantities of heat are available ?",
        "options": [
            "vaporization",
            "melting",
            "fusion",
            "cooling"
        ],
        "answer": "vaporization"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What is the most common Freon gas used in centrifugal compressors?",
        "options": [
            "F-12",
            "F-11",
            "F-22",
            "F-21"
        ],
        "answer": "F-11"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What is the most common Freon gas used in reciprocating compressors?",
        "options": [
            "F-12",
            "F-11",
            "F-22",
            "F-21"
        ],
        "answer": "F-12"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What is the other name of hygrometer?",
        "options": [
            "hydrometer",
            "manometer",
            "psychrometer",
            "A or C"
        ],
        "answer": "psychrometer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The temperature in the meat and fish box should be approximately",
        "options": [
            "10 ̊ to 20 ̊F",
            "-10 ̊ to 0 ̊F",
            "0 ̊ to -10 ̊F",
            "-10 ̊ to 10 ̊F"
        ],
        "answer": "10 ̊ to 20 ̊F"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The temperature in the vegetable box should be approximately",
        "options": [
            "35 ̊ to 45 ̊F",
            "10 ̊ to 20 ̊F",
            "40 ̊ to 50 ̊F",
            "15 ̊ to 30 ̊F"
        ],
        "answer": "35 ̊ to 45 ̊F"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The temperature in the dairy box should be approximately",
        "options": [
            "20 ̊ to 30 ̊F",
            "0 ̊ to 10 ̊F",
            "10 ̊ to 20 ̊F",
            "30 ̊ to 40 ̊F"
        ],
        "answer": "30 ̊ to 40 ̊F"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following can be the cause of low head pressure?",
        "options": [
            "too much or too cold condensing water",
            "leaky discharge valves",
            "insufficient charge of refrigerant",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "any of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If thermostatic expansion valve did not appear to be functioning properly, the cause could be :",
        "options": [
            "foreign matter in the valve",
            "ruptured control bulb tubing",
            "moisture in the system",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "any of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following is used in measuring the density of a brine solution?",
        "options": [
            "litmus paper",
            "a chemical rest",
            "a hydrometer",
            "A or B"
        ],
        "answer": "a hydrometer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following would not be cause for a refrigerating system to short cycle on HP cutout?",
        "options": [
            "discharge valve leaking",
            "pressure cutout set incorrectly",
            "system overcharged with refrigerant",
            "insufficient cooling water"
        ],
        "answer": "discharge valve leaking"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Excessive head pressure is caused by :",
        "options": [
            "air or noncondensable gas in the system",
            "dirty condenser tubes",
            "insufficient cooling water to condenser",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "any of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The capacity of a centrifugal type compressor is controlled by which of the following?",
        "options": [
            "regulating the discharge pressure",
            "regulating the speed",
            "regulating the suction pressure",
            "B or C"
        ],
        "answer": "B or C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Where is solenoid coil installed?",
        "options": [
            "vertically above the valve",
            "horizontally above the valve",
            "vertically below the valve",
            "horizontally below the valve"
        ],
        "answer": "vertically above the valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What is the condition of the compressor when purging a refrigeration system?",
        "options": [
            "the compressor is running",
            "compressor is running but the condenser secured",
            "shut down",
            "running with the bypass open"
        ],
        "answer": "shut down"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What must be done first when opening a single packed stop valve?",
        "options": [
            "loosen the packing before opening",
            "tighten packing before opening",
            "check to see that the seal is not scored",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "loosen the packing before opening"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Excessive head pressure is caused by :",
        "options": [
            "flooded condenser tubes",
            "too much cooling water to condenser",
            "cooling water temperature too high",
            "A or C"
        ],
        "answer": "A or C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Everything is in its normal operating position when charging a system except the ____.",
        "options": [
            "compressor discharge valve",
            "purge value",
            "solenoid valve",
            "king valve"
        ],
        "answer": "king valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "How often the condenser must be cleaned?",
        "options": [
            "once a year",
            "every month",
            "when pressure goes above normal",
            "every 6 months"
        ],
        "answer": "every 6 months"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which do you think is the cause of a hot suction line of a refrigerating compressor?",
        "options": [
            "lack of refrigerant",
            "insufficient condensing cooling water",
            "excess refrigeration",
            "B or C"
        ],
        "answer": "lack of refrigerant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following vital components of the refrigeration system where both temperature and pressure are increased?",
        "options": [
            "compressor",
            "condenser",
            "evaporator",
            "A or C"
        ],
        "answer": "evaporator"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The refrigerant temperature is at its maximum just before it enters the ________.",
        "options": [
            "expansion valve",
            "compressor",
            "condenser",
            "evaporator"
        ],
        "answer": "condenser"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The greatest decrease in refrigerant temperature occurs in the _____.",
        "options": [
            "evaporator",
            "compressor",
            "condenser",
            "A or C"
        ],
        "answer": "evaporator"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What do you call the storage tank for liquid refrigerant ?",
        "options": [
            "receiver tank",
            "charging tank",
            "purging",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "receiver tank"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A precooler is sometimes installed between the ______.",
        "options": [
            "compressor and condenser",
            "condenser and expansion valve",
            "expansion valve and evaporator",
            "evaporator and compressor"
        ],
        "answer": "condenser and expansion valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The solenoid valve controls which of the following?",
        "options": [
            "pressure in the evaporator coils",
            "amount of refrigerant entering the evaporator",
            "flow of refrigerant to the expansion valve",
            "amount of circulating water to the condenser"
        ],
        "answer": "flow of refrigerant to the expansion valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Closing the solenoid valve will stop the compressor through the _______.",
        "options": [
            "low water-pressure cutout switch",
            "bypass relief valve",
            "low-pressure cutout switch",
            "high-pressure cutout switch"
        ],
        "answer": "low-pressure cutout switch"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What are the four basic methods of determining whether the proper amount of refrigerant is being added to the system?",
        "options": [
            "bull’s-eye, weight, pressure and frost line",
            "temperature, weight, pressure and frost line",
            "bull’’s-eye, wight, pressure and dip stick",
            "bull’s-eye, weight, litmus test and frost line"
        ],
        "answer": "bull’s-eye, weight, pressure and frost line"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What is the cause of liquid slugging ?",
        "options": [
            "a liquid in the compressor clearance space",
            "excessive liquid refrigerant in the receiver",
            "the presence of liquid in the condenser causing excessive noise",
            "the pounding of liquid refrigerant in the suction line at a point of restriction"
        ],
        "answer": "a liquid in the compressor clearance space"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "All refrigerator compressor valves are opened and closed by ______.",
        "options": [
            "a cam shaft",
            "springs",
            "manual",
            "B or C"
        ],
        "answer": "springs"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following is also known as the hidden heat in refrigeration work?",
        "options": [
            "sensible heat",
            "heat intensity",
            "latent heat",
            "A or C"
        ],
        "answer": "latent heat"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A bull’s eye in an full liquid line will appear _____.",
        "options": [
            "cloudy",
            "clear",
            "latent",
            "A or C"
        ],
        "answer": "clear"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A compressor capacity reduction device reduces compressor capacity ______.",
        "options": [
            "by reducing the compressor speed",
            "by bypassing hot gas",
            "as the refrigerant load dictates",
            "by reducing compressor horsepower proportionately"
        ],
        "answer": "as the refrigerant load dictates"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If a Freon-12 compressor trip out on “cut-out,” the solenoid valve closes by which of the following",
        "options": [
            "an electrical release",
            "temperature and spring control",
            "pressure and bellows control",
            "bellows control"
        ],
        "answer": "an electrical release"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The thickness of the head gasket is important because it may cause _________.",
        "options": [
            "re-expansion",
            "decreased efficiency due to increased clearance",
            "the piston to stroke the head",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "all of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If the expansion valve capillary tube is pinched, which of the following must be replaced?",
        "options": [
            "tube",
            "diaphragm",
            "bulb",
            "all of the above",
            "be made of copper",
            "have no bends in it",
            "contain a strainer-dryer",
            "be above the level of the compressor"
        ],
        "answer": "contain a strainer-dryer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following must be considered when adding or removing oil from a refrigerator unit?",
        "options": [
            "use new oil",
            "do not overcharge",
            "watch crankcase pressure",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "all of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Where is the excess refrigerant removed?",
        "options": [
            "suction side of the side",
            "discharge side of the system",
            "bypass",
            "charging side of the system"
        ],
        "answer": "charging side of the system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A double trunk piston is used to _______.",
        "options": [
            "absorb side thrust",
            "seal off gas from crankcase",
            "prevent oil from mixing with gas",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "all of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "How do you call the process of changing a solid to a liquid?",
        "options": [
            "evaporation",
            "vaporization",
            "fusion",
            "condensation"
        ],
        "answer": "fusion"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If there is too much lube oil in the system, what must be done?",
        "options": [
            "remove same at once",
            "wait until  overhaul to remove",
            "wait until next recharging to remove",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "remove same at once"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The temperature bulb of the thermo-expansion valve is attached to which of the following?",
        "options": [
            "icebox coil",
            "evaporator coil outlet",
            "evaporator coil inlet",
            "wall of the icebox"
        ],
        "answer": "evaporator coil outlet"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What is the use of the suction pressure regulating valve?",
        "options": [
            "cuts in the compressor",
            "maintains the back pressure in the evaporator coils",
            "cuts out the compressor",
            "controls the expansion valve",
            "remove one ton of heat from the reefer box",
            "melt one ton of ice in 24 hrs",
            "make one ton of ice in 24 hrs",
            "remove the heat required to melt one ton in 24 hrs"
        ],
        "answer": "remove the heat required to melt one ton in 24 hrs"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The temperature bulb of the solenoid valve is attached to the _______.",
        "options": [
            "icebox coil",
            "wall of the icebox",
            "evaporator coil inlet",
            "evaporator coil outlet"
        ],
        "answer": "wall of the icebox"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What usually happens if the specific gravity of the brine is too low?",
        "options": [
            "the brine will freeze",
            "solids will deposits",
            "it will be more heat-absorbing",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "the brine will freeze"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The cooling water regulator is automatically actuated by which of the following?",
        "options": [
            "the discharge pressure of the refrigerant",
            "the temperature of the refrigerant",
            "an electric relay",
            "a thermo relay"
        ],
        "answer": "the discharge pressure of the refrigerant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What will happen to the capacity if the superheat is increased on the suction side?",
        "options": [
            "increases",
            "decreases",
            "remains the same",
            "will double"
        ],
        "answer": "decreases"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which do you think is very important in adjusting compressor “V” belts?",
        "options": [
            "allow about 1⁄2 slack",
            "make it as tight as possible",
            "make belt just tight enough to turn pulley",
            "keep belts parallel"
        ],
        "answer": "allow about 1⁄2 slack"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following is important is important for evaporator coils?",
        "options": [
            "it must be placed in the top of the compartment",
            "it must be secured to the sides",
            "it should have air completely surrounding them",
            "it must placed in front of circulating"
        ],
        "answer": "it should have air completely surrounding them"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If there were a 15 ̊F to 20 ̊F temperature differential between the temperature corresponding to the pressure at the compressor discharge and the temperature at the condenser outlet, it would probably indicate the need for ______.",
        "options": [
            "more refrigerant",
            "purging the system",
            "more circulating water",
            "less circulating"
        ],
        "answer": "purging the system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following is the most appropriate definition of the latent heat ?",
        "options": [
            "heat removed melt ice",
            "heat removed to change temperature of a substance",
            "head added to change temperature of a substance",
            "heat added to change the state of a substance"
        ],
        "answer": "heat added to change the state of a substance"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If the compressor  discharge becomes frosted, the probable cause would be _________.",
        "options": [
            "refrigerant flooding back",
            "expansion valve improperly set",
            "too much cooling water",
            "insufficient cooling water"
        ],
        "answer": "refrigerant flooding back"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The low-pressure control switch :",
        "options": [
            "is a safety device",
            "actuates the cooling water",
            "cuts out the compressor to maintain proper flow",
            "regulates the king valve"
        ],
        "answer": "cuts out the compressor to maintain proper flow"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following is an indications of faulty Freon compressor valves?",
        "options": [
            "compressor runs continously",
            "low head pressure – high suction pressure",
            "gradual or sudden decrease in capacity",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "any of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What is the probable cause if a compressor runs continuously?",
        "options": [
            "a clogged condenser",
            "insufficient refrigerant",
            "faulty cooling water valve",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "any of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "To test a thermostat valve, immerse the bulb in :",
        "options": [
            "crushed ice",
            "hot water",
            "oil",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "crushed ice"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If a compartment requires the removal of 36,000 Btu per hour, how much is the necessary compressor capacity?",
        "options": [
            "6 tons",
            "3 tons",
            "2 tons",
            "1 tons"
        ],
        "answer": "3 tons"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following must be done to eliminate frost on the discharge pipe of the compressor?",
        "options": [
            "open the expansion valve",
            "regulate water to the condenser",
            "crack bypass valve",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "none of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The following are standard characteristic of Freon – 11 exept :",
        "options": [
            "non-toxic",
            "separates from water",
            "boiling point over 200 ̊F",
            "very volatile"
        ],
        "answer": "boiling point over 200 ̊F"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following type valves are not found on a Freon – 12 system?",
        "options": [
            "bellows",
            "duplex",
            "diaphragm",
            "singled packed"
        ],
        "answer": "duplex"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "How much will be removed by one-ton refrigeration unit?",
        "options": [
            "200 Btu per min.",
            "144 Btu per min.",
            "400 Btu per min.",
            "2000 Btu per min."
        ],
        "answer": "200 Btu per min."
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following is the primary purpose of the evaporator?",
        "options": [
            "transmit latent heat of fusion",
            "transmit latent heat of evaporation",
            "absorb latent heat of fusion",
            "absorb latent heat of evaporation"
        ],
        "answer": "absorb latent heat of evaporation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "An automatically controlled Freon-12 compressor will start when the ______.",
        "options": [
            "expansion valve opens",
            "solenoid valve opens",
            "expansion valve closes",
            "solenoid valve closes"
        ],
        "answer": "solenoid valve opens"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A single trunk piston-type compressor is undesirable for a Freon unit because the :",
        "options": [
            "lubricant mixes with the refrigerant",
            "refrigerant reduces the crankcase pressure",
            "lubricant temperature becomes excessive",
            "refrigerant becomes superheated"
        ],
        "answer": "lubricant mixes with the refrigerant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Calcium chloride is sometimes used in refrigeration system as a :",
        "options": [
            "refrigerant",
            "lubricant",
            "primary coolant",
            "secondary coolant"
        ],
        "answer": "secondary coolant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "When the outlet temperature of the evaporator exceeds the inlet temperature the condition is called _____.",
        "options": [
            "boiling",
            "superheating",
            "melting",
            "freezing"
        ],
        "answer": "superheating"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following refrigerant would give the most trouble when operating with warm circulating water?",
        "options": [
            "Freon-12",
            "CO2",
            "Ammonia",
            "Ethyl chloride"
        ],
        "answer": "CO2"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "As Freon leaves the expansion valve :",
        "options": [
            "pressure increases – volume increases",
            "pressure decreases – volume increases",
            "pressure decreases – volume decreases",
            "pressure increase – volume decreases"
        ],
        "answer": "pressure decreases – volume increases"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The suction pressure switch is actuated by :",
        "options": [
            "pressure on a bellows",
            "temperature on a bellows",
            "a thermo-pressure regulator",
            "a thermostatic temperature device"
        ],
        "answer": "temperature on a bellows"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A thermometer senses which of the following?",
        "options": [
            "latent heat",
            "sensible heat",
            "heat of fusion",
            "specific heat"
        ],
        "answer": "sensible heat"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "File pounds of water heated to raise the temperature 2 ̊F requires how many Btu?",
        "options": [
            "20 Btu",
            "5 Btu",
            "2 Btu",
            "10 Btu"
        ],
        "answer": "10 Btu"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Superheat is heat added ______.",
        "options": [
            "in changing liquid to vapor",
            "after all liquid has been changed to vapor",
            "to increase pressure",
            "to increase temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "after all liquid has been changed to vapor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The expansion valve does not seem to be operating properly. There is high superheat. Test by listening to the sound of Freon flooding through the tubes and _________.",
        "options": [
            "warm bulb with hand",
            "place bulb in cold water",
            "place bulb in hot water",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "warm bulb with hand"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What do you call a material in a dryer?",
        "options": [
            "drain",
            "dryer",
            "desiccant",
            "A or C"
        ],
        "answer": "desiccant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What is the main function of a receiver?",
        "options": [
            "separate the oil from the refrigerant",
            "cool the hot gases",
            "store the refrigerant",
            "condense the refrigerant"
        ],
        "answer": "store the refrigerant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "During the re-expansion portion of the refrigeration compressor cycle",
        "options": [
            "the suction valve is open",
            "the suction valve is closed",
            "the discharged valve is closed",
            "B and C"
        ],
        "answer": "B and C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Absolute zero on the Fahrenheit scale is equal to :",
        "options": [
            "-273 ̊",
            "-460 ̊",
            "0 ̊",
            "-100 ̊"
        ],
        "answer": "-460 ̊"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A quick method of detecting a leaky condenser on a Freon system would be to _____.",
        "options": [
            "compare temperatures and pressures",
            "test circulating water with proper chemicals",
            "open vent on head and test with halide torch",
            "use soapsuds on condenser outlet fittings"
        ],
        "answer": "open vent on head and test with halide torch"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following is not a characteristic of Freon-12?",
        "options": [
            "corrosive",
            "non-flammable",
            "odorless",
            "boiling point -21 ̊F"
        ],
        "answer": "corrosive"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "In a discharge line between the compressor and the condenser one would find :",
        "options": [
            "high pressure , high temperature gas",
            "high pressure , low temperature liquid",
            "high temperature , high pressure liquid",
            "high pressure , low temperature gas"
        ],
        "answer": "high pressure , high temperature gas"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "For a low speed compressor the belt drive is preferred to the direct drive because it :",
        "options": [
            "eliminates the use of mineral lubricating oils",
            "permits the use of a smaller high speed motor",
            "absorbs torsional vibration",
            "reduces the number automatic controls"
        ],
        "answer": "permits the use of a smaller high speed motor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Refrigerant leakage from the compressor crankcase is prevented by",
        "options": [
            "using skirt type pistons",
            "maintaining a vacuum in the crankcase",
            "using shaft seals",
            "using lantern rings"
        ],
        "answer": "using shaft seals"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The heat used to change a liquid to a gas or vapor is called latent heat of",
        "options": [
            "absorption",
            "vaporization",
            "fusion",
            "liquid"
        ],
        "answer": "vaporization"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What is the compression ration a refrigerator compressor?",
        "options": [
            "the ratio of the absolute suction pressure to the absolute discharge pressure",
            "the ratio of the absolute discharge pressure to the absolute suction pressure",
            "the ratio of the excessive liquid refrigerant in the receiver to that in the system",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "the ratio of the absolute discharge pressure to the absolute suction pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The thermostatic expansion valve is designed to maintain a constant ________.",
        "options": [
            "superheat",
            "flow",
            "pressure",
            "temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "superheat"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A refrigerant gives up heat when it",
        "options": [
            "vaporizes",
            "evaporates",
            "condenses",
            "boils"
        ],
        "answer": "condenses"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The cooling component of a refrigeration cycle is called _____.",
        "options": [
            "a receiver",
            "an evaporator",
            "a condenser",
            "a desiccant"
        ],
        "answer": "an evaporator"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "When ordering an expansion valve which of the following information is necessary ?",
        "options": [
            "size and pressure",
            "size, tonnage, temperature and pressure",
            "pressure and temperature",
            "size and tonnage"
        ],
        "answer": "size, tonnage, temperature and pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A hot crankcase and cylinder head accompanied by a low suction pressure would be caused by",
        "options": [
            "excess refrigerant",
            "insufficient refrigerant",
            "air in the system",
            "stuck discharge valve"
        ],
        "answer": "insufficient refrigerant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following characteristic that is not desirable in a refrigerant?",
        "options": [
            "low latent heat of fusion",
            "high latent heat of vaporization",
            "low latent heat of vaporization",
            "A and C"
        ],
        "answer": "low latent heat of vaporization"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The principle of the centrifugal system is based on which of the following?",
        "options": [
            "kinetic energy",
            "potential energy",
            "Lenz’s law",
            "Boyle’s law"
        ],
        "answer": "kinetic energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The temperature in the vegetable box should be approximately",
        "options": [
            "-5 ̊F",
            "20 ̊F",
            "38 ̊F",
            "10 ̊F"
        ],
        "answer": "38 ̊F"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The compressor will run continuously if there is",
        "options": [
            "insufficient refrigerant",
            "air in the system",
            "too heavy a load",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "any of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A direct refrigeration system is one which :",
        "options": [
            "ice is used for cooling",
            "a secondary coolant is pumped through the evaporator coils",
            "the refrigerant passes through coils in the evaporator",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "the refrigerant passes through coils in the evaporator"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A “ CARRENE “ is a type of :",
        "options": [
            "refrigerant oil",
            "refrigerant",
            "scale cleaner",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "refrigerant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What is the first step that must be done when securing a system?",
        "options": [
            "open bypass valve",
            "close receiver ( king ) valve",
            "open solenoid valve",
            "cut out compressor on high pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "close receiver ( king ) valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "When securing a Freon-12 system for repairs",
        "options": [
            "open the line at 1 to 2 pounds pressure",
            "open the line at 5 to 10 pounds pressure",
            "pump down to a slight vacuum",
            "pump down to 10” vacuum"
        ],
        "answer": "open the line at 1 to 2 pounds pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The most common reason for small usage of CO2 system is :",
        "options": [
            "it is too dangerous",
            "its upkeep is too high",
            "the machinery is too heavy",
            "it is too costly"
        ],
        "answer": "the machinery is too heavy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "To increase heat transfer in the evaporator",
        "options": [
            "increase suction pressure",
            "increase air circulation",
            "defrost coils",
            "B and C"
        ],
        "answer": "B and C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "When the compressor is operated in short spurts after a lay-up or overhaul the purpose is to :",
        "options": [
            "allow refrigerant time to circulate",
            "determine actual compressor oil level",
            "effect gradual cooling",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "none of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following types of valve are not used for suction or discharge ?",
        "options": [
            "gate",
            "diaphragm",
            "metallic",
            "ring"
        ],
        "answer": "gate"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What usually happened if brine has a high specific gravity?",
        "options": [
            "it will freeze",
            "it will crystallize",
            "nothing will happen",
            "it will sodify"
        ],
        "answer": "it will crystallize"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "When does the refrigerant gives-up heat ?",
        "options": [
            "when it evaporates",
            "when it condenses",
            "when it vaporizes",
            "when it boils"
        ],
        "answer": "when it condenses"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The thermostatic expansion valve is designed to maintain constant _______.",
        "options": [
            "pressure",
            "flow",
            "temperature",
            "superheat"
        ],
        "answer": "superheat"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A reactor plate is essential to the operation of a ________.",
        "options": [
            "thermostatic valve",
            "halide torch",
            "solenoid bulb",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "halide torch"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The greatest decrease in the temperature of the refrigerant is at the ______.",
        "options": [
            "condenser",
            "expansion valve",
            "evaporator",
            "receiver"
        ],
        "answer": "expansion valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The temperature of the refrigerant is highest just before it enters the :",
        "options": [
            "receiver",
            "evaporator",
            "condenser",
            "king valve"
        ],
        "answer": "condenser"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A hot suction line could be caused by :",
        "options": [
            "insufficient refrigerant",
            "excess refrigerant",
            "excess cooling water",
            "insufficient cooling water"
        ],
        "answer": "insufficient refrigerant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following devices will prevent the relief valve from opening in the event of excessive pressure?",
        "options": [
            "water failure switch",
            "high-pressure cutout switch",
            "low-pressure cutout switch",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "high-pressure cutout switch"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following would cause the suction switch to remain open?",
        "options": [
            "insufficient spring tension",
            "too much spring tension",
            "bellows broken or jammed",
            "A or B"
        ],
        "answer": "bellows broken or jammed"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following would not cause high head pressure?",
        "options": [
            "air in system",
            "overcharge of refrigerant",
            "circulating water too warm",
            "liquid freezing back"
        ],
        "answer": "liquid freezing back"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A cold diffuser is a :",
        "options": [
            "type of condenser",
            "special valve used as a bypass",
            "type of evaporator",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "type of evaporator"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which do you think is the effect of subcooling ?",
        "options": [
            "it causes flooding back to the compressor",
            "it reduces the horsepower per ton of refrigeration",
            "it increases the compression ratio",
            "it increases the horsepower per ton of refrigeration"
        ],
        "answer": "it reduces the horsepower per ton of refrigeration"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Subcooling is to :",
        "options": [
            "cool the evaporator below its normal temperature",
            "cool the liquid before it enters the evaporator",
            "cool a liquid at constant pressure to a temperature lower than its condensing temperature",
            "cool the refrigerant gas before it enters the receiver"
        ],
        "answer": "cool a liquid at constant pressure to a temperature lower than its condensing"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "When figuring compression ratio, the ratio will increase with a ______.",
        "options": [
            "lower suction pressure",
            "higher suction pressure",
            "higher discharge pressure",
            "A and C"
        ],
        "answer": "A and C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Copper tubing is used in Freon system because :",
        "options": [
            "it has less internal resistance",
            "it is cheaper",
            "it is easier to check leaks",
            "iron corrodes",
            "an electric relay",
            "pressure of the refrigerant",
            "temperature of the refrigerant",
            "none if the above"
        ],
        "answer": "pressure of the refrigerant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If there is a 20 ̊F temperature drop between the temperature corresponding to the pressure at the compressor discharge and the condenser outlet, one should :",
        "options": [
            "decrease the amount of circulating water",
            "increase the amount of circulating water",
            "purge the system",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "purge the system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If refrigeration controls were constructed with little or no differential, the :",
        "options": [
            "compressor would short cycle",
            "icebox would get too cold",
            "icebox would get too warm",
            "refrigerant would be subcooled"
        ],
        "answer": "compressor would short cycle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What is the use of back pressure regulating valve?",
        "options": [
            "controls the evaporator temperature by throttling the flow of liquid refrigerant",
            "maintains a fixed pressure in the evaporator coils",
            "controls the flow of circulating water in the condenser tubes",
            "controls the temperature in the evaporator"
        ],
        "answer": "maintains a fixed pressure in the evaporator coils"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If the thermal bulb becomes loose on the evaporator coils, it will cause _______.",
        "options": [
            "an electrical short",
            "flooding back of the refrigerant",
            "improper operation of expansion valve",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "improper operation of expansion valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "External frost on inlet of expansion valve indicates :",
        "options": [
            "expansion valve plugged or dirty",
            "head pressure too high",
            "refrigerating compartment too cold",
            "air in system"
        ],
        "answer": "expansion valve plugged or dirty"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Subcooling the refrigerant results in :",
        "options": [
            "less circulating water needed",
            "effect of refrigerant increased",
            "liquid less likely to vaporize",
            "B and C"
        ],
        "answer": "B and C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following is the reason when the crankcase is cooler than the suction line?",
        "options": [
            "too much refrigerant",
            "insufficient refrigerant",
            "expansion valve open too wide",
            "suction valve leaking"
        ],
        "answer": "too much refrigerant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If the outlet of the thermostatic valve is warmer than the inlet, it indicates",
        "options": [
            "flooding back",
            "thermostatic valve working properly",
            "thermostatic valve not working properly",
            "solenoid valve not working properly"
        ],
        "answer": "thermostatic valve not working properly"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "High temperature of cylinder heads and crankcase is caused by :",
        "options": [
            "insufficient refrigerant",
            "too much refrigerant",
            "high head pressure",
            "noncondensable gases"
        ],
        "answer": "insufficient refrigerant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Frost on the high-pressure side of a thermostatic expansion valve would probably be caused by",
        "options": [
            "high head pressure",
            "dirty expansion valve",
            "refrigerator box too cold",
            "loss of circulating water to condenser"
        ],
        "answer": "dirty expansion valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A Freon-12 gage shows pressure and _____.",
        "options": [
            "superheat temperature",
            "saturation temperature",
            "back pressure",
            "vacuum"
        ],
        "answer": "saturation temperature"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Moisture in a system will cause a :",
        "options": [
            "faulty expansion valve",
            "high suction pressure",
            "high suction temperature",
            "low discharge temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "faulty expansion valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following is not essential to a centrifugal-type compressor system?",
        "options": [
            "evaporator",
            "distiller",
            "condenser",
            "expansion valve"
        ],
        "answer": "distiller"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A scale trap in a Freon system will be found on the :",
        "options": [
            "receiver",
            "discharge side",
            "suction side",
            "condenser"
        ],
        "answer": "suction side"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following would cause expansion valve failure?",
        "options": [
            "dirt in the valve",
            "moisture in the system",
            "bulb in icebox ruptured",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "any of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Two compressor should not be run in parallel because :",
        "options": [
            "there is a possibility of losing oil",
            "it will give over-capacity",
            "it is not efficient",
            "A or B"
        ],
        "answer": "there is a possibility of losing oil"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The process that takes place in the evaporator is called",
        "options": [
            "transfer of the latent heat of vaporization",
            "absorption of the latent heat of vaporization",
            "absorption of the latent heat of fusion",
            "transfer of the latent heat of fusion"
        ],
        "answer": "absorption of the latent heat of vaporization"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What is the use of the low-water cutout switch ?",
        "options": [
            "recirculates the cooling water when there is too much refrigerant in the condenser",
            "stops the compressor when there is no refrigerant running to the evaporator",
            "stops the flow of refrigerant when the condenser temperature is too low",
            "stops the compressor when there is insufficient cooling water"
        ],
        "answer": "stops the compressor when there is insufficient cooling water"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The high-pressure cutout switch :",
        "options": [
            "stops the flow of refrigerant when condenser pressure is too high",
            "recirculates the refrigerant through the compressor under emergency conditions",
            "stops flow of water to condenser when there is no refrigerant passing through",
            "stops compressor when head pressure is too high"
        ],
        "answer": "stops compressor when head pressure is too high"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Zinc rods are found in the :",
        "options": [
            "gas side of the condenser",
            "salt water side of the compressor",
            "evaporator  area",
            "compressor crankcase"
        ],
        "answer": "salt water side of the compressor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following is not essential to a compression refrigeration system?",
        "options": [
            "a receiver",
            "a condenser",
            "an evaporator",
            "a dehydrator"
        ],
        "answer": "a receiver"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What is the effect if the refrigerant is removes from the system too fast?",
        "options": [
            "it may flood the evaporator",
            "it may freeze-up the condenser",
            "it will lower the icebox temperature",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "it may freeze-up the condenser"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Closing the solenoid valve stops the compressor through the :",
        "options": [
            "high – pressure cutout switch",
            "low water – pressure cutout switch",
            "low – pressure cutout switch",
            "high water – pressure cutout switch"
        ],
        "answer": "low – pressure cutout switch"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A precooler, if used, is located between the :",
        "options": [
            "expansion valve and evaporator",
            "compressor and condenser",
            "evaporator and compressor",
            "condenser and expansion valve"
        ],
        "answer": "condenser and expansion valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "When the outlet temperature at the evaporator exceeds the inlet temperature, the condition is known as :",
        "options": [
            "superheating",
            "desuperheating",
            "dehydrating",
            "saturating"
        ],
        "answer": "superheating"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The purpose of providing hot-gas defrosting facilities :",
        "options": [
            "defrosting without raising compartment temperature above 32 ̊F",
            "thawing frozen coils",
            "defrosting automatically",
            "B or C"
        ],
        "answer": "defrosting without raising compartment temperature above 32 ̊F"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The suction control switch on the compressor is a",
        "options": [
            "thermal element",
            "thermostat",
            "pressure element",
            "bellows"
        ],
        "answer": "pressure element"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "With one machine serving several compartment, when one compartment reaches the desired temperature the temperature in that compartment is maintained by :",
        "options": [
            "the expansion valve",
            "the solenoid valve",
            "the back-pressure valve",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "the solenoid valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The back-pressure regulating valve :",
        "options": [
            "controls the water flow through the condenser",
            "stops the flow of liquid refrigerant when temperature drops in evaporator",
            "maintains a fixed pressure in the evaporator coils",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "maintains a fixed pressure in the evaporator coils"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Falty F-12 compressor valve will be indicated by :",
        "options": [
            "low head pressure-high suction pressure",
            "compressor running continuously",
            "gradual or sudden decrease in capacity",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "all of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "How were tubing joints done ?",
        "options": [
            "brazed",
            "bypassed",
            "screwed",
            "silver soldered"
        ],
        "answer": "silver soldered"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "When starting a refrigerating unit, be sure the water side of the condenser is :",
        "options": [
            "secured",
            "bypassed",
            "vented",
            "B and C"
        ],
        "answer": "vented"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The water regulating valve is operated by the",
        "options": [
            "compressor discharge pressure",
            "compressor discharge temperature",
            "compressor suction pressure",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "none of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "High superheat of the vapour in the system would cause ______.",
        "options": [
            "An increase in capacity",
            "A more efficient unit",
            "A decrease in capacity",
            "A and B"
        ],
        "answer": "A decrease in capacity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The solenoid valve is actuated by which of the following?",
        "options": [
            "A bellows",
            "A magnet",
            "A spring",
            "Any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "A magnet"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following stops the compressor before the relief valve opens?",
        "options": [
            "Low water-pressure cutout",
            "High-pressure cutout",
            "Low oil-pressure cutout",
            "Low-pressure cutout"
        ],
        "answer": "High-pressure cutout"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What is the effect if the thermal bulb is loose on the evaporator coils?",
        "options": [
            "Improper operation of expansion valve",
            "Flooding back of refrigerant",
            "Vibration causing leaks",
            "Improper operation of solenoid valve"
        ],
        "answer": "Improper operation of expansion valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If the superheat on the suction side of the compressor is increased, what happen to the tonnage capacity of the unit?",
        "options": [
            "Increases",
            "Decreases",
            "No change",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Decreases"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What do you usually do to correct slugging and flooding back?",
        "options": [
            "Change the discharge pressure",
            "Clean the traps",
            "Remove some refrigerant",
            "Check the expansion valve"
        ],
        "answer": "Check the expansion valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "In a Freon-11 system there is no",
        "options": [
            "Receiver",
            "Distiller",
            "Condenser",
            "Evaporator"
        ],
        "answer": "Distiller"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The suction pressure control valve is actuated by which of the following?",
        "options": [
            "Thermostat",
            "Bellows",
            "Thermal element",
            "Pressure diaphragm"
        ],
        "answer": "Pressure diaphragm"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following would cause the crankcase and head to get hot with low suction pressure?",
        "options": [
            "Excess refrigeration",
            "Air in system",
            "Insufficient refrigeration",
            "Insufficient cooling water"
        ],
        "answer": "Insufficient refrigeration"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following is the function of a suction pressure regulating valve?",
        "options": [
            "Cuts out the compressor",
            "Controls the expansion valve",
            "Cuts in the compressor",
            "Maintains proper back pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "Maintains proper back pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following is the cause if the outlet of a thermostatic valve is warmer than the inlet side?",
        "options": [
            "Valve is working properly",
            "Valve is not working properly",
            "Solenoid valve is not working properly",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Valve is not working properly"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "How is a thermostatic valve tested?",
        "options": [
            "Immersing its bulb in warm water",
            "Immersing its bulb in ice water",
            "Holding its bulb in one’s hand",
            "Shorting out the cutout switch"
        ],
        "answer": "Immersing its bulb in ice water"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following will cause an automatically controlled F-12 compressor to start?",
        "options": [
            "Closing of the expansion valve",
            "Opening of the expansion valve",
            "Closing of the solenoid valve",
            "Opening of the solenoid valve"
        ],
        "answer": "Opening of the solenoid valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Where is the solenoid coil installed?",
        "options": [
            "Horizontally over the valve",
            "Vertically over the valve",
            "Vertically below the valve",
            "Horizontally below the valve"
        ],
        "answer": "Vertically over the valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The refrigerating effect of a refrigerant is:",
        "options": [
            "Quantity of heat that 1 pound of refrigerant absorbs while flowing through the evaporator under given condition",
            "Amount of heat it can remove in a given time",
            "Quantity of heat that 1 pound of refrigerant absorbs",
            "A or B"
        ],
        "answer": "Quantity of heat that 1 pound of refrigerant absorbs while flowing through the evaporator"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The “refrigerating effect” of a refrigerant is always:",
        "options": [
            "More than its latent heat",
            "More than its sensible heat",
            "Less than its sensible heat",
            "Less than its latent heat"
        ],
        "answer": "Less than its latent heat"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What will happen if the expansion valve is opened too wide?",
        "options": [
            "Liquid will flood back to the compressor",
            "It will make no difference, as the automatic expansion valve is still operating",
            "The condenser coils will overheat",
            "A or C"
        ],
        "answer": "Liquid will flood back to the compressor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following should not be used to clean scale traps?",
        "options": [
            "Compressed air",
            "Cotton waste",
            "Kerosene",
            "Diesel oil"
        ],
        "answer": "Cotton waste"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If one of the ship’s service boxes suddenly stops cooling, the most likely cause would be the malfunction of the:",
        "options": [
            "Discharge valve",
            "King valve",
            "Solenoid valve",
            "Expansion valve"
        ],
        "answer": "Solenoid valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following items is not important when using a halide torch?",
        "options": [
            "Move flame slowly around the joints",
            "Hold flame close to the joints",
            "Adjust to a clear white flame",
            "Adjust to a clear blue flame"
        ],
        "answer": "Adjust to a clear white flame"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A system should be purged when the liquid outlet temperature from the condenser is more than the temperature corresponding to the discharge pressure.",
        "options": [
            "10°F above",
            "20°F below",
            "20°F above",
            "5°F below"
        ],
        "answer": "5°F below"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following would cause the compressor to run continuously?",
        "options": [
            "Low-pressure switch jammed",
            "High-pressure switch jammed",
            "Clogged strainer",
            "Defective thermal bulb"
        ],
        "answer": "Low-pressure switch jammed"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "In a vapor compression cycle the lowest temperature is found in ________.",
        "options": [
            "Receiver",
            "Condenser",
            "Compressor",
            "Evaporator"
        ],
        "answer": "Evaporator"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The moisture in a refrigeration system can be removed with the help of which of the following?",
        "options": [
            "Driers",
            "Evaporators",
            "Dehumidifiers",
            "Coolers"
        ],
        "answer": "Driers"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following refrigerants has lowest freezing point temperature?",
        "options": [
            "Freon 12",
            "Ammonia",
            "Freon 22",
            "Freon 11"
        ],
        "answer": "Freon 22"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "During compression in a vapour compression cycle when the refrigerant is super-heated, what happens to the performance?",
        "options": [
            "C.O.P is reduced",
            "C.O.P remains unchanged",
            "Work done is increased",
            "Refrigerating effect is reduced"
        ],
        "answer": "C.O.P is reduced"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A Bell-Colman cycle is also known as ________.",
        "options": [
            "Reversed Otto cycle",
            "Reversed Joule cycle",
            "Reversed Rankine cycle",
            "Reversed Carnot cycle"
        ],
        "answer": "Reversed Joule cycle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Critical temperature is that temperature above which:",
        "options": [
            "A gas will never liquefy",
            "A gas gets immediately liquefy",
            "Water gets evaporated",
            "Water will never evaporate"
        ],
        "answer": "A gas will never liquefy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Rating of a domestic refrigerator is of the order of:",
        "options": [
            "0.1 ton",
            "50 tons",
            "100 tons",
            "4 tons"
        ],
        "answer": "0.1 ton"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What is the usual COP of a domestic refrigerator?",
        "options": [
            "Less than 1",
            "More than 1",
            "Equal to 1",
            "Depends upon the make of it"
        ],
        "answer": "More than 1"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Horsepower per ton of refrigeration is expressed as:",
        "options": [
            "4.75/COP",
            "4.75xCOP",
            "COP/4.75",
            "4.75/COP"
        ],
        "answer": "COP/4.75"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The highest temperature in vapour compression cycle is produced during:",
        "options": [
            "Expansion valve",
            "Evaporator",
            "Condenser discharge",
            "Compressor discharge"
        ],
        "answer": "Compressor discharge"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which type of compressor is used in refrigeration system?",
        "options": [
            "Reciprocating",
            "Centrifugal",
            "Rotary sliding vane",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What is the reason why a thermometer in vapor compression system is installed close to the compressor?",
        "options": [
            "Because it helps the operator in adjusting compressor for greatest efficiency",
            "Because temperature indicates whether liquid or vapor refrigerant is going to compressor",
            "Because temperature helps in calculating the coefficient of performance",
            "Because the performance of other units of the cycle can be controlled"
        ],
        "answer": "Because it helps the operator in adjusting compressor for greatest efficiency"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which refrigerant has the highest critical point temperature?",
        "options": [
            "Ammonia",
            "Freon 11",
            "Freon 12",
            "Freon 22"
        ],
        "answer": "Freon 11"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "White ice is",
        "options": [
            "Fast cooled water",
            "Sub cooled water",
            "Due to dissolved air, gases and impurities",
            "Formed by blowing air during freezing"
        ],
        "answer": "Due to dissolved air, gases and impurities"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Clear ice is",
        "options": [
            "Is pure ice",
            "Contains dissolved gases",
            "Contains dissolved air",
            "Is formed by blowing air during freezing"
        ],
        "answer": "Is formed by blowing air during freezing"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Dry ice is",
        "options": [
            "Free from water",
            "Free from dissolved air or gases",
            "Does not contain impurities",
            "Solidified form of carbon dioxide"
        ],
        "answer": "Solidified form of carbon dioxide"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The leaks in a refrigeration system using Freon can be detected by:",
        "options": [
            "Halide torch which detection forms greenish flame lighting",
            "Sulfur sticks which on detection form white smoke",
            "Using certain reagents",
            "Smelling"
        ],
        "answer": "Halide torch which detection forms greenish flame lighting"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The lower horizontal line of the following of the refrigeration cycle plotted on pressure enthalpy diagram represents:",
        "options": [
            "Compression of the refrigerant vapor",
            "Evaporation of the refrigerant liquid",
            "Condensation of the refrigerant vapor",
            "Metering of the refrigerant liquid"
        ],
        "answer": "Evaporation of the refrigerant liquid"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following uses a secondary refrigerant",
        "options": [
            "Domestic refrigerator",
            "Room air conditioner",
            "Deep freezer",
            "Ice plant"
        ],
        "answer": "Ice plant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following secondary refrigerants generally used in milk chilling plants?",
        "options": [
            "Brine",
            "Ammonia solution",
            "Glycol",
            "Sodium silicate"
        ],
        "answer": "Glycol"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What is the cycle where a refrigeration system generally operates?",
        "options": [
            "Open cycle",
            "Closed cycle",
            "Mixed cycle",
            "Hybrid cycle"
        ],
        "answer": "Closed cycle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following is also known as refrigerant NO. R-717?",
        "options": [
            "Ammonia",
            "Freon 22",
            "Freon 12",
            "Methyl chloride"
        ],
        "answer": "Ammonia"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "In which part of the vapour compression cycle there is abrupt change in pressure and temperature?",
        "options": [
            "Solenoid valve",
            "Evaporator",
            "Expansion valve",
            "Drier"
        ],
        "answer": "Expansion valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What do you call a plate or vane used to direct or control movement of fluid or air within the confined area?",
        "options": [
            "Baffle",
            "Bellows",
            "Regulator",
            "Diffuser"
        ],
        "answer": "Baffle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Brazing is used for joining two ________.",
        "options": [
            "Two ferrous material",
            "One ferrous and non-ferrous material",
            "Two non-ferrous materials",
            "Two non-metals"
        ],
        "answer": "Two non-ferrous materials"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which refrigerant is used for the air-conditioning of passenger aircraft cabin?",
        "options": [
            "Ammonia",
            "Freon 12",
            "Freon 11",
            "Air"
        ],
        "answer": "Air"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Oil separator in a refrigeration cycle is installed between the ______.",
        "options": [
            "Compressor and condenser",
            "Condenser and evaporator",
            "Metering device and evaporator",
            "None of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "Compressor and condenser"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A flash chamber is installed in the refrigeration circuit so as to:",
        "options": [
            "Improve overall heat transfer coefficient",
            "Reduce pressure losses through the evaporator",
            "Reduce the size of evaporator by avoiding vapors going to evaporator",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The color of the flame of halide torch, in case of leakage of Freon refrigerant, will change to:",
        "options": [
            "Yellow",
            "Red",
            "Green",
            "Orange"
        ],
        "answer": "Green"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What is the Boiling temperature of F-12?",
        "options": [
            "-33.33°C",
            "-78.5°C",
            "-29.8°C",
            "-40°C"
        ],
        "answer": "-29.8°C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which is the Boiling temperature of F-22?",
        "options": [
            "-33.33°C",
            "-29.8°C",
            "-78.5°C",
            "-40°C"
        ],
        "answer": "-40°C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The following gas is preferred in refrigeration system:",
        "options": [
            "F-11",
            "F-22",
            "CO2",
            "NH3"
        ],
        "answer": "F-22"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The bhp/ton refrigeration requirement with increase in condenser temperature, in a vapour compression system that uses reciprocating compressor receiving refrigerant gas at constant suction temperature, will follow:",
        "options": [
            "Linearly decreasing characteristic",
            "Linearly increasing characteristic",
            "First increase rapidly and then decrease slowly",
            "First increase slowly and then rapidly"
        ],
        "answer": "Linearly increasing characteristic"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Antifreeze chemicals are:",
        "options": [
            "Same as refrigerants",
            "Those that are added to refrigerants for better performance",
            "Those that lower down the freezing points of liquids",
            "Those that do not freeze at all"
        ],
        "answer": "Those that lower down the freezing points of liquids"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The capacity in ice making is always",
        "options": [
            "Less than the refrigerating effect",
            "Greater than the refrigerating effect",
            "Equal to the refrigerating effect",
            "Directly proportional to the refrigerating effect"
        ],
        "answer": "Directly proportional to the refrigerating effect"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "To check the lack of refrigerant or clogged refrigerant lines",
        "options": [
            "Installing service valves must be necessary",
            "Installing king valve must be an option",
            "Sight glasses can be possibly used",
            "Discharge pressure and temperature must be monitored"
        ],
        "answer": "Installing service valves must be necessary"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Past ME Board Examination Can any refrigerant be used with a booster system?",
        "options": [
            "Yes",
            "No",
            "Used for some",
            "Used for all"
        ],
        "answer": "No"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What is the chemical formula of methylene chloride?",
        "options": [
            "CHCIF",
            "CHCI",
            "CCIF",
            "CBRF"
        ],
        "answer": "CHCI"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What is the chemical formula of butane?",
        "options": [
            "CHCI",
            "CH",
            "CHO",
            "CH"
        ],
        "answer": "CH"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Type of refrigerant control which maintains pressure difference between high side and low side pressure in refrigerating mechanism:",
        "options": [
            "Suction valve",
            "Expansion valve",
            "Service valve",
            "Solenoid valve"
        ],
        "answer": "Expansion valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The dividing point between the high pressure and low pressure sides of the refrigeration cycle occurs at the:",
        "options": [
            "Expansion valve",
            "Compressor",
            "Condenser",
            "Cooling coil"
        ],
        "answer": "Expansion valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Boiling temperature of Freon 12 is:",
        "options": [
            "-33.33°C",
            "-78.5°C",
            "-29.8°C",
            "-40.7°C"
        ],
        "answer": "-29.8°C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Boiling temperature of Freon 22 is:",
        "options": [
            "-33.33°F",
            "-29.8°C",
            "-78.5°C",
            "-41.04°C"
        ],
        "answer": "-41.04°C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The fastest way to remove frost from a direct -expansion finned – tube evaporator is to:",
        "options": [
            "Send hot gas through the coil",
            "Scrape off frost",
            "Wash with warm water",
            "Shut down warm let frost melt"
        ],
        "answer": "Send hot gas through the coil"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "You want to change refrigerants in a Freon-12 plant using a reciprocating single- acting compressor. Which refrigerant requires the smallest amount of change to the system?",
        "options": [
            "Carbon dioxide",
            "Ammonia",
            "Methyl chloride",
            "Aqua ammonia"
        ],
        "answer": "Methyl chloride"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Soft copper tubing is used for refrigerant piping, erected on premises containing other than Group 1 refrigerant must be protected by ______.",
        "options": [
            "Supporting it by approved clamps",
            "Limiting its length between supports up to 10 feet",
            "A rigid or flexible metal enclosure",
            "Wrapping it with insulation tape throughout its length"
        ],
        "answer": "A rigid or flexible metal enclosure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A Freon-12 refrigeration system is fitted with thermal expansion valves. The valves are rated in:",
        "options": [
            "Pound per minute",
            "Superheat setting",
            "Tons of refrigeration",
            "Cubic feet per minute"
        ],
        "answer": "Tons of refrigeration"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The vapour cycle in thermal efficiency as the refrigeration cycle is to the ______.",
        "options": [
            "Energy efficiency ratio",
            "COP for a refrigerator",
            "COP for a heat pump",
            "Carnot efficiency"
        ],
        "answer": "COP for a refrigerator"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The main purpose of a subcooler in a refrigerating system especially a two- stage system is to:",
        "options": [
            "Increase the heat rejection per ton and avoid system shutdown",
            "Improve the flow of evaporator gas per ton and increase the temperature",
            "Reduce the total power requirements and return oil to the compressor",
            "Reduce the total power requirements and heat rejection to the second stage"
        ],
        "answer": "Reduce the total power requirements and heat rejection to the second stage"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Ton of refrigeration is a unit equivalent to:",
        "options": [
            "50.4 kCal/sec",
            "12,660 kN-m/hr",
            "3413 kW/-hr",
            "2545 Btu/hr"
        ],
        "answer": "12,660 kN-m/hr"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "In a refrigerating system, the heat absorbed in the evaporator per kg mass of refrigerant passing through:",
        "options": [
            "Equals the increase in enthalpy",
            "Does not depend on the refrigerant used",
            "Is decreased if pre-cooler is used",
            "Equals the increase in volume"
        ],
        "answer": "Equals the increase in enthalpy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Lithium bromide is used in refrigeration system in:",
        "options": [
            "Condensate return lines",
            "Absorbers",
            "Centrifugal compressors",
            "Ion exchangers"
        ],
        "answer": "Absorbers"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A refrigeration system in which only part of the refrigerant passes over the heat transfer surface is evaporated and the balance is separated from the vapour and recirculated.",
        "options": [
            "Direct expansion system",
            "Chilled water system",
            "Flooded system",
            "Multiple system"
        ],
        "answer": "Flooded system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A device whose primary function is to meter the flow of refrigerant to the evaporator.",
        "options": [
            "Sniffer valve",
            "Equalizer",
            "Thermostatic expansion valve",
            "Crossover valve"
        ],
        "answer": "Thermostatic expansion valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Select the one in which secondary refrigerant is used.",
        "options": [
            "Domestic refrigerator",
            "Room air conditioner",
            "Deep freezer",
            "Ice plant"
        ],
        "answer": "Ice plant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "An odorless refrigerant whose boiling point varies over a wide range of temperatures.",
        "options": [
            "Freon 22",
            "Freon 12",
            "Ammonia",
            "Freon 11"
        ],
        "answer": "Freon 22"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The part that directs the flow of refrigerant through the compressor",
        "options": [
            "Wrist pin",
            "Valve",
            "Piston",
            "Connecting rod"
        ],
        "answer": "Valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The highest temperature in vapor compression cycle is produced during:",
        "options": [
            "Receiver",
            "Evaporator",
            "Condenser discharge",
            "Compressor discharge"
        ],
        "answer": "Compressor discharge"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The boiling point of Freon 22 is:",
        "options": [
            "-41.04°F",
            "20.60°F",
            "-38.40°F",
            "-31.40°F"
        ],
        "answer": "-41.04°F"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The secondary refrigerant used in milk chilling plants is generally:",
        "options": [
            "Brine",
            "Ammonia",
            "Glycol",
            "Sodium silicate"
        ],
        "answer": "Glycol"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The sensible heat ratio is 0.8. That is",
        "options": [
            "20% latent heat and 60% sensible heat",
            "80% sensible heat and 20% latent heat",
            "80% sensible heat and 20% sensible heat and latent heat",
            "20% latent heat and 80% sensible heat and latent heat"
        ],
        "answer": "80% sensible heat and 20% latent heat"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The effect of superheating the refrigerant is to:",
        "options": [
            "Increase the COP",
            "Increase and decrease the COP",
            "Decrease the COP",
            "Maintains the COP"
        ],
        "answer": "Increase the COP"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The ice making capacity is always",
        "options": [
            "Directly proportional to the refrigerating effect",
            "Less than the refrigerating effect",
            "Greater than the refrigerating effect",
            "Equal to the refrigerating effect"
        ],
        "answer": "Directly proportional to the refrigerating effect"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The amount of sensible heat for a sensible heat ration of 0.80 and a total cooling load of 100 is:",
        "options": [
            "80",
            "20",
            "100",
            "60"
        ],
        "answer": "80"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The high pressure of refrigeration system consist of the line to the expansion valve, the receiver, the uppermost half of the compressor and the:",
        "options": [
            "Line after the expansion valve",
            "Lower most half of compressor",
            "Condenser",
            "Evaporator"
        ],
        "answer": "Condenser"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following materials is suitable for tubing in refrigeration application where refrigerant ammonia is employed?",
        "options": [
            "Plastic",
            "Brass",
            "Steel",
            "Copper"
        ],
        "answer": "Steel"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If PV is the power required for a vapor-compression refrigeration system, then what is the power required for an air-refrigeration system, assuming that they have the same capacity?",
        "options": [
            "5PV",
            "2PV",
            "PV/10",
            "1/PV"
        ],
        "answer": "5PV"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Tons of refrigeration in Btu/24 hours is",
        "options": [
            "288,000",
            "28,800",
            "290,000",
            "29,000"
        ],
        "answer": "288,000"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "R-22 is:",
        "options": [
            "Dichloridfluoromethane",
            "Monochlorodifluoromethane",
            "Methyl chloride",
            "Trichlorodifluoromethane"
        ],
        "answer": "Monochlorodifluoromethane"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "A salimeter reads the:",
        "options": [
            "Density of brine",
            "Rate of brine",
            "Dew point temperature",
            "Relative humidity"
        ],
        "answer": "Density of brine"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "Which of the following measures the density of salt in water?",
        "options": [
            "Salimeter",
            "Hydrometer",
            "Pitot tube",
            "Calorimeter"
        ],
        "answer": "Salimeter"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "What is the device used to protect the compressor from overloading due to high head pressure?",
        "options": [
            "Overload relay",
            "Hold back suction valve",
            "Thermostatic expansion valve",
            "Expansion valve"
        ],
        "answer": "Overload relay"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "The purpose of the expansion valve is to control the flow of the refrigerant to the evaporator. The other function is to:",
        "options": [
            "Reduce the pressure of the liquid refrigerant",
            "Increase the pressure of the vapor refrigerant",
            "Reduce the pressure of the vapor refrigerant",
            "Increase the pressure of the liquid refrigerant"
        ],
        "answer": "Reduce the pressure of the liquid refrigerant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "It prevents the refrigerant from the condenser to go back to the compressor.",
        "options": [
            "Check valve",
            "Float switch",
            "Expansion valve",
            "Low side float"
        ],
        "answer": "Check valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 14,
        "question": "If the freezing point of water is 0°C, which of the following is its melting point?",
        "options": [
            "Slightly less than 0°C",
            "Slightly more than 0°C",
            "0°C",
            "32°C"
        ],
        "answer": "0°C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "How do you call the water vapor content of air?",
        "options": [
            "moisture",
            "humidity",
            "dew",
            "vapor"
        ],
        "answer": "humidity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "When air contains all of the  water vapor it can hold, it is said to be",
        "options": [
            "simulated",
            "loaded",
            "saturated",
            "moistured"
        ],
        "answer": "saturated"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "What is the instrument used to register relative humidity?",
        "options": [
            "hygrometer",
            "hydrometer",
            "perometer",
            "manometer"
        ],
        "answer": "hygrometer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Humidity is a measure of which of  the following?",
        "options": [
            "water vapor content",
            "temperature",
            "latent heat",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "water vapor content"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Air conditioning is the process of :",
        "options": [
            "keeping a place cool",
            "removing the heat from a specific area",
            "maintaining air at a required temperature and humidity",
            "A or C"
        ],
        "answer": "maintaining air at a required temperature and humidity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "In an air-conditioning system, before the air is circulated to the required are it is:",
        "options": [
            "cooled",
            "filtered",
            "dehumidified",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "all of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "The temperature at which water vapor in the atmosphere begins to condense is known as the:",
        "options": [
            "vapor point",
            "dew point",
            "moisture point",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "dew point"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Saturation temperature is the same as:",
        "options": [
            "dew point B.vapor temperature",
            "steam temperature",
            "humidity"
        ],
        "answer": "dew point"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "When the bypass factor is B, the coil efficiency for sensible cooling of air equal to:",
        "options": [
            "1+B",
            "1-B",
            "1-B/B",
            "1+B/B"
        ],
        "answer": "1-B"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "The psychrometric chart in air conditioning determines the",
        "options": [
            "wet bulb and dry bulb temperatures",
            "psychrometric temperature requirements",
            "saturation temperature and relatives humidity",
            "moist air conditions"
        ],
        "answer": "moist air conditions"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Which of the following is considered as comfort condition in air conditioning?",
        "options": [
            "40 C DBT, 80% RH",
            "30 C DBT, 60% RH",
            "30 C DBT, 80% RH",
            "20 C DBT, 60% RH"
        ],
        "answer": "20 C DBT, 60% RH"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "The drift loss in cooling towers is about :",
        "options": [
            "1% only",
            "12 to 15%",
            "10 to 20%",
            "30 to 40%"
        ],
        "answer": "10 to 20%"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Cooling towers are used for cooling water :",
        "options": [
            "to be injected in circulating air",
            "to be used for humidification",
            "to be used for filtration of air",
            "to be used for cooling the compressor"
        ],
        "answer": "to be used for cooling the compressor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "By which of the following processes heat mainly dissipates in cooling towers?",
        "options": [
            "conduction",
            "convection",
            "radiation",
            "evaporation"
        ],
        "answer": "evaporation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Which one is commonly used liquid absorbent?",
        "options": [
            "silica gel",
            "activated alumina C.ethylene glycol",
            "any one of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "in sensible heating cooling following parameter remains unchanged",
        "options": [
            "dry bulb temperature",
            "wet bulb temperature",
            "relative humidity",
            "humidity ratio",
            "sprays of water kept at a temperature higher than the dew point temperature of the entering",
            "a solid absorbent surface",
            "a liquid absorbent spray",
            "any one of B and C"
        ],
        "answer": "any one of B and C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Dirt and foreign materials normally build-up on the side of the condenser tubes. To ensure adequate condenser capacity, a certain factor is used in calculating the overall heat transfer through the walls of the tubes including the heat transfer through the walls of the tubes including the heat transfer rate of the layers dirt and foreign materials. What is the factor?",
        "options": [
            "booster factor",
            "factor of safety",
            "fouling factor",
            "compression factor"
        ],
        "answer": "fouling factor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "The engineer was tested to design the air conditioning system for a ball room dance hall. Considering that this involve a lot of activity from its users,the engineer would design that will require:",
        "options": [
            "maximum attainable effective temperature",
            "constant effective temperature",
            "higher effective temperature",
            "lower effective temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "maximum attainable effective temperature"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "What is the value of the Mach No. throat of the converging-diverging nozzle?",
        "options": [
            "zero",
            "two",
            "one",
            "ten"
        ],
        "answer": "one"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "What do bodies at a temperature above absolute zero?",
        "options": [
            "it emits Energy",
            "it emits Thermal Radiation",
            "it emits Heat for conduction",
            "it emits Heat for convection"
        ],
        "answer": "it emits Thermal Radiation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "When air is saturated, the wet bulb depression is:",
        "options": [
            "zero",
            "indefinite",
            "unity",
            "100 %"
        ],
        "answer": "zero"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "In a window air conditioning unit which if the following is done by the owner?",
        "options": [
            "semiannual cleaning or replacement of filters",
            "annual cleaning of the evaporator, condenser, fan blades, fan motor, compressor and casing",
            "Inspection of fan motors and lubricate them",
            "all of these"
        ],
        "answer": "semiannual cleaning or replacement of filters"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Fan motors in air conditioning units have:",
        "options": [
            "2 or 3 speeds",
            "3 or 4 speeds",
            "1 or 2 speeds",
            "4 or 5 speeds"
        ],
        "answer": "2 or 3 speeds"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Which of the following capacitors that can usually be found in an air conditioning unit?",
        "options": [
            "starting capacitors",
            "running capacitors",
            "fan motor capacitors",
            "all of these"
        ],
        "answer": "all of these"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Which of the following troubles commonly occurs inside an air conditioning unit?",
        "options": [
            "stuck compressor",
            "clogged refrigerant circuit",
            "short circuit, open circuit, grounded motor winding",
            "all of these"
        ],
        "answer": "all of these"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "The motor condition of an air conditioning unit can be checked with:",
        "options": [
            "the continuity of light or with an ohmmeter",
            "the flow of refrigerant in the receiver",
            "the discharge pressure in the compressor",
            "all of these"
        ],
        "answer": "the continuity of light or with an ohmmeter"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "An air conditioning system wherein the entire systems are mounted in the cabinet:",
        "options": [
            "console air conditioners",
            "centralized air conditioners",
            "packaged type air conditioners",
            "multizone split ductless system"
        ],
        "answer": "console air conditioners"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "The use of water to carry heat occupied spaces",
        "options": [
            "hydronic heating system",
            "water boiling system",
            "hydrokinetic heating system",
            "hydraulic heating system"
        ],
        "answer": "hydronic heating system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "The method of cooling which primarily used where ambient air temperatures are high and relative humidity is used:",
        "options": [
            "swamp cooling",
            "evaporative cooling",
            "condensate cooling",
            "hydroionic cooling"
        ],
        "answer": "swamp cooling"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "The other name for Swamp Cooling is:",
        "options": [
            "Evaporative Cooling",
            "Condensate Cooling",
            "Wet Roof Cooling",
            "Excelsior Cooling"
        ],
        "answer": "Wet Roof Cooling"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Evaporative Condenser is used to cool",
        "options": [
            "condenser vapor",
            "condenser surface",
            "condensate liquid",
            "all of these"
        ],
        "answer": "condenser vapor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "A method of cooling which uses water as refrigerant.  Pressure on the water surface is reduced to lower its boiling temperature.",
        "options": [
            "Steam Jet Cooling",
            "Evaporative Cooling",
            "Vortex Tube Cooling",
            "Pressurized Cooling"
        ],
        "answer": "Steam Jet Cooling"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Palladium Chloride may be used to measure the presence of :",
        "options": [
            "vapor",
            "CO",
            "ammonia",
            "refrigerant"
        ],
        "answer": "CO"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "The amount of CO can be determined by the color of Palladium Chloride. An amount of 30 ppm to 70 ppm will cause:",
        "options": [
            "slight darkening",
            "grey color",
            "red color",
            "black color"
        ],
        "answer": "slight darkening"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "The term used to express the amount moisture in a given sample of air. It is  compared with amount of moisture in a given sample of air.",
        "options": [
            "humidity",
            "relative humidity",
            "absolute humidity",
            "humidity ratio"
        ],
        "answer": "relative humidity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "How should the window type air conditioning unit can be placed?",
        "options": [
            "slant toward the inside of the home",
            "slant toward the outside of the home",
            "level",
            "slant at approximately 15 degrees from the horizontal"
        ],
        "answer": "slant toward the outside of the home"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "A dehumidifier is usually a small hermitic refrigerating system. It has both a condenser and an evaporator. Many older systems use R-12 or R-500. The newer units use:",
        "options": [
            "R-124a",
            "R-145a",
            "R-217a",
            "R-121a"
        ],
        "answer": "R-124a"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "The normal cut-out setting of a window unit thermostat is between:",
        "options": [
            "13 degrees C to 16 degrees C",
            "16 degrees C to 21 degrees C",
            "17 degrees C to 22 degrees C",
            "10 degrees C to 15 degrees C"
        ],
        "answer": "13 degrees C to 16 degrees C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Thermostat are used with most window units. They have differentials which may vary between:",
        "options": [
            "2 degrees C to 4 degrees C",
            "3 degrees C to 5 degrees  C",
            "4 degrees  C to 5 degrees  C",
            "1 degrees  C to 2 degrees  C"
        ],
        "answer": "2 degrees C to 4 degrees C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "In an air conditioning unit, the thermostat fails. The unit did not start. How do you test the operation of the thermostat?",
        "options": [
            "Cover the air outlet and air inlet with a cloth. The air will recirculate into the unit  and the temperature will quickly drop to the cut out temperature",
            "Cover the outlet and the air will not circulate and the thermostat functions because no air movement",
            "Cover both the inlet and outlet so that  the recirculating air has the same temperature",
            "Never cover any air passage so that air can freely move and thermostat functions well"
        ],
        "answer": "Cover the air outlet and air inlet with a cloth. The air will recirculate into the unit  and the"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Which of the following duhimidifier is often used to reheat the air after moisture is removed?",
        "options": [
            "Evaporator",
            "Chiller",
            "Condenser",
            "Compressor"
        ],
        "answer": "Condenser"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Which of the following refrigerant is added sometimes to other refrigerant to improve oil circulation?",
        "options": [
            "R-117",
            "R-778",
            "R-170 (ethane)",
            "R-270"
        ],
        "answer": "R-170 (ethane)"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "A refrigeration that deals with producing temperature of -157 degrees C or lower.",
        "options": [
            "Low temperature",
            "Extremely low temperature refrigeration",
            "Absolute zero refrigeration",
            "Cryogenics"
        ],
        "answer": "Cryogenics"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Measurement of a device's ability to remove atmospheric air from test air.",
        "options": [
            "Atmospheric Dust Spot Efficiency",
            "Atmospheric Dry Air Efficiency",
            "Test air Efficiency",
            "Baudelot Air Efficiency"
        ],
        "answer": "Atmospheric Dust Spot Efficiency"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "A liquid mixture having constant maximum and minimum boiling points. Refrigerants comprising this mixture do not combine chemically, yet the mixture provides constant characteristics.",
        "options": [
            "Azeotropic Mixture",
            "Homogeneous Mixture",
            "Conzeotropic Mixture",
            "Cyrogenic Mixture"
        ],
        "answer": "Azeotropic Mixture"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Refrigerant in Group A1 (R-11). Chemical combination of carbon , chlorine, and flourine.",
        "options": [
            "Carrene",
            "Cerrene",
            "CCL group",
            "HCL group"
        ],
        "answer": "Carrene"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Which of the following refrigerants is popular in the industrial refrigerating system; also popularly absorption system of refrigerant.",
        "options": [
            "R-117 (ammonia)",
            "R-600 (butane)",
            "R-611 (methyl formate)",
            "R-504"
        ],
        "answer": "R-117 (ammonia)"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Which of the following is a function of air conditioning?",
        "options": [
            "Temperature and Humidity Control",
            "Air Filtering, Cleaning, and Purification",
            "Air Movement and Circulation",
            "All of these"
        ],
        "answer": "All of these"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Oxygen is approximately what percent by weight in the atmosphere?",
        "options": [
            "23%",
            "27%",
            "77%",
            "73%"
        ],
        "answer": "23%"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Substances that have the ability to absorb moisture from the air are called:",
        "options": [
            "Desiccants",
            "Moisturizer",
            "Dehygroscopic substances",
            "Moisture absorber"
        ],
        "answer": "Desiccants"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "When the dry bulb and the wet bulb temperatures are identical, the air is said to be:",
        "options": [
            "saturated",
            "compressed",
            "humidified",
            "dehumidified"
        ],
        "answer": "saturated"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "In what form that water exists in air?",
        "options": [
            "solid",
            "liquid",
            "vapor",
            "saturated"
        ],
        "answer": "vapor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "When air is heated, what happened to its relative humidity?",
        "options": [
            "increases",
            "decreases",
            "remain constant",
            "may increase or decrease depending on temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "decreases"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "The horizontal Scale ( abscissa ) in the psychrometric chart represents:",
        "options": [
            "Dry bulb temperature",
            "Wet bulb temperature",
            "Relative Humidity",
            "Humidity"
        ],
        "answer": "Dry bulb temperature"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Most people are comfortable with the relative humidity of :",
        "options": [
            "30% to 70%",
            "10% to 40%",
            "20% to 30%",
            "40% to 80%"
        ],
        "answer": "30% to 70%"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "The temperature below which vapor in the air will start to condense :",
        "options": [
            "condensing temperature",
            "dry bulb temperature",
            "dew point temperature",
            "wet bulb temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "dew point temperature"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Which of the following is not used as method to measure air velocities?",
        "options": [
            "hot wire anemometer",
            "rotating anemometer",
            "swinging vane velocimeter",
            "open type barometer"
        ],
        "answer": "open type barometer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "It is a form of oxygen photochemically produced in nature.",
        "options": [
            "Ozone",
            "Oxidation",
            "Oxidation Agent",
            "DO2"
        ],
        "answer": "Ozone"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "What is the Chemical formula of Ozone?",
        "options": [
            "O3",
            "O2",
            "D2O",
            "O1"
        ],
        "answer": "O3"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "In the upper atmosphere, ozone is made by ultraviolet light reacting with:",
        "options": [
            "Oxygen",
            "Hydrogen",
            "Nitrogen",
            "Water Vapor"
        ],
        "answer": "Oxygen"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "The ozone concentration of 0.10 parts per million (ppm) is generally considered the maximum permissible for how many hours exposure?",
        "options": [
            "8 hrs.",
            "4 hrs.",
            "7 hrs.",
            "3 hrs."
        ],
        "answer": "8 hrs."
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "How many moisture be removed from air ?",
        "options": [
            "Condensation",
            "Absorption",
            "A and B",
            "none of these"
        ],
        "answer": "A and B"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "In cooling cycle, the dry bulb temperature (db) of the air is lowered. when this happens the relative humidity",
        "options": [
            "increases",
            "decreases",
            "remains constant",
            "increases or decreases depending on the temperature at which it is cooled"
        ],
        "answer": "increases"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "What is the effect of superheating the refrigerant?",
        "options": [
            "it increases the coefficient of performance",
            "it decreases the coefficient of performance",
            "it lowers the boiling point of the refrigerant",
            "it increases the suction pressure of the refrigerant"
        ],
        "answer": "it increases the coefficient of performance"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "In sensible heating the absolute humidity remains contant but the relative humidity :",
        "options": [
            "increases",
            "decreases",
            "remains constant",
            "zero"
        ],
        "answer": "decreases"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "The relative humidity becomes 100% and where the water vapor starts to condense.",
        "options": [
            "dew point",
            "cloud point",
            "saturated point",
            "critical point"
        ],
        "answer": "dew point"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Why should you avoid bending or twisting of fan blades in an air conditioning unit?",
        "options": [
            "it will not cause ice build-up",
            "it will wear out the motor bearings and cause noise",
            "it may not slice suction line",
            "it decreases the volume flow of refrigerant"
        ],
        "answer": "it will wear out the motor bearings and cause noise"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "A type of refrigerant that will not damage the ozone layer.",
        "options": [
            "Hydrofluorucarbons ( HCF's )",
            "Hydrochlorofluorocarbons ( HCHF's )",
            "R-22",
            "R-12"
        ],
        "answer": "Hydrofluorucarbons ( HCF's )"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Which of the following refrigerants damages the ozone layer?",
        "options": [
            "Hydrochlorofluorocarbons ( HCHF's )",
            "R-12",
            "R-22",
            "All of these"
        ],
        "answer": "All of these"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Which of the following components of the window air conditioning system must be cleaned annually?",
        "options": [
            "evaporator and condenser",
            "motor and compressor",
            "fan blades and fan motor",
            "all of these"
        ],
        "answer": "all of these"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "The phenomenon that warm air rise and cold air settle is called:",
        "options": [
            "stratification",
            "sedimentation",
            "setting due",
            "ventilation"
        ],
        "answer": "stratification"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Air delivered to the room from the supply duct, moving at a velocity of 150ft/min is called:",
        "options": [
            "primary air",
            "secondary air",
            "saturated air",
            "air turbulance"
        ],
        "answer": "primary air"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Carries needed to deliver air to the conditioned space. It is made of metals like alluminum, galvanized sheet steel and some structural materials that will not burn.",
        "options": [
            "duct",
            "air inlet",
            "air outlet",
            "diffuser"
        ],
        "answer": "duct"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "From what principle that air ducts operate?",
        "options": [
            "principle of pressure difference",
            "principle of temperature difference C.forced draft fan principle",
            "principle of natural convection"
        ],
        "answer": "principle of pressure difference"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Which of the following is the common classification of ducts?",
        "options": [
            "conditioned air-duct",
            "recirculating",
            "fresh-air duct",
            "all of these"
        ],
        "answer": "all of these"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "It is used deliver concentrated air streams into a room. Many have one-way or two-way adjustable air stream deflectors.",
        "options": [
            "register",
            "grille",
            "diffuser",
            "damper"
        ],
        "answer": "register"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "It is used to control air-throw distance, height, and spread, as well as the amount of air.",
        "options": [
            "grille",
            "register",
            "diffuser",
            "damper"
        ],
        "answer": "grille"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "It is used to deliver widespread, fan shaped flows of air into the room.",
        "options": [
            "grille",
            "register",
            "diffuser",
            "damper"
        ],
        "answer": "diffuser"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Which of the following fans in air conditioning systems which can be classified as centrifugal flow?",
        "options": [
            "axial fan",
            "propeller fan",
            "bi-axial fan",
            "none of these"
        ],
        "answer": "propeller fan"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "The most common controller in the heating and cooling systems.",
        "options": [
            "thermostat",
            "pressure gage",
            "barometer",
            "sling psychometer"
        ],
        "answer": "thermostat"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "A thermostat that functions as increase or decrease instead of starting and stopping system is called:",
        "options": [
            "modulate",
            "heating-cooling the thermostat",
            "interlocked",
            "compound thermostat"
        ],
        "answer": "modulate"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "A number used to compare energy usage for different areas. It is calculated by dividing the energy consumption by the fottage of the conditioned area.",
        "options": [
            "energy utilization unit",
            "energy utilization efficiency",
            "energy utilization index",
            "energy utilization ratio"
        ],
        "answer": "energy utilization index"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "The ratio of the rated cooling  capacity divided by the amount of electrical power used:",
        "options": [
            "energy efficiency ratio (EER)",
            "energy efficiency index (EE)",
            "cooling efficiency (CE)",
            "energy cooling ratio (ECR)"
        ],
        "answer": "energy efficiency ratio (EER)"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Heat exchanger in which water flows by gravity over the outside of  the tubes or plates.",
        "options": [
            "baudelot cooler",
            "free cooler",
            "newtonian cooler",
            "bourdon cooler"
        ],
        "answer": "baudelot cooler"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "A popular air conditioning system that includes a single outdoor condenser, 3 independent evaporators, and individual evaporator temperature control. The condensing unit is located outside on a slab. They are frequently used in legal and medical offices, motels and  homes without ducts.",
        "options": [
            "multizone ductless split system",
            "packaged terminal air conditioner",
            "console air conditioner",
            "window type air conditioner"
        ],
        "answer": "multizone ductless split system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "An air conditioning system which is a combination of heating and cooling system. It is designed to serve an individual room or zone.",
        "options": [
            "Multizone Ductless Split System",
            "Packaged Terminal Air Conditioner",
            "Console air Conditioner",
            "Window Type air Conditioner"
        ],
        "answer": "Packaged Terminal Air Conditioner"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Which of the following is to be checked as regular monthly maintenance schedule of a console air conditioning units?",
        "options": [
            "Water Leaks",
            "Fan Speeds",
            "Cooling Tower",
            "Duct Dampers, Registers and Diffusers"
        ],
        "answer": "Duct Dampers, Registers and Diffusers"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Which of the following is to be checked as part of the weekly maintenance shedule of a console air conditioners?",
        "options": [
            "Filters",
            "Humidifiers",
            "Safety valves",
            "Cooling Tower"
        ],
        "answer": "Cooling Tower"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "A mechanism that removes moisture.",
        "options": [
            "Humidifiers",
            "Dehumidifiers",
            "Moisturizers",
            "Cooling Towers"
        ],
        "answer": "Dehumidifiers"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "When coil surface temperature is below the dew point of the air.",
        "options": [
            "moisture will condense out of the air*",
            "vapor will evaporate through the air",
            "air is dehumidified",
            "air is humidified and saturated"
        ],
        "answer": "moisture will condense out of the air*"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Nitrogen occupied almost how much of the Earth's Atmosphere.",
        "options": [
            "One-fourth",
            "Three-fourths",
            "One-half",
            "One-third",
            "above",
            "equals",
            "below",
            "almost"
        ],
        "answer": "below"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "An instrument used in measuring air velocity by velocity-pressure method.",
        "options": [
            "Pitot Tube",
            "Anemometer",
            "Aneroid Barometer",
            "Flowmeter"
        ],
        "answer": "Pitot Tube"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "What is the specific humidity of dry air?",
        "options": [
            "100",
            "20",
            "0",
            "50"
        ],
        "answer": "0"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "When hot soup was served in a cup during dinner, an engineer was so eager to drink it. Since It was hot, he added ice cubes of ice to cool the soup stirred it. He noticed that dew starts to form on the outermost surface of the cup. He wanted to check the temperature of the outermost surface of the cup. What is this temperature equal to?",
        "options": [
            "superheated temperature",
            "equal to zero",
            "standard temperature",
            "equal to air's dew point temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "equal to air's dew point temperature"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "The temperature at which the water vapor in the gas begins to condense in a constant pressure process.",
        "options": [
            "Dew point",
            "Vapor point",
            "Flue point",
            "Gas point"
        ],
        "answer": "Dew point"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "All of the following processes can be found on a psychrometric chart except :",
        "options": [
            "humidification",
            "sensible heating",
            "natural convection",
            "sensible cooling"
        ],
        "answer": "natural convection"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "All of the following processes can be found on a psychrometric chart except:",
        "options": [
            "heating and humidifying",
            "cooling and dehumidification",
            "black body radiation",
            "evaporative cooling"
        ],
        "answer": "black body radiation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Which is not commonly used to cool and dehumidify equipment?",
        "options": [
            "Calcium chloride",
            "Activated alumina",
            "Sodium zeolite",
            "Silica gel"
        ],
        "answer": "Calcium chloride"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "All of the following temperatures have meaning in psychrometrics except:",
        "options": [
            "dry - bulb temperature",
            "wet - bulb temperature",
            "adiabatic wall temperature",
            "dew point"
        ],
        "answer": "adiabatic wall temperature"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "The relative humidity is given by the :",
        "options": [
            "ratio of the actual humidity to the saturated humidity at the same temperature and pressure",
            "ratio of the partial pressure of water vapor to saturation pressure",
            "ratio of wet-bulb to dry-bulb temperature",
            "ratio of dry bulb temperature to dew point"
        ],
        "answer": "ratio of the partial pressure of water vapor to saturation pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "The determination of properties and behavior of atmospheric air usually the purview of :",
        "options": [
            "thermodynamics",
            "psychrometrics",
            "forced convection",
            "Kirchoff's law"
        ],
        "answer": "psychrometrics"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Which of the following statements is correct? The relative humidity of an air water vapor mixture",
        "options": [
            "is the ratio of the partial pressure of the water vapor to the partial pressure of the air.",
            "indicates the mass of water vapor in the mixture",
            "is equal to the mole fraction of water vapor in the mixture at the mixture temperature.",
            "is the ratio of the partial pressure of water vapor to the saturation pressure at the mixture temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "is the ratio of the partial pressure of water vapor to"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "In sensible cooling process, moisture content.",
        "options": [
            "does not change",
            "decreases",
            "indeterminate",
            "increases"
        ],
        "answer": "does not change"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "What amount of air is required in a low bypass factor?",
        "options": [
            "Greater",
            "Lesser",
            "Indeterminate",
            "Constant"
        ],
        "answer": "Lesser"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "The design of an air supply duct of an air conditioning system ________.",
        "options": [
            "adds moisture to the air",
            "lowers the temperature of the air",
            "does not affect the moisture of air",
            "affects the distribution"
        ],
        "answer": "affects the distribution"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "What is the lowest temperature to which water could possibly be cooled in a cooling tower?",
        "options": [
            "The effective temperature",
            "The temperature of adiabatic compression",
            "The wet bulb depression",
            "The dew point temperature of the air"
        ],
        "answer": "The temperature of adiabatic compression"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Combined process of cooling and humidifying is also known as :",
        "options": [
            "heating and humidifying",
            "cooling tower",
            "evaporative cooling process",
            "moisture removal process"
        ],
        "answer": "evaporative cooling process"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "In a cooling tower, the water is cooled by :",
        "options": [
            "condensation",
            "evaporation",
            "convection",
            "conduction"
        ],
        "answer": "convection"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "Which of the following types of air dryers works by absorbing moisture on a solid dessicant or drying material such as activated alumina, silicon gel or molecular sieve?",
        "options": [
            "Regenerative dryer",
            "Deliquescent dryer",
            "Spray dryer",
            "Refrigerated dryer"
        ],
        "answer": "Deliquescent dryer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "The relationship of water vapor in the air at the dew point temperature to the amount that would be in the air if the air were saturated at the dry bulb temperature is:",
        "options": [
            "partial pressure actual at dew point",
            "percentage humidity",
            "relative humidity",
            "partial pressure of water"
        ],
        "answer": "relative humidity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "When the air is saturated the wet bulb depression is:",
        "options": [
            "zero",
            "indefinite",
            "unity",
            "100 %"
        ],
        "answer": "zero"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "A temperature measurement in an ordinary thermometer which has constant speciï¬•c humidity.",
        "options": [
            "Critical temperature",
            "Dew point temperature",
            "Dry bulb temperature",
            "Wet bulb temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "Dew point temperature"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "During sensible heating, the humidity remains constant  but the relative humidity.",
        "options": [
            "increases",
            "decreases",
            "remains constant",
            "zero"
        ],
        "answer": "decreases"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "The relative humidity becomes 100% and where the water vapor starts to condense.",
        "options": [
            "Critical point",
            "Saturated point",
            "Dew point",
            "Cloud point"
        ],
        "answer": "Dew point"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "What is the specific humidity of dry air?",
        "options": [
            "150",
            "100",
            "50",
            "0"
        ],
        "answer": "0"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "An engineer inspected an air-conditioning unit. He found out that the unit does not produce any cooling effect, however, the air-conditioning unit is running. 2, He checked the temperatures of the condenser and evaporator and had the unit run. He found out that there was no change in the temperature. What should he do? A Replace fuse",
        "options": [
            "Charge with new refrigerant",
            "Replace relay",
            "Adjust door seal"
        ],
        "answer": "Charge with new refrigerant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "What is the temperature range of air in air conditioning application where the dry air can be considered ideal gas?",
        "options": [
            "100°C to 125°C",
            "50°C  to 75°C",
            "75°C  to 100°C",
            "-10°C  to 50°C"
        ],
        "answer": "-10°C  to 50°C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 15,
        "question": "What is the value of air stratification in air conditioning design fit for human comfort? A minimum",
        "options": [
            "maximum",
            "less than air temperature",
            "equal to air temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "less than air temperature"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "Foundations are preferably built of concrete in the proportion of what measure of portland cement: sand: crushed stones?",
        "options": [
            "1:2:5",
            "2:4:6",
            "2:3:5",
            "1:2:4"
        ],
        "answer": "1:2:4"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "For design  stability, the center of gravity of the total combined engine, driven equipment and foundation should be kept _______.",
        "options": [
            "anywhere",
            "above the foundation top",
            "in line with surface of the foundation",
            "below the foundation top"
        ],
        "answer": "below the foundation top"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "The machine foundation must have a factor of safety of",
        "options": [
            "4",
            "5",
            "6",
            "7"
        ],
        "answer": "5"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "The diesel engine foundation safe soil bearing pressure is :",
        "options": [
            "4,890 kg/cm2",
            "4,500 kg/cm2",
            "4,490 kg/cm2",
            "4,125 kg/cm2"
        ],
        "answer": "4,890 kg/cm2"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "Anchor bolts in a machine foundation should be embedded in a concrete af at least how many times of the bolt diameter?",
        "options": [
            "15",
            "20",
            "30",
            "25"
        ],
        "answer": "30"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "As a good practical rule, the foundation depth  may be taken as how may times of the engine stroke?",
        "options": [
            "2.2 to 3.2",
            "3.2 to 4.2",
            "2.5 to 3.5",
            "3.5 to 4.5"
        ],
        "answer": "3.2 to 4.2"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "To secure the belts embedded within the foundation, the distance of the edges of the foundation from the bedplate must be _______.",
        "options": [
            "120 mm to 300 mm",
            "150 mm to 330 mm",
            "100 mm to 280 mm",
            "200 mm to 380 mm"
        ],
        "answer": "120 mm to 300 mm"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "The weight of the machine foundation is how many times of the weight of the engine ?",
        "options": [
            "4 to 5 times",
            "3 to 5 times",
            "2 to 3 times",
            "4 to 6 times"
        ],
        "answer": "3 to 5 times"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "To eliminate transmission of vibration, the foundation should be isolated from floor slabs or building footings at least how many mm around its perimeter",
        "options": [
            "15",
            "20",
            "25",
            "30"
        ],
        "answer": "25"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "The minimum vertical distance from the floor or soil level to the top edge of the foundation must be around ______.",
        "options": [
            "150 mm",
            "100 mm",
            "200 mm",
            "120 mm"
        ],
        "answer": "120 mm"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "For stability, the total combined engine, driven equipment, and foundation center of gravity must be kept ________.",
        "options": [
            "below the foundations top",
            "above the foundations  top",
            "120 mm above the foundations top",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "below the foundations top"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "There shall be no foundation bolts less that ____.",
        "options": [
            "12 mm in diameter",
            "16 mm in diameter",
            "18 mm in diameter",
            "20 mm in diameter"
        ],
        "answer": "12 mm in diameter"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "The weight of steel bar reinforcements should be how many times the weight of the foundation?",
        "options": [
            "1/2% to 1%",
            "1% to 1.5%",
            "2% to 5%",
            "3.2% to 4.2%"
        ],
        "answer": "1/2% to 1%"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "Concrete foundation should have steel bar reinforcements placed vertically and horizontally to avoid ______.",
        "options": [
            "breaking",
            "thermal cracking",
            "melting",
            "vibration"
        ],
        "answer": "thermal cracking"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "Foundations bolt length should be at least how many times the anchor bolt diameter?",
        "options": [
            "16 times",
            "18 times",
            "20 times",
            "30 times"
        ],
        "answer": "18 times"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "Foundation bolts of specified size should be used and surrounded by a pipe sleeve with an inside diameter of at least how many times the diameter of the anchor bolt?",
        "options": [
            "3",
            "4",
            "5",
            "6"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "For a diesel engine's foundation, in pouring a concrete mixture, it should be poured :",
        "options": [
            "one time",
            "two times",
            "three times",
            "four times"
        ],
        "answer": "one time"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "For foundations of steam turbine, the concrete mixture should be ______.",
        "options": [
            "1:2:4",
            "1:3:5",
            "1:3:4",
            "1:2:4"
        ],
        "answer": "1:2:4"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "The steam turbine foundation should be designed to support the machine load plus how many percent for impact, condenser load, floor loads and dead loads ?",
        "options": [
            "15",
            "20",
            "25",
            "30"
        ],
        "answer": "25"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "Which of the following draft rely on the stack effect to draw off combustion gases?",
        "options": [
            "natural draft",
            "forced draft",
            "induced draft",
            "balanced draft"
        ],
        "answer": "natural draft"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "Fans located before the furnace that are used to supply air for burning",
        "options": [
            "natural draft",
            "forced draft",
            "induced draft",
            "balanced draft"
        ],
        "answer": "forced draft"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "Forced draft fans are run at relatively high speeds in the range of :",
        "options": [
            "1200 to 1800 rpm",
            "1000 to 1600 rpm",
            "1500 to 2000 rpm",
            "900 to 1500 rpm"
        ],
        "answer": "1200 to 1800 rpm"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "Chimneys that rely on natural draft are sometimes reffered to as",
        "options": [
            "natural chimney",
            "gravity chimney",
            "normal chimney",
            "stack"
        ],
        "answer": "gravity chimney"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "Force draft fans create a positive pressure of :",
        "options": [
            "0.5 to 2.5 kPa",
            "1.0 to 3.0 kPa",
            "2.0 to 4.0 kPa",
            "0.2 to 2.2 kPa"
        ],
        "answer": "0.5 to 2.5 kPa"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "Fans that are used to draw combustion products through the furnace bed, stack and pollution control system by injecting air into the stack after combustion.",
        "options": [
            "natural draft",
            "forced draft",
            "induced draft",
            "balanced draft",
            "natural draft",
            "forced draft",
            "induced draft",
            "balanced draft"
        ],
        "answer": "balanced draft"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "In order to keep combustion products inside the combustion chamber and stack system, balanced draft system may actually operate with a slight",
        "options": [
            "negative pressure",
            "positive pressure",
            "positive and negative pressures",
            "absolute pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "negative pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "The static pressure drop due to friction through the boiler and stack.",
        "options": [
            "draft loss",
            "available draft",
            "stack effect",
            "fan boost"
        ],
        "answer": "draft loss"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "The difference between the theoretical draft loss.",
        "options": [
            "draft loss",
            "available draft",
            "stack effect",
            "fan boost"
        ],
        "answer": "available draft"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "In a balanced system the available draft is:",
        "options": [
            "unity",
            "zero",
            "100",
            "infinite"
        ],
        "answer": "zero"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "The total pressure supplied by the fan at maximum operating conditions.",
        "options": [
            "net rating or fan boost",
            "draft loss",
            "available draft",
            "stack effect"
        ],
        "answer": "net rating or fan boost"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "Generally the higher the chimney",
        "options": [
            "the smaller the stack effect",
            "the greater the stack effect",
            "stack effect is zero",
            "stack effect approaches unity"
        ],
        "answer": "the greater the stack effect"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "Modern stacks are seldom built higher than",
        "options": [
            "60 m",
            "50 m",
            "40 m",
            "30 m"
        ],
        "answer": "60 m"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "Most stacks are built of height less than:",
        "options": [
            "60 m",
            "50 m",
            "40 m",
            "30 m"
        ],
        "answer": "30 m"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "The average flue gas temperature is",
        "options": [
            "the temperature entering the stack",
            "the temperature leaving the stack",
            "the temperature halfway up the stack",
            "the sum of the temperatures"
        ],
        "answer": "the temperature halfway up the stack"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "The coefficient of velocity is approximately",
        "options": [
            "0.30 to 0.50",
            "0.40 to 0.60",
            "0.20 to 0.40",
            "0.50 to 0.70"
        ],
        "answer": "0.30 to 0.50"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "For realistic problems, the achievable stack effect probably should be considered to be:",
        "options": [
            "75% of the ideal",
            "80% of the ideal",
            "equal of the ideal",
            "half of the ideal"
        ],
        "answer": "80% of the ideal"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "Guyed stacks seldom exceed:",
        "options": [
            "1.83 m in diameter",
            "2.83 in diameter",
            "1.45 in diameter",
            "2.45 in diameter"
        ],
        "answer": "1.83 m in diameter"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "The angle between the stack and the guy wire is usually :",
        "options": [
            "30 degrees",
            "45 degrees",
            "60 degrees",
            "75 degrees"
        ],
        "answer": "60 degrees"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "Guyed stacks height seldom exceed",
        "options": [
            "30.48 m",
            "34.80 m",
            "43.80 m",
            "48.30 m"
        ],
        "answer": "30.48 m"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "Foundations should be isolated from floor slabs or building footings by at least how many mm to eliminate transmission of vibration.",
        "options": [
            "25 mm",
            "15 mm",
            "35 mm",
            "45 mm"
        ],
        "answer": "25 mm"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "Concrete foundations should have steel bar reinforcements placed both vertically and horizontally to avoid",
        "options": [
            "vibrations",
            "thermal cracking",
            "breakdown",
            "rupture"
        ],
        "answer": "thermal cracking"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "Foundation bolts of specified size should be used and surrounded by a pipe sleeve with an inside diameter of at least how many times the diameter of the anchor bolt?",
        "options": [
            "3",
            "4",
            "5",
            "6"
        ],
        "answer": "3"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "Foundation bolts of specified size should be used and surrounded by a pipe sleeve with a length of  at least how many times the diameter of the bolt?",
        "options": [
            "18",
            "14",
            "15",
            "16"
        ],
        "answer": "18"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "Foundation should be designed to support the machine load plus how many % for impact, condenser load, floor load, and dead load?",
        "options": [
            "25",
            "34",
            "15",
            "36"
        ],
        "answer": "25"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "In guyed steel stacks, the angle between wires in a set of 3 is:",
        "options": [
            "120 degrees",
            "110 degrees",
            "135 degrees",
            "145 degrees"
        ],
        "answer": "120 degrees"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "Guys are usually applied in how many sets?",
        "options": [
            "1 to 3",
            "2 to 4",
            "3 to 5",
            "4 to 6"
        ],
        "answer": "1 to 3"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "The empirical coefficient e in machine foundation if not given is assumed",
        "options": [
            "0.11",
            "0.25",
            "0.32",
            "0.15"
        ],
        "answer": "0.11"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 16,
        "question": "The term suction units is used with",
        "options": [
            "natural draft",
            "forced draft",
            "induced draft",
            "balanced draft"
        ],
        "answer": "induced draft"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "An instrument used for measuring evaporation, generally that of water, into the atmosphere.",
        "options": [
            "aerometer",
            "atmometer",
            "anemometer",
            "fadometer"
        ],
        "answer": "atmometer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "An instrument for testing the resistance of material to fading when they are exposed to artificial sunlight or ultraviolet light under controlled conditions.",
        "options": [
            "fadometer",
            "fulgurator",
            "odometer",
            "atmometer"
        ],
        "answer": "fadometer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "The type of calorimeter in which the specific heat of a specimen is measured by the quantity of ice it melts is the :",
        "options": [
            "ice calorimeter",
            "heat calorimeter",
            "vapor calorimeter",
            "hysometer"
        ],
        "answer": "ice calorimeter"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "An instrument used for determination of the boiling point of water for estimating the altitude above sea level from its known variation with atmospheric pressure.",
        "options": [
            "vapor calorimeter",
            "hysometer",
            "boiler",
            "vapor bomb"
        ],
        "answer": "hysometer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "A unit of work or energy equal to 107 ergs. It is equivalent to the work done by a force of one Newton acting through a distance of one meter.",
        "options": [
            "Btu",
            "Calorie",
            "Joule",
            "Watt"
        ],
        "answer": "Joule"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "An elegtromagnetic device for separating isotopes by electrical sorting of their ions.",
        "options": [
            "ion sorter",
            "isotopes sorter",
            "isotron",
            "jolly balance"
        ],
        "answer": "isotron"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "A device used for the determination of the specific gravity of a substance by weighing it in air and in water.",
        "options": [
            "kelvin balance",
            "spring balance",
            "hysometer",
            "jolly balance"
        ],
        "answer": "jolly balance"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "which of the following instruments is NOT used to measure flow rates?",
        "options": [
            "anenometer",
            "rotameter",
            "flowmeter D.velometer"
        ],
        "answer": "D"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "An instrument used to measure the quality of steam is the :",
        "options": [
            "psychometer",
            "gas calorimeter",
            "pyrometer",
            "steam calorimeter"
        ],
        "answer": "steam calorimeter"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "An instrument used to measure the density if gases is known as:",
        "options": [
            "aerovane",
            "aerometer",
            "hygrometer",
            "atmometer"
        ],
        "answer": "aerovane"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "Which of the following is the apparatus used for mixing air with other fluids?",
        "options": [
            "carburetor",
            "dehydrator",
            "gas mixer",
            "aerotor"
        ],
        "answer": "aerotor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "A device that supplies air to an air - injection system is called :",
        "options": [
            "air pump",
            "air nozzle",
            "gas scrubber",
            "air injector"
        ],
        "answer": "air nozzle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "An intrument used for measuring pressure, flow velocity an discharge  rate of a fluid flowing in a conduit.",
        "options": [
            "kampometer",
            "flowmeter",
            "pitot tube",
            "katharometer"
        ],
        "answer": "flowmeter"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "An instrument used for measuring radiant energy especially in the thermal region.",
        "options": [
            "kampometer",
            "luxmeter",
            "kapnometer",
            "katharometer"
        ],
        "answer": "kampometer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "An instrument for the determination of the composition of the gas mixture by measuring variations in the thermal conductivity.",
        "options": [
            "kampometer",
            "atmometer",
            "kapnometer",
            "katharometer"
        ],
        "answer": "katharometer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "An apparatus used for measuring the surface tension  of a liquid by recording the force necessary to detach a metal ring from the surface.",
        "options": [
            "tachometer",
            "tensionmeter",
            "odometer",
            "telemeter"
        ],
        "answer": "tensionmeter"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "An instrument used for measuring  various quantities at a distance.",
        "options": [
            "tachometer",
            "odometer",
            "DME",
            "telemeter"
        ],
        "answer": "telemeter"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "An apparatus used for determination of the transition point by measuring the temperature at which the  vapor pressure of the two modifications become equal.",
        "options": [
            "tensionmeter",
            "tensimeter",
            "tachometer",
            "bourdon gauge"
        ],
        "answer": "tensimeter"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "An instrument for measuring the revolutions per minute of a rotating shaft.",
        "options": [
            "tachometer",
            "odometer",
            "all of the choices",
            "speedometer"
        ],
        "answer": "tachometer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "A device used for demonstrating  the extreme force exerted by water when it freezes is called:",
        "options": [
            "ice calorimeter",
            "hysometer",
            "ice bomb",
            "freezer"
        ],
        "answer": "ice bomb"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "A device to measure vertical distances or displacements?",
        "options": [
            "kampometer",
            "kapnometer",
            "altimeter",
            "cathetometer"
        ],
        "answer": "cathetometer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "A precision instrument for measuring very short time intervals.",
        "options": [
            "clinometer",
            "chronoscope",
            "stop watch",
            "decremeter"
        ],
        "answer": "chronoscope"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "Which of the following is a laboratory method for the determination of the  boiling range of petroleum?",
        "options": [
            "jolly balance",
            "kelvin balance",
            "engler distillation",
            "fractional distillation"
        ],
        "answer": "engler distillation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "An instrument used to measure the humidity in the air.",
        "options": [
            "hygrometer",
            "hydrometer",
            "pressure gage",
            "wind vane"
        ],
        "answer": "hygrometer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "An instrument used to measure the specific gravity or relative density of liquids.",
        "options": [
            "hygrometer",
            "hydrometer",
            "u-tube",
            "manometer"
        ],
        "answer": "hydrometer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "An apparatus used for the determination of the concentration of solid or liquid particles dispersed in a gas, such as the density of smoke or fog.",
        "options": [
            "kampometer",
            "atmometer",
            "kapnometer",
            "katharometer"
        ],
        "answer": "kapnometer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "Hydrometer is used to find out:",
        "options": [
            "specific gravity of liquids",
            "specific gravity of solids",
            "specific gravity of gases",
            "relative humidity"
        ],
        "answer": "specific gravity of liquids"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "What is the clockwork operated device which records continuously the humidity of the atmosphere?",
        "options": [
            "hetograph",
            "hygrometer",
            "hygrodeik",
            "hyrograph"
        ],
        "answer": "hyrograph"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "A device whose function is to pass an information in an unchanged form or in some modified form.",
        "options": [
            "relay",
            "sensor",
            "transmitter D.transducer"
        ],
        "answer": "relay"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "A general term for a device that receives information in the form of one or more physical quantities, modifies the information and or its form if required and produces a resultant output signal.",
        "options": [
            "converter",
            "transducer",
            "sensor",
            "scanner"
        ],
        "answer": "transducer"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "An engine indicator is generally used to measure what?",
        "options": [
            "steam temperature",
            "heat loss",
            "steam cylinder pressure",
            "gauge reading errors"
        ],
        "answer": "steam cylinder pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "In the processing section, there is an instrument frequently used to measure the flow rate of fluids. what is the instrument consisting  of a vertical passage with variable  cross-sectional area,  float and a calibrated scale?",
        "options": [
            "rotameter",
            "pitot tube",
            "rota aire",
            "manometer"
        ],
        "answer": "rotameter"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "What is the function of a steam separator?",
        "options": [
            "trapping the steam and letting water through",
            "throttling",
            "changing direction of the steam flow",
            "steam metering"
        ],
        "answer": "trapping the steam and letting water through"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "A salimeter reads what?",
        "options": [
            "density of brine",
            "dew point temperature",
            "rate of brine",
            "relative humidity"
        ],
        "answer": "density of brine"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "Which of the following measures the density of salt in the water?",
        "options": [
            "salimeter",
            "pitot tube",
            "hydrometer",
            "odometer"
        ],
        "answer": "salimeter"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 17,
        "question": "Ebb current refers to:",
        "options": [
            "eddy current BASIC EE",
            "the movement of the tidal current away from the shore or down the tidal stream",
            "the removal by screen of undesirable fine materials from broken ore",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "none of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "In power station practice ''spinning reverse'' is",
        "options": [
            "reverse generating capacity that is in operation but ot in service",
            "reverse generating capacity that is connected to bus and ready to take load",
            "reverse generating capacity that is available for service but not in operation",
            "capacity of the part of plant remains under maintenance"
        ],
        "answer": "reverse generating capacity that is connected to bus and ready to take load"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "Turn around efficiency of battery energy storage system is about",
        "options": [
            "75%",
            "40%",
            "25%",
            "80%"
        ],
        "answer": "75%"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "Most of the generators in thermal power plants run at :",
        "options": [
            "15000 rpm",
            "1500 rpm",
            "700 rpm",
            "3000 rpm"
        ],
        "answer": "1500 rpm"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "The power supplied to domestic consumers is at 220 volts. This represents:",
        "options": [
            "mean value of voltage",
            "seak value of voltage",
            "RMS value of voltage",
            "none of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "RMS value of voltage"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "The conductors that are used for transmitting bulk of power at high voltage are which of the following type?",
        "options": [
            "cadmium copper",
            "galvanized steel",
            "any of the above",
            "copper"
        ],
        "answer": "copper"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "When the conductor is suspended between two supports at the same level its shape becomes",
        "options": [
            "catenary",
            "cycloid",
            "semi circle",
            "parabola"
        ],
        "answer": "catenary"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "Sag is provided in overheated transmission lines so that:",
        "options": [
            "repairs can be carried out easily",
            "corona can be reduced",
            "skin effect can be reduced",
            "safe tension is not exceeded"
        ],
        "answer": "safe tension is not exceeded"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "The string efficiency in an AC system is",
        "options": [
            "50.75%",
            "100%",
            "25.50%",
            "70.7%"
        ],
        "answer": "70.7%"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "Satellites are powered by:",
        "options": [
            "solar cells",
            "thermo-electric generators",
            "thermionic converters",
            "photo-electric cells"
        ],
        "answer": "solar cells"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "A ship is powered by :",
        "options": [
            "steam turbine",
            "diesel engine",
            "steam turbines or diesel engine",
            "steam turbines, diesel engine, hydraulic turbines or nuclear reactors"
        ],
        "answer": "steam turbines or diesel engine"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "Which of the following plant is suitable for peak load?",
        "options": [
            "diesel engine plant",
            "steam power plant",
            "nuclear power plant",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "diesel engine plant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "The term 'critical' is associated with power plant of the type:",
        "options": [
            "steam power plant",
            "diesel engine power plant",
            "hydro-electric power plant",
            "nuclear power plant"
        ],
        "answer": "nuclear power plant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "A turbo charger is a part of a:",
        "options": [
            "thermal power plant",
            "diesel engine power plant",
            "hydro-electric power plant",
            "nuclear power plant"
        ],
        "answer": "diesel engine power plant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "Which of the following plant has least pollution problem?",
        "options": [
            "steam power plant",
            "gas turbine power plant",
            "nuclear power plant",
            "hydro-electric power plant"
        ],
        "answer": "hydro-electric power plant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "Which of the following power plant can be installed within the shortest time?",
        "options": [
            "nuclear power plant",
            "hydro-electric power plant",
            "gas turbine power plant",
            "diesel engine power plant"
        ],
        "answer": "diesel engine power plant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "Which of the following item consumes least power?",
        "options": [
            "toaster",
            "desert cooler",
            "electric shaver",
            "electric iron"
        ],
        "answer": "electric shaver"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "Which of the following  needs highest level of illumination?",
        "options": [
            "proof reading",
            "hospital wards",
            "railway platforms",
            "foyer for cinema halls"
        ],
        "answer": "proof reading"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "The lamp that is used for cinema projection is a:",
        "options": [
            "frosted GLS lamp",
            "nitrogen filled GLS lamp",
            "mercury vapor lamp",
            "carbon arc lamp"
        ],
        "answer": "carbon arc lamp"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "In  flourescent tube circuit, choke acts as a",
        "options": [
            "a starter",
            "a device for improving the power factor",
            "a current limiting device",
            "a source of heat"
        ],
        "answer": "a device for improving the power factor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "Transient disturbances are due to:",
        "options": [
            "switching operations",
            "load variations",
            "faults",
            "any of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "any of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "Bottoming cycle is quite common in:",
        "options": [
            "cement plants",
            "sugar mills",
            "paper mills",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "cement plants"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "Which of the following is the most highly developed device for confining plasma with magnetic field?",
        "options": [
            "tokamak",
            "tomahawk",
            "breeder reactor",
            "cyclotron"
        ],
        "answer": "tokamak"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "Fuses and circuit breakers do not protect electric motors from :",
        "options": [
            "short circuiting",
            "motor burnout",
            "overload",
            "overheating"
        ],
        "answer": "overheating"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "Corona generally results in:",
        "options": [
            "violet glow",
            "hissing noise",
            "production of ozone gas",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "all of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "Which of the following affects corona?",
        "options": [
            "conductor size",
            "spacing between conductors",
            "line voltage",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "all of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "The statement that the product of the error in the  measured determination of a particle's position and its momentum is of the order of Plank's constant \"h\" is known as",
        "options": [
            "Bohr's theory",
            "D'Alembert's paradox",
            "The Heisenberg uncertainty principle",
            "Planck's law"
        ],
        "answer": "The Heisenberg uncertainty principle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "The phenomenon of physical adhesion of molecules of the surfaces of solids without chemical reaction is",
        "options": [
            "dredging",
            "absorption",
            "coking",
            "liquation"
        ],
        "answer": "absorption"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "Fuses and circuit breaker do not protect electric motors from:",
        "options": [
            "short circuiting",
            "motor burnout",
            "overload",
            "overheating"
        ],
        "answer": "overheating"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "In which of the following systems where Betz law is widely used?",
        "options": [
            "MHD systems",
            "solar cells",
            "geothermal power plants",
            "wind mills"
        ],
        "answer": "wind mills"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "At what rpm  where most of the generator in thermal power plants run?",
        "options": [
            "15000 rpm",
            "1500 rpm",
            "750 rpm",
            "3000"
        ],
        "answer": "1500 rpm"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "Turnaround efficiency of the battery energy storage system is about",
        "options": [
            "75%",
            "40%",
            "25%",
            "80%"
        ],
        "answer": "75%"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "The conductors that are used for transmitting bulk  of power at high voltage are of which of the following type?",
        "options": [
            "cadmium copper",
            "galvanized steel",
            "any of the above",
            "copper"
        ],
        "answer": "copper"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "Corona generally results in",
        "options": [
            "violet glow",
            "hissing noise",
            "production of ozone gas",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "all of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "Which of the following affects corona?",
        "options": [
            "coductor size",
            "spacing between conductors",
            "line voltage",
            "all of the above"
        ],
        "answer": "all of the above"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "When a conductor is suspended between two supports at the same  level its shape becomes",
        "options": [
            "catenary",
            "cycloid",
            "semicircle",
            "parabola"
        ],
        "answer": "catenary"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "What is the unit of electromagnetic wave frequency?",
        "options": [
            "volts",
            "horsepower",
            "hertz",
            "knot"
        ],
        "answer": "hertz"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 18,
        "question": "Past Board Question LATEST BOARD EXAM QUESTIONS A pump with capacity Q1 and head H1 series with another pump with capacity Q2 and head H2. What is the head developed if Q2 is less than Q1?",
        "options": [
            "2 H2 H1",
            "H2 + H1",
            "H2 / H1",
            "H2H1"
        ],
        "answer": "H2 + H1"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question At ordinary temperature what substance will behave as inert gas and will not react in the combustion process?",
        "options": [
            "nitrogen",
            "sulfur",
            "hydrogen",
            "carbon"
        ],
        "answer": "nitrogen"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question Which of the following cycles is ideal for spark-ignition reciprocating engine?",
        "options": [
            "Diesel cycle",
            "Dual cycle",
            "Rankine Cycle",
            "Otto cycle"
        ],
        "answer": "Otto cycle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question What is the relative humidity when the dew point and dry bulb temperature are equal?",
        "options": [
            "110 %",
            "O %",
            "100 %",
            "50%"
        ],
        "answer": "100 %"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question Reheating process is normally employed in steam plane when:",
        "options": [
            "there is excess steam",
            "subcooling is required",
            "turbine undergoes excessive moisture",
            "dehumidifying is required"
        ],
        "answer": "turbine undergoes excessive moisture"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question Where does the final removal of water vapor In an absorption refrigeration system occur?",
        "options": [
            "analyzer",
            "generator",
            "condenser",
            "rectifier",
            "increase",
            "remain constant",
            "decrease",
            "zero"
        ],
        "answer": "increase"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question What is the temperature of lubricant at which it will ignite thus limit its application?",
        "options": [
            "cold point",
            "burning point",
            "flash point",
            "use point"
        ],
        "answer": "flash point"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question What is the heat that is removed from the space to be cooled, which is the same as the heat absorbed by the cooling coils?",
        "options": [
            "heating capacity",
            "enthalpy",
            "work compression",
            "refrigerating effect"
        ],
        "answer": "refrigerating effect"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question An air conditioning system In Wthh water is chilled or cooled and which passes the evaporator coils.",
        "options": [
            "chilled water system",
            "direct expansion",
            "absorption",
            "water circulation system"
        ],
        "answer": "chilled water system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question A multi-stage refrigeration system which is realizable in using different refrigerants.",
        "options": [
            "direct",
            "cascade",
            "flooded",
            "vapor"
        ],
        "answer": "cascade"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question Very large pipe diameter means a thicker wall and high cost. It also means",
        "options": [
            "zero pressure drop",
            "high pressure drop",
            "constant temperature",
            "low pressure drop"
        ],
        "answer": "high pressure drop"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question Aside from maintaining appropriate temperature for food cold storage, how is desiccation minimized or decreased?",
        "options": [
            "low oxygen",
            "maintain humidity ratio",
            "low air circulation",
            "increase humidity ratio"
        ],
        "answer": "maintain humidity ratio"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question During combustion process, only limited air is supplied and not enough to supply two molecule of oxygen per one molecule of carbon, then the product is:",
        "options": [
            "hydration",
            "carbon monoxide",
            "carbonic acid",
            "carbon dioxide"
        ],
        "answer": "carbon monoxide"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question As far as combustion chamber design is considered, the maximum power output of a given engine can be increased by:",
        "options": [
            "increasing combustion time",
            "increasing combustion chamber volume",
            "decreasing combustion chamber volume",
            "providing small values"
        ],
        "answer": "decreasing combustion chamber volume"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question A water conservation device which employs both air and water is condensed a condenser and cooling tower combined into one is called:",
        "options": [
            "shell and tube condenser",
            "air-cooled condenser",
            "water-cooled condenser",
            "evaporative condenser"
        ],
        "answer": "evaporative condenser"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question lnorder to perform efficiently, a power cycle must be communicated with the outside temperature of its surroundings and into one is called;",
        "options": [
            "Kirchoff's Law",
            "Second Law of Thermodynamics",
            "Kelvin-Planck Law",
            "First Law of Thermodynamics"
        ],
        "answer": "Second Law of Thermodynamics"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question Water is heated in a container. lt eXpands and becomes less dense and lighter. lt rises up the container because of its reduced density and replaced by cooler air. As this process continues, the heat is transferred and disturbed all throughout. What is this mode of heat transfer called?",
        "options": [
            "condenser",
            "radiation",
            "conduction",
            "convection",
            "on the suction line on compressor Iine",
            "in the water inlet",
            "anywhere in the system",
            "in the water outlet"
        ],
        "answer": "in the water outlet"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question When there is no work between the thermodynamic system and its surrounding, the quantity of net heat transfer is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "total energy of an open system",
            "temperature of an open system",
            "temperature of a closed system",
            "total energy of a closed system"
        ],
        "answer": "total energy of a closed system"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question In order to attain equilibrium in the condenser, the cooling tower range must be _____ with respect to temperature rise in the condenser.",
        "options": [
            "greater",
            "equal",
            "less",
            "zero"
        ],
        "answer": "equal"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board question If ice will form in a solution of water and salt, then it is at a temperature called:",
        "options": [
            "dew point",
            "freezing point depression",
            "boiling point depression",
            "critical point"
        ],
        "answer": "freezing point depression"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question The flow of the convergent section of a nozzle is always subsonic. If the flow is subsonic then the mach number is:",
        "options": [
            "greater than unity",
            "less than unity",
            "near than unity",
            "unity"
        ],
        "answer": "less than unity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question One hundred twenty percent theoretical air was supplied for combustion. What is the equivalent excess equal to:",
        "options": [
            "20 %",
            "100 %",
            "240 %",
            "120 %"
        ],
        "answer": "20 %"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question If Pi is the indicated horsepower and Pb is the indicated horsepower of a compressor, then what is mechanical efficiency, Em, equal to:",
        "options": [
            "Em = Pb/Pi",
            "Em = Pi/Pb",
            "Em = Pb-Pi",
            "Em = Pi-Pb"
        ],
        "answer": "Em = Pi/Pb"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question What is the least number of compressor a multistage system that will use?",
        "options": [
            "three",
            "two",
            "four",
            "one"
        ],
        "answer": "two"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question The relation between the Fahrenheit absolute scale and the Celsius absolute scale is:",
        "options": [
            "R= 1.8 °K",
            "R=32 °K",
            "R=3.2 °K",
            "R= 18 °K"
        ],
        "answer": "R= 1.8 °K"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question The sum of the internal energy and the product of pressure and specific volume is known as the:",
        "options": [
            "enthalpy",
            "entropy",
            "total work",
            "total internal energy"
        ],
        "answer": "enthalpy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question A refrigeration control that guards the compressor form overloads brought about by abruptly increases loads resulting from defrosting, warm products and others, is called:",
        "options": [
            "safety valve",
            "suction hold-back valve",
            "solenoid valve",
            "expansion valve"
        ],
        "answer": "suction hold-back valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question What does fossil-fuel fired power plants release, which in turn produces the key ingredient in acid rain?",
        "options": [
            "nitrogen",
            "sulfur emission",
            "carbon monoxide",
            "carbon dioxide"
        ],
        "answer": "sulfur emission"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question The fraction of the radiation energy incident on a surface which is absorbed by the surface is called:",
        "options": [
            "Convection",
            "Absorptivity",
            "Emission",
            "Radiation"
        ],
        "answer": "Absorptivity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question Which of the following power plants uses energy from uranium to produce electric power?",
        "options": [
            "Diesel Plant",
            "Geothermal Plant",
            "Nuclear Plant",
            "Hydroelectric Plant i"
        ],
        "answer": "Nuclear Plant"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question Ice cubes added to a glass of water and stirred. Moisture starts to form on the outer surface of the glass. At his point. what is the temperature at the outer surface called?",
        "options": [
            "critical temperature",
            "surface temperature",
            "dew point temperature",
            "saturation temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "dew point temperature"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question The force when applied to a mass of one kilogram will give mass an acceleration of one meter per second for every second called:",
        "options": [
            "Watt",
            "Joule",
            "Newton",
            "Pascal"
        ],
        "answer": "Newton"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question The kinetic energy of a moving fluid is used to isentropically compressed the fluid to state of zero velocity. The temperature ofa moving fluid at the state zero velocity is called:",
        "options": [
            "stagnation temperature",
            "partial temperature",
            "critical temperature",
            "absolute temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "stagnation temperature"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question The dew point temperature of the product of combustion in the saturation temperature that corresponds to the partial pressure of the ____ in the products.",
        "options": [
            "SO2",
            "H2O",
            "N2",
            "CO2"
        ],
        "answer": "H2O"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question What do we call a devrce that is used to boiler operation that will stop the burner or at least send a signal to the operator if the water drops to a low level that is no longer safe?",
        "options": [
            "safety valve",
            "dead - weight valve",
            "high water cut off",
            "low water out off"
        ],
        "answer": "low water out off"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question Dry analysis is a fractional analysis of the products of combustion which does not include:",
        "options": [
            "water vapor",
            "carbon dioxide",
            "sulfur dioxide",
            "carbon monoxide"
        ],
        "answer": "water vapor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question The size of a reciprocating pump is stamped on the builder's plate 3\" x 4\" x 6'. The diameter of the liquid cylinder is:",
        "options": [
            "5\"",
            "6\"",
            "3\"",
            "4\""
        ],
        "answer": "4\""
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question One foot water is equal to:",
        "options": [
            "0.4138Ib/in.2",
            "68.3lb/ft.2",
            "0.8673lb/in.2",
            "62.43lb/ft.2"
        ],
        "answer": "62.43lb/ft.2"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question The freezing point of R - 22 is:",
        "options": [
            "-109 °F",
            "-252 °F",
            "-256 °F",
            "-211 °F"
        ],
        "answer": "-256 °F"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question Which of the following is a type of evaporator?",
        "options": [
            "shell-and-tube- condenser",
            "sell-and-tube-water cooler",
            "oil lantern rings",
            "polyphase motors"
        ],
        "answer": "shell-and-tube- condenser"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question For Brayton cycle. the result of regeneration is:",
        "options": [
            "increase in thermal efficiency",
            "decrease thermal efficiency",
            "moderate thermal efficiency",
            "low thermal efficiency"
        ],
        "answer": "increase in thermal efficiency"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question If the pressure exerted on a liquid is higher than the saturation corresponding to its temperature, the liquid is a:",
        "options": [
            "saturated liquid",
            "subcooled liquid",
            "superheated liquid",
            "highly superheated liquid"
        ],
        "answer": "subcooled liquid"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question In a power driven pump. each piston stroke is displaced by 360° divided the ______.",
        "options": [
            "revolution per minute",
            "bore",
            "length of the stroke",
            "number of cylinders"
        ],
        "answer": "number of cylinders"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question If the air is compressed without discarding heat, then what do you call this kind of compression?",
        "options": [
            "isobaric",
            "isochoric",
            "adiabatic",
            "isothermal"
        ],
        "answer": "adiabatic"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question If a gas posses internal energy, then it is due to its;",
        "options": [
            "velocity",
            "pressure and volume values",
            "height from a certain datum level",
            "molecular motion"
        ],
        "answer": "molecular motion"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question The pressure of ammonia was detected in brine solution. How can ammonia be removed?",
        "options": [
            "freeze the brine solution",
            "heat the brine to a high temperature enough to free the ammonia",
            "throw the brine solution",
            "lower the temperature of the brine"
        ],
        "answer": "heat the brine to a high temperature enough to free the ammonia"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question What will happen when the pressure at any point inside a centrifugal pump goes below the vapor pressure corresponding to the temperature of the liquid?",
        "options": [
            "turbulent flow",
            "laminar flow",
            "cavitation",
            "priming"
        ],
        "answer": "cavitation"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question What does a negative Joule-Thompson coefficient means during a throttling process?",
        "options": [
            "fluid pressure is constant",
            "fluid temperature drop",
            "fluid temperature rises",
            "fluid pressure zero"
        ],
        "answer": "fluid temperature rises"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question For steam power plants, increasing the operating pressure of the boiler will:",
        "options": [
            "increase thermal efficiency",
            "decrease thermal efficiency",
            "bring thermal efficiency to zero",
            "make thermal efficiency constant"
        ],
        "answer": "increase thermal efficiency"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question The ratio of the average load to that of the rated capacity of a plant is called:",
        "options": [
            "output factor",
            "load factor",
            "demand factor",
            "capacity factor"
        ],
        "answer": "capacity factor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question What is the method used to evaluate all welds performed on pressure parts of boiler tube materials?",
        "options": [
            "hydrostatic test",
            "Orsat analysis",
            "vacuum test",
            "radiographic test"
        ],
        "answer": "radiographic test"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question If the pressure is disregarded in the various other components of a steam of gas power plants, the pressure rise in the pump or compressor is _______ to the pressure drop in the turbine.",
        "options": [
            "inversely proportional",
            "constant",
            "equal",
            "varying"
        ],
        "answer": "equal"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question What is the effect on saturated temperature if the pressure of the fluid is decreased?",
        "options": [
            "there is no effect",
            "saturation temperature decreases",
            "saturation temperature remains constant",
            "saturatlon temperature increases"
        ],
        "answer": "saturation temperature decreases"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question lf V3 is the cylinder volume after the combustion process of 8 Diesel cycle and V2 is its cylinder volume before combustion, then calculate the cut-off ratio, r.",
        "options": [
            "r = V3 - V2",
            "r = V2 - V3",
            "r = V2/V3",
            "r = V3/V2"
        ],
        "answer": "r = V3/V2"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question Compare the temperature of discharge vapor refrigerant leaving the compressor for a superheated cycle and the saturated cycle. for the same condensing temperature and pressure. A, there is no difference",
        "options": [
            "higher for the superheated cycle",
            "higher. for the saturated cycle",
            "lower for the Superheated cycle"
        ],
        "answer": "higher for the superheated cycle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question A valve that releases steam from the boiler by opening at a pre-determined pressure in order to keep the steam pressure from rising more than the pressure from which the valve is set is called a",
        "options": [
            "ammonia valve",
            "stop valve",
            "check valve",
            "safety valve"
        ],
        "answer": "safety valve"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question What is the relationship of the capacity of a centrifugal pump, Q, to impeller diameter. D, when there are two impeller diameters in the same pump?",
        "options": [
            "Q is directly proportional to the square of the ratio of D",
            "Q is inversely proportional to the ratio of D",
            "Q is directly proportional to the ratio of D",
            "Q is inversely proportional to the square of the ratio of D"
        ],
        "answer": "Q is directly proportional to the ratio of D"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question If Wt is the turbine shaft work of a gas turbine unit, Wc is its compressor shaft work and Q is the heat supplied in duel, then determine its thermal efficiency.",
        "options": [
            "Q / (Wt 4- Wc)",
            "Q / (Wt + We)",
            "(wt + We) / Q",
            "(Wt - Wc) / Q"
        ],
        "answer": "(Wt - Wc) / Q"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question The schedule number of a pipe, N, indicates the thickness of the pipe wall. If the allowable stress of the pipe is S, then what is the internal pressure equal to?",
        "options": [
            "N-S",
            "N/S",
            "N*S",
            "S/N"
        ],
        "answer": "N*S"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question What is the pressure present inside the casing of an impulse turbine?",
        "options": [
            "vacuum",
            "atmospheric pressure",
            "above atmospheric",
            "zero"
        ],
        "answer": "atmospheric pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question In order to remove the fly ashes from the flue gas, which of the following must a power plant be equipped with?",
        "options": [
            "condenser",
            "demineralizer",
            "electrostatic precipitator",
            "desulphurization plant"
        ],
        "answer": "electrostatic precipitator"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question If Hs is the total suction head of a pump, Hp is its suction surface pressure, and Hf is its suction friction head, then calculate the total suction head. Ht.",
        "options": [
            "Ht=Hs-Hp-Hf",
            "Ht=Hs+Hp-Hf",
            "Ht=Hs+Hp+Hf",
            "Ht=Hs-Hp+Hf"
        ],
        "answer": "Ht=Hs+Hp+Hf"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question The constant spending of certain percentage of circulated water in a cooling tower in order to prevent accumulation of dissolved mineral solids and other impurities in the condenser water is called",
        "options": [
            "approach",
            "drift",
            "range",
            "bleed-off"
        ],
        "answer": "bleed-off"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question What process is employed when the turbine steam power plants experience excessive moisture?",
        "options": [
            "reheating",
            "supercooling",
            "suboooling",
            "freezing"
        ],
        "answer": "reheating"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past board Question A company is interested to produce a water turbine wherein only little energy is required or necessary because the guide vanes are to be controlled. The turbine must be a:",
        "options": [
            "gas turbine",
            "propeller turbine",
            "Kaplan turbine",
            "Francis turbine"
        ],
        "answer": "Kaplan turbine"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question lf Et is the total net energy generated by a plant in a certain period of time and Er is the rated net energy capacity of the plant during the same period of time then what is the plant operating factor?",
        "options": [
            "Er - Et",
            "Et/ Er",
            "Et - Er",
            "Er/ Et"
        ],
        "answer": "Et/ Er"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question If W is the work output of a heat engine and H is the total heat input of an engine. then determine its thermal efficiency, e.",
        "options": [
            "e=H/W",
            "e=W/H",
            "e=WxH",
            "e=I - (W - H)"
        ],
        "answer": "e=W/H"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question Which of the following is converted to mechanical energy by a water.",
        "options": [
            "lnternal energy",
            "kinetic energy",
            "potential energy",
            "hydraulic energy"
        ],
        "answer": "potential energy"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question What must be the value of the available Net PositiVe Suction Head (NPSH) of a centrifugal pump compared to its require NPSH to avoid losing priming?",
        "options": [
            "available NPSH lesser than required NPSH",
            "available NPSH equal than required NPSH",
            "available NPSH greater than required NPSH D.available NPSH constant at all times"
        ],
        "answer": "available NPSH greater than required NPSH"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question What type of fuel is used with stationary power plants where gas is available by pipeline?",
        "options": [
            "gaseous fuels",
            "solid fuels",
            "coal",
            "liquid fuels"
        ],
        "answer": "gaseous fuels"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question Wb is shaft work of an engine and Wi is the indicated work of an engine. If mechanical friction is present in the engine mechanism, then:",
        "options": [
            "Wb is equal to Wi",
            "Wb is less than Wi",
            "Wb is proportional to Wi",
            "Wb is greater then Wi"
        ],
        "answer": "Wb is less than Wi"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question What is the saturation pressure at the critical temperature, or the lowest pressure in which a substance can be in the liquid state at its critical pressure?",
        "options": [
            "external pressure",
            "critical pressure",
            "condensing pressure",
            "evaporation pressure"
        ],
        "answer": "critical pressure"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question What is the significance of a high dielectric strength of lubricating oil?",
        "options": [
            "oil is thick",
            "oil is contaminant-free",
            "oil is thin",
            "oil is not clean"
        ],
        "answer": "oil is contaminant-free"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question Theoretically. what is the effect of the compressor clearance on horsepower?",
        "options": [
            "varies in direct proportion",
            "increase power",
            "decrease power",
            "there is no effect"
        ],
        "answer": "there is no effect"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question Compare the refrigerating effect per unit mass of refrigerant circulated for a superheated cycle that produces useful cooling and a saturated cycle. for the same vaporizing and condensing temperature.",
        "options": [
            "lower for a superheated cycle",
            "greater for a saturated cycle",
            "the same",
            "greater for a superheated cycle"
        ],
        "answer": "greater for a superheated cycle"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question It is important to take some moisture from the air to dehumidify it if the relative humidity reaches high levels. To do this, it requires cooling the air:",
        "options": [
            "at wet-bulb temperature",
            "above its dew point temperature",
            "at critical temperature",
            "below its dew point temperature"
        ],
        "answer": "below its dew point temperature"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question What does enthalpy measure in a substance?",
        "options": [
            "its coldness",
            "its heat content",
            "its humidity",
            "its dew point"
        ],
        "answer": "its heat content"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question Pneumatic tools are powered by:",
        "options": [
            "natural gas",
            "air",
            "electricity",
            "steam"
        ],
        "answer": "air"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question The pump will not cavitate if the available Net Positive Suction Head (NPSH) is:",
        "options": [
            "less than the required NPSH",
            "equal or lesser than the required NPSH",
            "equal or greater than the required NPSH",
            "zero compared to the mquired NPSH of 1"
        ],
        "answer": "equal or greater than the required NPSH"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question A water-tube condenser has a total of 60 tubes. If these are two passes, then compute the number of tube per pass.",
        "options": [
            "6C",
            "15",
            "3C D.2"
        ],
        "answer": "15"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question if Ev is the volumetric efficiency of a reciprocating pump, then determine SLIP which represents all losses of capacity given in percentage of the displacement.",
        "options": [
            "1/Ev",
            "1-1/EV C.1-Ev",
            "Ev+1"
        ],
        "answer": "C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question What is the relationship of the horsepower of a centrifugal pump, Hp, to the impeller speed, S,  if the pump is at two different rotative speeds?",
        "options": [
            "Hp is inversely proportional to the cube of the ratio of S",
            "Hp is directly proportional to the ratio of S",
            "Hp is inversely proportional to the ratio of S",
            "Hp is directly proportional to the cube of the ratio of S"
        ],
        "answer": "Hp is directly proportional to the cube of the ratio of S"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question What is likely to occur when sections of the lmpeller of a centrifugal pump are handling vapor and other sections are handling liquid?",
        "options": [
            "erosion of the pump",
            "high head and low capacity",
            "excessive vibration",
            "complete failure to operate"
        ],
        "answer": "complete failure to operate"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question When vapor compression takes place on one side of the piston and one during one revolution of the crankshaft, then the compressor is :",
        "options": [
            "double-acting",
            "four-cycle",
            "two-revolution",
            "single-acting"
        ],
        "answer": "single-acting"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question ln Stirling and Erickson Cycles, the efficiency can be  increased by:",
        "options": [
            "compressibility",
            "superheating",
            "regeneration",
            "subcooling"
        ],
        "answer": "regeneration"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question Which of the following is used to control refrigeration compressor capacity?",
        "options": [
            "dehumidifier",
            "check valve",
            "solenoid valve",
            "unloader"
        ],
        "answer": "unloader"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question During a cooling and dehumidifying process, sensible and latent heats are removed in the cooling coil. If Hs is the sensible heat and Ht is the total heat transferred. then determine the coil sensible factor.",
        "options": [
            "Ht - Hs",
            "Hs- Ht",
            "Ht/Hs",
            "Hs/ Ht"
        ],
        "answer": "Hs/ Ht"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question Based on PSME code, what should be provided in  each stream outlets if two or more boilers will be connected in parallel?",
        "options": [
            "relief and check valves",
            "non-retum and shut-off valves",
            "expansion and shut-off valves",
            "expansion and check valves"
        ],
        "answer": "non-retum and shut-off valves"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question The diesel cycle is the ideal cycle for a: A, absorption",
        "options": [
            "steam-jet",
            "compression-ignition engine",
            "gas turbine"
        ],
        "answer": "compression-ignition engine"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question If a Carnot cycle is at the same maximum and minimum temperatures as a Rankine cycle. then how would you compare the efficiency of a Rankine cycle to that of the Carnot cycle?",
        "options": [
            "efficiency is the same",
            "higher efficiency",
            "efficiency is the higher .by 30%",
            "lower efficiency"
        ],
        "answer": "lower efficiency"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question Compute the wall gain load of a load storage room when A is the outside surface area of the wall. D is the temperature differential across the wall, and U is the overall coefficient of heat transition.",
        "options": [
            "AU/D",
            "D/N",
            "A/UD",
            "AUD"
        ],
        "answer": "AUD"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question If m is the mass of dry air and H is the specific enthalpy of the water vapor in air and r is the humidity ratio, then determine the latent heat of any dry air.",
        "options": [
            "m/(r-H)",
            "r/(H-m)",
            "(m-r)/H",
            "m(rxH)"
        ],
        "answer": "m(rxH)"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question When an electric motor nameplate indicates a \"100-kw electric motor\"• then what does a 100 kw rating refers to?",
        "options": [
            "thermal energy input",
            "thermal energy output",
            "electrical power output",
            "mechanical power output"
        ],
        "answer": "mechanical power output"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "1/3 H",
        "options": [
            "1/4 H",
            "5H"
        ],
        "answer": "1/4 H"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question The ratio of the average load during a certain time to peak the load occurring during the same period of time is called:",
        "options": [
            "demand factor",
            "capacity factor",
            "load factor",
            "output factor"
        ],
        "answer": "load factor"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question Based on the PSME Code, what should be the effective temperature of the air to be maintained for comfort cooling at an air movement from 0.0761 to 0.127 meter per second?",
        "options": [
            "25 - 29 degrees C",
            "35 - 39 degrees C",
            "20 - 24 degrees C",
            "30 - 34 degrees C"
        ],
        "answer": "20 - 24 degrees C"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question If R is the delivery rate of a pump. H is the total pumping head and e is the efficiency of the pump, then compute the power required to drive the pump.",
        "options": [
            "R/H x e",
            "1 - (R+H)/e",
            "(RxH)/e",
            "(h - R)/e"
        ],
        "answer": "(RxH)/e"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question There are three basic boiler types, namely:",
        "options": [
            "water-tube, horizontal tube and cast-iron boilers",
            "cast-iron. fire-tube and water tube boilers",
            "fire-tube, cast-steel nad water tube boilers",
            "HRT, fire-tube and Marine Boilers"
        ],
        "answer": "cast-iron. fire-tube and water tube boilers"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question The amount of heat necessary to bring up the temperature of a unit mass of a substance through a unit degree is called:",
        "options": [
            "specific volume",
            "thermal heat",
            "total heat",
            "specific heat"
        ],
        "answer": "specific heat"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question What is the specific gravity of an oil which has a baume reading g of 28 degrees F?",
        "options": [
            "0.215",
            "0.562",
            "0.886",
            "0.774"
        ],
        "answer": "0.886"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question If C is the capacity of the compressor in a refrigeration system and F is the heat rejection factor, then calculate the condenser load, L.",
        "options": [
            "L = F - C",
            "L = F / C",
            "L = C x F",
            "L = C / F"
        ],
        "answer": "L = C x F"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question Based on the PSME Code, what should be the humidity of air to be used for comfort cooling?",
        "options": [
            "75% - 80% relative humidity",
            "50% - 60% relative humidity",
            "60% - 70% relative humidity",
            "70% - 75% relative humidity"
        ],
        "answer": "50% - 60% relative humidity"
    },
    {
        "chapter": 19,
        "question": "Past Board Question What is the cause of pressure drop in the boiler, condenser and the pipings between different Components?  Because of this drop, steam leaving the boiler is at a lower pressure.",
        "options": [
            "positive slip",
            "fluid friction",
            "negative slip",
            "low thermal efficiency"
        ],
        "answer": "fluid friction"
    }
]